<!DOCTYPE frameset SYSTEM "frameset.dtd">
<frameset>
<predicate lemma="amend">
<note>
  Frames file for 'amend' based on sentences in financial subcorpus.
  No Verbnet entry, no Framenet entry.
</note>

<roleset id="amend.01" name="add to or correct">
<roles>
  <role descr="amender, corrector" n="0"/>
  <role descr="thing amended" n="1"/>
  <role descr="secondary predication on arg1" n="2"/>
</roles>

<example name="just transitive">
<inflection aspect="ns" form="full" person="ns" tense="past" voice="active"/>
<text>
    The company said it amended its shareholder rights plan by
    reducing to 10% from 20% the level of ownership by an outsider
    that would trigger the issuance to other holders of rights to buy
    additional shares of Nashua common at half price. 
</text>
        <arg n="0">it</arg>
        <rel>amended</rel>
        <arg n="1">its shareholder rights plan</arg>
        <arg f="MNR" n="M">by reducing to 10% from 20% the level of
        ownership by an outsider that would trigger the issuance to
        other holders of rights to buy additional shares of Nashua
        common at half price</arg> 
</example>

<note>
It's possible that the MNR above should be regarded as an instrument
and therefore take a numbered argument (arg3, probably), but I don't
think an instrument/&quot;amendment&quot; will actually occur all that often,
and it actually sounds a little weird to me.  We'll see.
</note>

<example name="with secondary predication">
<inflection aspect="ns" form="full" person="ns" tense="past" voice="active"/>
<text>
    PS of New Hampshire amended its plan to call for two years of 5.5%
    rate increases followed by five years of 4.5% increases. 
</text>
        <arg n="0">PS of New Hampshire</arg>
        <rel>amended</rel>
        <arg n="1">its plan</arg>
        <arg n="2">to call for two years of 5.5% rate
        increases followed by five years of 4.5% increases</arg> 
</example>

<note>
I read the latter sentence as the plan now calls for such-and-such
increases, not that PS amended its plan in order to call for the
increases.  It's subtle.
</note>

</roleset>
</predicate>
</frameset>
