<!DOCTYPE frameset SYSTEM "frameset.dtd">
<frameset>
<predicate lemma="wonder">
<note>
  Frames file for 'wonder' based on sentences in financial subcorpus.
  Verbnet entry 31.3, other framed members include fear react and
  wallow.  OK, that makes sense.  Comparison with those and with
  'think'. 
</note>

<roleset id="wonder.01" name="think about, ponder" vncls="31.3">
<roles>
  <role descr="thinker" n="0"><vnrole vncls="31.3" vntheta="Experiencer"/></role>
  <role descr="thought" n="1"><vnrole vncls="31.3" vntheta="Cause"/></role>
</roles>

<example name="very typical">
<inflection aspect="ns" form="full" person="ns" tense="present" voice="active"/>
<text>
    At the same time, the sheer size of the loss, coupled with a
    slowing of orders, made some securities analysts wonder just how
    strong that turnaround will be at the computer maker and
    defense-electronics concern. 
</text>
        <arg n="0">some securities analysts</arg>
        <rel>wonder</rel>
        <arg n="1">just how strong that turnaround will be  at the
        computer maker and defense-electronics concern</arg> 
</example>

<note>
Unlike verbs of saying, and other verbs of thinking, &quot;wonder&quot; MUST
take an SBAR introduced by a WH-word or -phrase.  Therefore, arg1 will
take the entire SBAR, not just the S.
</note>

<example name="with a PP instead">
<inflection aspect="ns" form="full" person="ns" tense="present" voice="active"/>
<text>
    Not everyone is reacting so calmly, however, and many wonder about
    the long-term implications of what is widely viewed as the cause
    of Friday's slide, reluctance by banks to provide financing for a
    buy-out of UAL Corp., parent of United Airlines. 
</text>
        <arg n="0">many</arg>
        <rel>wonder</rel>
        <arg f="about" n="1">the long-term implications of what  is
        widely viewed  as the cause of Friday's slide , reluctance  by
        banks  to provide financing for a buy-out of UAL Corp.,
        parent of United Airlines</arg> 
</example>

</roleset>

<roleset id="wonder.02" name="experience a sense of wonder">
<roles>
  <role descr="experiencer" n="0"/>
  <role descr="wonder at what?" n="1"/>
</roles>

<example name="poor John">
  <inflection aspect="ns" form="full" person="ns" tense="past" voice="active"/>
  <text>
    John wondered at the display of unreasoning hatred directed at
    him from all the other kids.
  </text>
  <arg n="0">John</arg>
  <rel>wondered</rel>
  <arg f="at" n="1">the display of unreasoning hatred directed at
    him from all the other kids</arg>
</example>

<note>
</note>

</roleset>
</predicate>
</frameset>
