<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="shakes.css"?>
<!-- <!DOCTYPE PLAY SYSTEM "play.dtd"> -->

<PLAY>
<TITLE>The Tragedy of Julius Caesar</TITLE>

<!--

<P>Text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</P>
<P>XML markup by Jon Bosak, 1996-1998.</P>
<P>XML Styling done by Ajay Juneja, 1999.<P>
<P>This work may be freely copied and distributed worldwide.</P>

-->

<PERSONAE>
<TITLE>Dramatis Personae</TITLE>

<PERSONA>JULIUS CAESAR</PERSONA>

<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>OCTAVIUS CAESAR</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>MARCUS ANTONIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>M. AEMILIUS LEPIDUS</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>triumvirs after death of Julius Caesar.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>


<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>CICERO</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>PUBLIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>POPILIUS LENA</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>senators.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>


<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>MARCUS BRUTUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CASSIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CASCA</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>TREBONIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>LIGARIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>DECIUS BRUTUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>METELLUS CIMBER</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CINNA</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>conspirators against Julius Caesar.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>


<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>FLAVIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>MARULLUS</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>tribunes.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>

<PERSONA>ARTEMIDORUS Of Cnidos, a teacher of rhetoric. </PERSONA>
<PERSONA>A Soothsayer</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CINNA, a poet. </PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Another Poet</PERSONA>

<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>LUCILIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>TITINIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>MESSALA</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Young CATO</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>VOLUMNIUS</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>friends to Brutus and Cassius.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>


<PGROUP>
<PERSONA>VARRO</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CLITUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CLAUDIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>STRATO</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>LUCIUS</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>DARDANIUS</PERSONA>
<GRPDESCR>servants to Brutus.</GRPDESCR>
</PGROUP>

<PERSONA>PINDARUS, servant to Cassius.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CALPURNIA, wife to Caesar.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>PORTIA, wife to Brutus.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Senators, Citizens, Guards, Attendants, &amp;c.</PERSONA>
</PERSONAE>

<SCNDESCR>SCENE  Rome: the neighbourhood of Sardis: the neighbourhood of Philippi.</SCNDESCR>

<PLAYSUBT>JULIUS CAESAR</PLAYSUBT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT I</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter FLAVIUS, MARULLUS, and certain Commoners</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hence! home, you idle creatures get you home:</LINE>
<LINE>Is this a holiday? what! know you not,</LINE>
<LINE>Being mechanical, you ought not walk</LINE>
<LINE>Upon a labouring day without the sign</LINE>
<LINE>Of your profession? Speak, what trade art thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Commoner</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, sir, a carpenter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARULLUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is thy leather apron and thy rule?</LINE>
<LINE>What dost thou with thy best apparel on?</LINE>
<LINE>You, sir, what trade are you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Commoner</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, sir, in respect of a fine workman, I am but,</LINE>
<LINE>as you would say, a cobbler.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARULLUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But what trade art thou? answer me directly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Commoner</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A trade, sir, that, I hope, I may use with a safe</LINE>
<LINE>conscience; which is, indeed, sir, a mender of bad soles.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARULLUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What trade, thou knave? thou naughty knave, what trade?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Commoner</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I beseech you, sir, be not out with me: yet,</LINE>
<LINE>if you be out, sir, I can mend you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARULLUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What meanest thou by that? mend me, thou saucy fellow!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Commoner</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, sir, cobble you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art a cobbler, art thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Commoner</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, sir, all that I live by is with the awl: I</LINE>
<LINE>meddle with no tradesman's matters, nor women's</LINE>
<LINE>matters, but with awl. I am, indeed, sir, a surgeon</LINE>
<LINE>to old shoes; when they are in great danger, I</LINE>
<LINE>recover them. As proper men as ever trod upon</LINE>
<LINE>neat's leather have gone upon my handiwork.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But wherefore art not in thy shop today?</LINE>
<LINE>Why dost thou lead these men about the streets?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Commoner</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, sir, to wear out their shoes, to get myself</LINE>
<LINE>into more work. But, indeed, sir, we make holiday,</LINE>
<LINE>to see Caesar and to rejoice in his triumph.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARULLUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wherefore rejoice? What conquest brings he home?</LINE>
<LINE>What tributaries follow him to Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>To grace in captive bonds his chariot-wheels?</LINE>
<LINE>You blocks, you stones, you worse than senseless things!</LINE>
<LINE>O you hard hearts, you cruel men of Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>Knew you not Pompey? Many a time and oft</LINE>
<LINE>Have you climb'd up to walls and battlements,</LINE>
<LINE>To towers and windows, yea, to chimney-tops,</LINE>
<LINE>Your infants in your arms, and there have sat</LINE>
<LINE>The livelong day, with patient expectation,</LINE>
<LINE>To see great Pompey pass the streets of Rome:</LINE>
<LINE>And when you saw his chariot but appear,</LINE>
<LINE>Have you not made an universal shout,</LINE>
<LINE>That Tiber trembled underneath her banks,</LINE>
<LINE>To hear the replication of your sounds</LINE>
<LINE>Made in her concave shores?</LINE>
<LINE>And do you now put on your best attire?</LINE>
<LINE>And do you now cull out a holiday?</LINE>
<LINE>And do you now strew flowers in his way</LINE>
<LINE>That comes in triumph over Pompey's blood? Be gone!</LINE>
<LINE>Run to your houses, fall upon your knees,</LINE>
<LINE>Pray to the gods to intermit the plague</LINE>
<LINE>That needs must light on this ingratitude.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, go, good countrymen, and, for this fault,</LINE>
<LINE>Assemble all the poor men of your sort;</LINE>
<LINE>Draw them to Tiber banks, and weep your tears</LINE>
<LINE>Into the channel, till the lowest stream</LINE>
<LINE>Do kiss the most exalted shores of all.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt all the Commoners</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>See whether their basest metal be not moved;</LINE>
<LINE>They vanish tongue-tied in their guiltiness.</LINE>
<LINE>Go you down that way towards the Capitol;</LINE>
<LINE>This way will I disrobe the images,</LINE>
<LINE>If you do find them deck'd with ceremonies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MARULLUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May we do so?</LINE>
<LINE>You know it is the feast of Lupercal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>FLAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is no matter; let no images</LINE>
<LINE>Be hung with Caesar's trophies. I'll about,</LINE>
<LINE>And drive away the vulgar from the streets:</LINE>
<LINE>So do you too, where you perceive them thick.</LINE>
<LINE>These growing feathers pluck'd from Caesar's wing</LINE>
<LINE>Will make him fly an ordinary pitch,</LINE>
<LINE>Who else would soar above the view of men</LINE>
<LINE>And keep us all in servile fearfulness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  A public place.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Flourish. Enter CAESAR; ANTONY, for the course;
CALPURNIA, PORTIA, DECIUS BRUTUS, CICERO, BRUTUS,
CASSIUS, and CASCA; a great crowd following, among
them a Soothsayer</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Calpurnia!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, ho! Caesar speaks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Calpurnia!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CALPURNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand you directly in Antonius' way,</LINE>
<LINE>When he doth run his course. Antonius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Forget not, in your speed, Antonius,</LINE>
<LINE>To touch Calpurnia; for our elders say,</LINE>
<LINE>The barren, touched in this holy chase,</LINE>
<LINE>Shake off their sterile curse.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall remember:</LINE>
<LINE>When Caesar says 'do this,' it is perform'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Set on; and leave no ceremony out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Flourish</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! who calls?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bid every noise be still: peace yet again!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who is it in the press that calls on me?</LINE>
<LINE>I hear a tongue, shriller than all the music,</LINE>
<LINE>Cry 'Caesar!' Speak; Caesar is turn'd to hear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beware the ides of March.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What man is that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A soothsayer bids you beware the ides of March.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Set him before me; let me see his face.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fellow, come from the throng; look upon Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What say'st thou to me now? speak once again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beware the ides of March.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is a dreamer; let us leave him: pass.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Sennet. Exeunt all except BRUTUS and CASSIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you go see the order of the course?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you, do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not gamesome: I do lack some part</LINE>
<LINE>Of that quick spirit that is in Antony.</LINE>
<LINE>Let me not hinder, Cassius, your desires;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll leave you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brutus, I do observe you now of late:</LINE>
<LINE>I have not from your eyes that gentleness</LINE>
<LINE>And show of love as I was wont to have:</LINE>
<LINE>You bear too stubborn and too strange a hand</LINE>
<LINE>Over your friend that loves you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>Be not deceived: if I have veil'd my look,</LINE>
<LINE>I turn the trouble of my countenance</LINE>
<LINE>Merely upon myself. Vexed I am</LINE>
<LINE>Of late with passions of some difference,</LINE>
<LINE>Conceptions only proper to myself,</LINE>
<LINE>Which give some soil perhaps to my behaviors;</LINE>
<LINE>But let not therefore my good friends be grieved--</LINE>
<LINE>Among which number, Cassius, be you one--</LINE>
<LINE>Nor construe any further my neglect,</LINE>
<LINE>Than that poor Brutus, with himself at war,</LINE>
<LINE>Forgets the shows of love to other men.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then, Brutus, I have much mistook your passion;</LINE>
<LINE>By means whereof this breast of mine hath buried</LINE>
<LINE>Thoughts of great value, worthy cogitations.</LINE>
<LINE>Tell me, good Brutus, can you see your face?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, Cassius; for the eye sees not itself,</LINE>
<LINE>But by reflection, by some other things.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis just:</LINE>
<LINE>And it is very much lamented, Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>That you have no such mirrors as will turn</LINE>
<LINE>Your hidden worthiness into your eye,</LINE>
<LINE>That you might see your shadow. I have heard,</LINE>
<LINE>Where many of the best respect in Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>Except immortal Caesar, speaking of Brutus</LINE>
<LINE>And groaning underneath this age's yoke,</LINE>
<LINE>Have wish'd that noble Brutus had his eyes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Into what dangers would you lead me, Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>That you would have me seek into myself</LINE>
<LINE>For that which is not in me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore, good Brutus, be prepared to hear:</LINE>
<LINE>And since you know you cannot see yourself</LINE>
<LINE>So well as by reflection, I, your glass,</LINE>
<LINE>Will modestly discover to yourself</LINE>
<LINE>That of yourself which you yet know not of.</LINE>
<LINE>And be not jealous on me, gentle Brutus:</LINE>
<LINE>Were I a common laugher, or did use</LINE>
<LINE>To stale with ordinary oaths my love</LINE>
<LINE>To every new protester; if you know</LINE>
<LINE>That I do fawn on men and hug them hard</LINE>
<LINE>And after scandal them, or if you know</LINE>
<LINE>That I profess myself in banqueting</LINE>
<LINE>To all the rout, then hold me dangerous.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Flourish, and shout</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What means this shouting? I do fear, the people</LINE>
<LINE>Choose Caesar for their king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, do you fear it?</LINE>
<LINE>Then must I think you would not have it so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would not, Cassius; yet I love him well.</LINE>
<LINE>But wherefore do you hold me here so long?</LINE>
<LINE>What is it that you would impart to me?</LINE>
<LINE>If it be aught toward the general good,</LINE>
<LINE>Set honour in one eye and death i' the other,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will look on both indifferently,</LINE>
<LINE>For let the gods so speed me as I love</LINE>
<LINE>The name of honour more than I fear death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know that virtue to be in you, Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>As well as I do know your outward favour.</LINE>
<LINE>Well, honour is the subject of my story.</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot tell what you and other men</LINE>
<LINE>Think of this life; but, for my single self,</LINE>
<LINE>I had as lief not be as live to be</LINE>
<LINE>In awe of such a thing as I myself.</LINE>
<LINE>I was born free as Caesar; so were you:</LINE>
<LINE>We both have fed as well, and we can both</LINE>
<LINE>Endure the winter's cold as well as he:</LINE>
<LINE>For once, upon a raw and gusty day,</LINE>
<LINE>The troubled Tiber chafing with her shores,</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar said to me 'Darest thou, Cassius, now</LINE>
<LINE>Leap in with me into this angry flood,</LINE>
<LINE>And swim to yonder point?' Upon the word,</LINE>
<LINE>Accoutred as I was, I plunged in</LINE>
<LINE>And bade him follow; so indeed he did.</LINE>
<LINE>The torrent roar'd, and we did buffet it</LINE>
<LINE>With lusty sinews, throwing it aside</LINE>
<LINE>And stemming it with hearts of controversy;</LINE>
<LINE>But ere we could arrive the point proposed,</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar cried 'Help me, Cassius, or I sink!'</LINE>
<LINE>I, as Aeneas, our great ancestor,</LINE>
<LINE>Did from the flames of Troy upon his shoulder</LINE>
<LINE>The old Anchises bear, so from the waves of Tiber</LINE>
<LINE>Did I the tired Caesar. And this man</LINE>
<LINE>Is now become a god, and Cassius is</LINE>
<LINE>A wretched creature and must bend his body,</LINE>
<LINE>If Caesar carelessly but nod on him.</LINE>
<LINE>He had a fever when he was in Spain,</LINE>
<LINE>And when the fit was on him, I did mark</LINE>
<LINE>How he did shake: 'tis true, this god did shake;</LINE>
<LINE>His coward lips did from their colour fly,</LINE>
<LINE>And that same eye whose bend doth awe the world</LINE>
<LINE>Did lose his lustre: I did hear him groan:</LINE>
<LINE>Ay, and that tongue of his that bade the Romans</LINE>
<LINE>Mark him and write his speeches in their books,</LINE>
<LINE>Alas, it cried 'Give me some drink, Titinius,'</LINE>
<LINE>As a sick girl. Ye gods, it doth amaze me</LINE>
<LINE>A man of such a feeble temper should</LINE>
<LINE>So get the start of the majestic world</LINE>
<LINE>And bear the palm alone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Shout. Flourish</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Another general shout!</LINE>
<LINE>I do believe that these applauses are</LINE>
<LINE>For some new honours that are heap'd on Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, man, he doth bestride the narrow world</LINE>
<LINE>Like a Colossus, and we petty men</LINE>
<LINE>Walk under his huge legs and peep about</LINE>
<LINE>To find ourselves dishonourable graves.</LINE>
<LINE>Men at some time are masters of their fates:</LINE>
<LINE>The fault, dear Brutus, is not in our stars,</LINE>
<LINE>But in ourselves, that we are underlings.</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus and Caesar: what should be in that 'Caesar'?</LINE>
<LINE>Why should that name be sounded more than yours?</LINE>
<LINE>Write them together, yours is as fair a name;</LINE>
<LINE>Sound them, it doth become the mouth as well;</LINE>
<LINE>Weigh them, it is as heavy; conjure with 'em,</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus will start a spirit as soon as Caesar.</LINE>
<LINE>Now, in the names of all the gods at once,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon what meat doth this our Caesar feed,</LINE>
<LINE>That he is grown so great? Age, thou art shamed!</LINE>
<LINE>Rome, thou hast lost the breed of noble bloods!</LINE>
<LINE>When went there by an age, since the great flood,</LINE>
<LINE>But it was famed with more than with one man?</LINE>
<LINE>When could they say till now, that talk'd of Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>That her wide walls encompass'd but one man?</LINE>
<LINE>Now is it Rome indeed and room enough,</LINE>
<LINE>When there is in it but one only man.</LINE>
<LINE>O, you and I have heard our fathers say,</LINE>
<LINE>There was a Brutus once that would have brook'd</LINE>
<LINE>The eternal devil to keep his state in Rome</LINE>
<LINE>As easily as a king.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That you do love me, I am nothing jealous;</LINE>
<LINE>What you would work me to, I have some aim:</LINE>
<LINE>How I have thought of this and of these times,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall recount hereafter; for this present,</LINE>
<LINE>I would not, so with love I might entreat you,</LINE>
<LINE>Be any further moved. What you have said</LINE>
<LINE>I will consider; what you have to say</LINE>
<LINE>I will with patience hear, and find a time</LINE>
<LINE>Both meet to hear and answer such high things.</LINE>
<LINE>Till then, my noble friend, chew upon this:</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus had rather be a villager</LINE>
<LINE>Than to repute himself a son of Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Under these hard conditions as this time</LINE>
<LINE>Is like to lay upon us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad that my weak words</LINE>
<LINE>Have struck but thus much show of fire from Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The games are done and Caesar is returning.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As they pass by, pluck Casca by the sleeve;</LINE>
<LINE>And he will, after his sour fashion, tell you</LINE>
<LINE>What hath proceeded worthy note to-day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter CAESAR and his Train</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will do so. But, look you, Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>The angry spot doth glow on Caesar's brow,</LINE>
<LINE>And all the rest look like a chidden train:</LINE>
<LINE>Calpurnia's cheek is pale; and Cicero</LINE>
<LINE>Looks with such ferret and such fiery eyes</LINE>
<LINE>As we have seen him in the Capitol,</LINE>
<LINE>Being cross'd in conference by some senators.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Casca will tell us what the matter is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Antonius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me have men about me that are fat;</LINE>
<LINE>Sleek-headed men and such as sleep o' nights:</LINE>
<LINE>Yond Cassius has a lean and hungry look;</LINE>
<LINE>He thinks too much: such men are dangerous.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear him not, Caesar; he's not dangerous;</LINE>
<LINE>He is a noble Roman and well given.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would he were fatter! But I fear him not:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet if my name were liable to fear,</LINE>
<LINE>I do not know the man I should avoid</LINE>
<LINE>So soon as that spare Cassius. He reads much;</LINE>
<LINE>He is a great observer and he looks</LINE>
<LINE>Quite through the deeds of men: he loves no plays,</LINE>
<LINE>As thou dost, Antony; he hears no music;</LINE>
<LINE>Seldom he smiles, and smiles in such a sort</LINE>
<LINE>As if he mock'd himself and scorn'd his spirit</LINE>
<LINE>That could be moved to smile at any thing.</LINE>
<LINE>Such men as he be never at heart's ease</LINE>
<LINE>Whiles they behold a greater than themselves,</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore are they very dangerous.</LINE>
<LINE>I rather tell thee what is to be fear'd</LINE>
<LINE>Than what I fear; for always I am Caesar.</LINE>
<LINE>Come on my right hand, for this ear is deaf,</LINE>
<LINE>And tell me truly what thou think'st of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Sennet. Exeunt CAESAR and all his Train, but CASCA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You pull'd me by the cloak; would you speak with me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, Casca; tell us what hath chanced to-day,</LINE>
<LINE>That Caesar looks so sad.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, you were with him, were you not?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I should not then ask Casca what had chanced.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, there was a crown offered him: and being</LINE>
<LINE>offered him, he put it by with the back of his hand,</LINE>
<LINE>thus; and then the people fell a-shouting.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What was the second noise for?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, for that too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They shouted thrice: what was the last cry for?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, for that too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Was the crown offered him thrice?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, marry, was't, and he put it by thrice, every</LINE>
<LINE>time gentler than other, and at every putting-by</LINE>
<LINE>mine honest neighbours shouted.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who offered him the crown?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tell us the manner of it, gentle Casca.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I can as well be hanged as tell the manner of it:</LINE>
<LINE>it was mere foolery; I did not mark it. I saw Mark</LINE>
<LINE>Antony offer him a crown;--yet 'twas not a crown</LINE>
<LINE>neither, 'twas one of these coronets;--and, as I told</LINE>
<LINE>you, he put it by once: but, for all that, to my</LINE>
<LINE>thinking, he would fain have had it. Then he</LINE>
<LINE>offered it to him again; then he put it by again:</LINE>
<LINE>but, to my thinking, he was very loath to lay his</LINE>
<LINE>fingers off it. And then he offered it the third</LINE>
<LINE>time; he put it the third time by: and still as he</LINE>
<LINE>refused it, the rabblement hooted and clapped their</LINE>
<LINE>chapped hands and threw up their sweaty night-caps</LINE>
<LINE>and uttered such a deal of stinking breath because</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar refused the crown that it had almost choked</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar; for he swounded and fell down at it: and</LINE>
<LINE>for mine own part, I durst not laugh, for fear of</LINE>
<LINE>opening my lips and receiving the bad air.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But, soft, I pray you: what, did Caesar swound?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He fell down in the market-place, and foamed at</LINE>
<LINE>mouth, and was speechless.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis very like: he hath the failing sickness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, Caesar hath it not; but you and I,</LINE>
<LINE>And honest Casca, we have the falling sickness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not what you mean by that; but, I am sure,</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar fell down. If the tag-rag people did not</LINE>
<LINE>clap him and hiss him, according as he pleased and</LINE>
<LINE>displeased them, as they use to do the players in</LINE>
<LINE>the theatre, I am no true man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What said he when he came unto himself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, before he fell down, when he perceived the</LINE>
<LINE>common herd was glad he refused the crown, he</LINE>
<LINE>plucked me ope his doublet and offered them his</LINE>
<LINE>throat to cut. An I had been a man of any</LINE>
<LINE>occupation, if I would not have taken him at a word,</LINE>
<LINE>I would I might go to hell among the rogues. And so</LINE>
<LINE>he fell. When he came to himself again, he said,</LINE>
<LINE>If he had done or said any thing amiss, he desired</LINE>
<LINE>their worships to think it was his infirmity. Three</LINE>
<LINE>or four wenches, where I stood, cried 'Alas, good</LINE>
<LINE>soul!' and forgave him with all their hearts: but</LINE>
<LINE>there's no heed to be taken of them; if Caesar had</LINE>
<LINE>stabbed their mothers, they would have done no less.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And after that, he came, thus sad, away?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did Cicero say any thing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, he spoke Greek.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To what effect?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, an I tell you that, Ill ne'er look you i' the</LINE>
<LINE>face again: but those that understood him smiled at</LINE>
<LINE>one another and shook their heads; but, for mine own</LINE>
<LINE>part, it was Greek to me. I could tell you more</LINE>
<LINE>news too: Marullus and Flavius, for pulling scarfs</LINE>
<LINE>off Caesar's images, are put to silence. Fare you</LINE>
<LINE>well. There was more foolery yet, if I could</LINE>
<LINE>remember it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you sup with me to-night, Casca?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I am promised forth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you dine with me to-morrow?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, if I be alive and your mind hold and your dinner</LINE>
<LINE>worth the eating.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good: I will expect you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do so. Farewell, both.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What a blunt fellow is this grown to be!</LINE>
<LINE>He was quick mettle when he went to school.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So is he now in execution</LINE>
<LINE>Of any bold or noble enterprise,</LINE>
<LINE>However he puts on this tardy form.</LINE>
<LINE>This rudeness is a sauce to his good wit,</LINE>
<LINE>Which gives men stomach to digest his words</LINE>
<LINE>With better appetite.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so it is. For this time I will leave you:</LINE>
<LINE>To-morrow, if you please to speak with me,</LINE>
<LINE>I will come home to you; or, if you will,</LINE>
<LINE>Come home to me, and I will wait for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will do so: till then, think of the world.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Well, Brutus, thou art noble; yet, I see,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy honourable metal may be wrought</LINE>
<LINE>From that it is disposed: therefore it is meet</LINE>
<LINE>That noble minds keep ever with their likes;</LINE>
<LINE>For who so firm that cannot be seduced?</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar doth bear me hard; but he loves Brutus:</LINE>
<LINE>If I were Brutus now and he were Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>He should not humour me. I will this night,</LINE>
<LINE>In several hands, in at his windows throw,</LINE>
<LINE>As if they came from several citizens,</LINE>
<LINE>Writings all tending to the great opinion</LINE>
<LINE>That Rome holds of his name; wherein obscurely</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar's ambition shall be glanced at:</LINE>
<LINE>And after this let Caesar seat him sure;</LINE>
<LINE>For we will shake him, or worse days endure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  The same. A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Thunder and lightning. Enter from opposite sides,
CASCA, with his sword drawn, and CICERO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CICERO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good even, Casca: brought you Caesar home?</LINE>
<LINE>Why are you breathless? and why stare you so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are not you moved, when all the sway of earth</LINE>
<LINE>Shakes like a thing unfirm? O Cicero,</LINE>
<LINE>I have seen tempests, when the scolding winds</LINE>
<LINE>Have rived the knotty oaks, and I have seen</LINE>
<LINE>The ambitious ocean swell and rage and foam,</LINE>
<LINE>To be exalted with the threatening clouds:</LINE>
<LINE>But never till to-night, never till now,</LINE>
<LINE>Did I go through a tempest dropping fire.</LINE>
<LINE>Either there is a civil strife in heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>Or else the world, too saucy with the gods,</LINE>
<LINE>Incenses them to send destruction.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CICERO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, saw you any thing more wonderful?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A common slave--you know him well by sight--</LINE>
<LINE>Held up his left hand, which did flame and burn</LINE>
<LINE>Like twenty torches join'd, and yet his hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Not sensible of fire, remain'd unscorch'd.</LINE>
<LINE>Besides--I ha' not since put up my sword--</LINE>
<LINE>Against the Capitol I met a lion,</LINE>
<LINE>Who glared upon me, and went surly by,</LINE>
<LINE>Without annoying me: and there were drawn</LINE>
<LINE>Upon a heap a hundred ghastly women,</LINE>
<LINE>Transformed with their fear; who swore they saw</LINE>
<LINE>Men all in fire walk up and down the streets.</LINE>
<LINE>And yesterday the bird of night did sit</LINE>
<LINE>Even at noon-day upon the market-place,</LINE>
<LINE>Hooting and shrieking. When these prodigies</LINE>
<LINE>Do so conjointly meet, let not men say</LINE>
<LINE>'These are their reasons; they are natural;'</LINE>
<LINE>For, I believe, they are portentous things</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the climate that they point upon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CICERO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, it is a strange-disposed time:</LINE>
<LINE>But men may construe things after their fashion,</LINE>
<LINE>Clean from the purpose of the things themselves.</LINE>
<LINE>Come Caesar to the Capitol to-morrow?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He doth; for he did bid Antonius</LINE>
<LINE>Send word to you he would be there to-morrow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CICERO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good night then, Casca: this disturbed sky</LINE>
<LINE>Is not to walk in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, Cicero.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit CICERO</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who's there?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A Roman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Casca, by your voice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your ear is good. Cassius, what night is this!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A very pleasing night to honest men.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who ever knew the heavens menace so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Those that have known the earth so full of faults.</LINE>
<LINE>For my part, I have walk'd about the streets,</LINE>
<LINE>Submitting me unto the perilous night,</LINE>
<LINE>And, thus unbraced, Casca, as you see,</LINE>
<LINE>Have bared my bosom to the thunder-stone;</LINE>
<LINE>And when the cross blue lightning seem'd to open</LINE>
<LINE>The breast of heaven, I did present myself</LINE>
<LINE>Even in the aim and very flash of it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But wherefore did you so much tempt the heavens?</LINE>
<LINE>It is the part of men to fear and tremble,</LINE>
<LINE>When the most mighty gods by tokens send</LINE>
<LINE>Such dreadful heralds to astonish us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are dull, Casca, and those sparks of life</LINE>
<LINE>That should be in a Roman you do want,</LINE>
<LINE>Or else you use not. You look pale and gaze</LINE>
<LINE>And put on fear and cast yourself in wonder,</LINE>
<LINE>To see the strange impatience of the heavens:</LINE>
<LINE>But if you would consider the true cause</LINE>
<LINE>Why all these fires, why all these gliding ghosts,</LINE>
<LINE>Why birds and beasts from quality and kind,</LINE>
<LINE>Why old men fool and children calculate,</LINE>
<LINE>Why all these things change from their ordinance</LINE>
<LINE>Their natures and preformed faculties</LINE>
<LINE>To monstrous quality,--why, you shall find</LINE>
<LINE>That heaven hath infused them with these spirits,</LINE>
<LINE>To make them instruments of fear and warning</LINE>
<LINE>Unto some monstrous state.</LINE>
<LINE>Now could I, Casca, name to thee a man</LINE>
<LINE>Most like this dreadful night,</LINE>
<LINE>That thunders, lightens, opens graves, and roars</LINE>
<LINE>As doth the lion in the Capitol,</LINE>
<LINE>A man no mightier than thyself or me</LINE>
<LINE>In personal action, yet prodigious grown</LINE>
<LINE>And fearful, as these strange eruptions are.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis Caesar that you mean; is it not, Cassius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let it be who it is: for Romans now</LINE>
<LINE>Have thews and limbs like to their ancestors;</LINE>
<LINE>But, woe the while! our fathers' minds are dead,</LINE>
<LINE>And we are govern'd with our mothers' spirits;</LINE>
<LINE>Our yoke and sufferance show us womanish.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, they say the senators tomorrow</LINE>
<LINE>Mean to establish Caesar as a king;</LINE>
<LINE>And he shall wear his crown by sea and land,</LINE>
<LINE>In every place, save here in Italy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know where I will wear this dagger then;</LINE>
<LINE>Cassius from bondage will deliver Cassius:</LINE>
<LINE>Therein, ye gods, you make the weak most strong;</LINE>
<LINE>Therein, ye gods, you tyrants do defeat:</LINE>
<LINE>Nor stony tower, nor walls of beaten brass,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor airless dungeon, nor strong links of iron,</LINE>
<LINE>Can be retentive to the strength of spirit;</LINE>
<LINE>But life, being weary of these worldly bars,</LINE>
<LINE>Never lacks power to dismiss itself.</LINE>
<LINE>If I know this, know all the world besides,</LINE>
<LINE>That part of tyranny that I do bear</LINE>
<LINE>I can shake off at pleasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Thunder still</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So can I:</LINE>
<LINE>So every bondman in his own hand bears</LINE>
<LINE>The power to cancel his captivity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And why should Caesar be a tyrant then?</LINE>
<LINE>Poor man! I know he would not be a wolf,</LINE>
<LINE>But that he sees the Romans are but sheep:</LINE>
<LINE>He were no lion, were not Romans hinds.</LINE>
<LINE>Those that with haste will make a mighty fire</LINE>
<LINE>Begin it with weak straws: what trash is Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>What rubbish and what offal, when it serves</LINE>
<LINE>For the base matter to illuminate</LINE>
<LINE>So vile a thing as Caesar! But, O grief,</LINE>
<LINE>Where hast thou led me? I perhaps speak this</LINE>
<LINE>Before a willing bondman; then I know</LINE>
<LINE>My answer must be made. But I am arm'd,</LINE>
<LINE>And dangers are to me indifferent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You speak to Casca, and to such a man</LINE>
<LINE>That is no fleering tell-tale. Hold, my hand:</LINE>
<LINE>Be factious for redress of all these griefs,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will set this foot of mine as far</LINE>
<LINE>As who goes farthest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There's a bargain made.</LINE>
<LINE>Now know you, Casca, I have moved already</LINE>
<LINE>Some certain of the noblest-minded Romans</LINE>
<LINE>To undergo with me an enterprise</LINE>
<LINE>Of honourable-dangerous consequence;</LINE>
<LINE>And I do know, by this, they stay for me</LINE>
<LINE>In Pompey's porch: for now, this fearful night,</LINE>
<LINE>There is no stir or walking in the streets;</LINE>
<LINE>And the complexion of the element</LINE>
<LINE>In favour's like the work we have in hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Most bloody, fiery, and most terrible.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand close awhile, for here comes one in haste.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis Cinna; I do know him by his gait;</LINE>
<LINE>He is a friend.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CINNA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Cinna, where haste you so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To find out you. Who's that? Metellus Cimber?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, it is Casca; one incorporate</LINE>
<LINE>To our attempts. Am I not stay'd for, Cinna?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad on 't. What a fearful night is this!</LINE>
<LINE>There's two or three of us have seen strange sights.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Am I not stay'd for? tell me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, you are.</LINE>
<LINE>O Cassius, if you could</LINE>
<LINE>But win the noble Brutus to our party--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be you content: good Cinna, take this paper,</LINE>
<LINE>And look you lay it in the praetor's chair,</LINE>
<LINE>Where Brutus may but find it; and throw this</LINE>
<LINE>In at his window; set this up with wax</LINE>
<LINE>Upon old Brutus' statue: all this done,</LINE>
<LINE>Repair to Pompey's porch, where you shall find us.</LINE>
<LINE>Is Decius Brutus and Trebonius there?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All but Metellus Cimber; and he's gone</LINE>
<LINE>To seek you at your house. Well, I will hie,</LINE>
<LINE>And so bestow these papers as you bade me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That done, repair to Pompey's theatre.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit CINNA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Come, Casca, you and I will yet ere day</LINE>
<LINE>See Brutus at his house: three parts of him</LINE>
<LINE>Is ours already, and the man entire</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the next encounter yields him ours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, he sits high in all the people's hearts:</LINE>
<LINE>And that which would appear offence in us,</LINE>
<LINE>His countenance, like richest alchemy,</LINE>
<LINE>Will change to virtue and to worthiness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Him and his worth and our great need of him</LINE>
<LINE>You have right well conceited. Let us go,</LINE>
<LINE>For it is after midnight; and ere day</LINE>
<LINE>We will awake him and be sure of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT II</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. BRUTUS's orchard.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, Lucius, ho!</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot, by the progress of the stars,</LINE>
<LINE>Give guess how near to day. Lucius, I say!</LINE>
<LINE>I would it were my fault to sleep so soundly.</LINE>
<LINE>When, Lucius, when? awake, I say! what, Lucius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call'd you, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get me a taper in my study, Lucius:</LINE>
<LINE>When it is lighted, come and call me here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It must be by his death: and for my part,</LINE>
<LINE>I know no personal cause to spurn at him,</LINE>
<LINE>But for the general. He would be crown'd:</LINE>
<LINE>How that might change his nature, there's the question.</LINE>
<LINE>It is the bright day that brings forth the adder;</LINE>
<LINE>And that craves wary walking. Crown him?--that;--</LINE>
<LINE>And then, I grant, we put a sting in him,</LINE>
<LINE>That at his will he may do danger with.</LINE>
<LINE>The abuse of greatness is, when it disjoins</LINE>
<LINE>Remorse from power: and, to speak truth of Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>I have not known when his affections sway'd</LINE>
<LINE>More than his reason. But 'tis a common proof,</LINE>
<LINE>That lowliness is young ambition's ladder,</LINE>
<LINE>Whereto the climber-upward turns his face;</LINE>
<LINE>But when he once attains the upmost round.</LINE>
<LINE>He then unto the ladder turns his back,</LINE>
<LINE>Looks in the clouds, scorning the base degrees</LINE>
<LINE>By which he did ascend. So Caesar may.</LINE>
<LINE>Then, lest he may, prevent. And, since the quarrel</LINE>
<LINE>Will bear no colour for the thing he is,</LINE>
<LINE>Fashion it thus; that what he is, augmented,</LINE>
<LINE>Would run to these and these extremities:</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore think him as a serpent's egg</LINE>
<LINE>Which, hatch'd, would, as his kind, grow mischievous,</LINE>
<LINE>And kill him in the shell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The taper burneth in your closet, sir.</LINE>
<LINE>Searching the window for a flint, I found</LINE>
<LINE>This paper, thus seal'd up; and, I am sure,</LINE>
<LINE>It did not lie there when I went to bed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Gives him the letter</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get you to bed again; it is not day.</LINE>
<LINE>Is not to-morrow, boy, the ides of March?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look in the calendar, and bring me word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The exhalations whizzing in the air</LINE>
<LINE>Give so much light that I may read by them.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Opens the letter and reads</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>'Brutus, thou sleep'st: awake, and see thyself.</LINE>
<LINE>Shall Rome, &amp;c. Speak, strike, redress!</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus, thou sleep'st: awake!'</LINE>
<LINE>Such instigations have been often dropp'd</LINE>
<LINE>Where I have took them up.</LINE>
<LINE>'Shall Rome, &amp;c.' Thus must I piece it out:</LINE>
<LINE>Shall Rome stand under one man's awe? What, Rome?</LINE>
<LINE>My ancestors did from the streets of Rome</LINE>
<LINE>The Tarquin drive, when he was call'd a king.</LINE>
<LINE>'Speak, strike, redress!' Am I entreated</LINE>
<LINE>To speak and strike? O Rome, I make thee promise:</LINE>
<LINE>If the redress will follow, thou receivest</LINE>
<LINE>Thy full petition at the hand of Brutus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, March is wasted fourteen days.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Knocking within</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis good. Go to the gate; somebody knocks.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Since Cassius first did whet me against Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>I have not slept.</LINE>
<LINE>Between the acting of a dreadful thing</LINE>
<LINE>And the first motion, all the interim is</LINE>
<LINE>Like a phantasma, or a hideous dream:</LINE>
<LINE>The Genius and the mortal instruments</LINE>
<LINE>Are then in council; and the state of man,</LINE>
<LINE>Like to a little kingdom, suffers then</LINE>
<LINE>The nature of an insurrection.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, 'tis your brother Cassius at the door,</LINE>
<LINE>Who doth desire to see you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is he alone?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, sir, there are moe with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you know them?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, sir; their hats are pluck'd about their ears,</LINE>
<LINE>And half their faces buried in their cloaks,</LINE>
<LINE>That by no means I may discover them</LINE>
<LINE>By any mark of favour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let 'em enter.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>They are the faction. O conspiracy,</LINE>
<LINE>Shamest thou to show thy dangerous brow by night,</LINE>
<LINE>When evils are most free? O, then by day</LINE>
<LINE>Where wilt thou find a cavern dark enough</LINE>
<LINE>To mask thy monstrous visage? Seek none, conspiracy;</LINE>
<LINE>Hide it in smiles and affability:</LINE>
<LINE>For if thou path, thy native semblance on,</LINE>
<LINE>Not Erebus itself were dim enough</LINE>
<LINE>To hide thee from prevention.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter the conspirators, CASSIUS, CASCA, DECIUS
BRUTUS, CINNA, METELLUS CIMBER, and TREBONIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think we are too bold upon your rest:</LINE>
<LINE>Good morrow, Brutus; do we trouble you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have been up this hour, awake all night.</LINE>
<LINE>Know I these men that come along with you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, every man of them, and no man here</LINE>
<LINE>But honours you; and every one doth wish</LINE>
<LINE>You had but that opinion of yourself</LINE>
<LINE>Which every noble Roman bears of you.</LINE>
<LINE>This is Trebonius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is welcome hither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This, Decius Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is welcome too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This, Casca; this, Cinna; and this, Metellus Cimber.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They are all welcome.</LINE>
<LINE>What watchful cares do interpose themselves</LINE>
<LINE>Betwixt your eyes and night?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall I entreat a word?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>BRUTUS and CASSIUS whisper</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here lies the east: doth not the day break here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, pardon, sir, it doth; and yon gray lines</LINE>
<LINE>That fret the clouds are messengers of day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall confess that you are both deceived.</LINE>
<LINE>Here, as I point my sword, the sun arises,</LINE>
<LINE>Which is a great way growing on the south,</LINE>
<LINE>Weighing the youthful season of the year.</LINE>
<LINE>Some two months hence up higher toward the north</LINE>
<LINE>He first presents his fire; and the high east</LINE>
<LINE>Stands, as the Capitol, directly here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give me your hands all over, one by one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And let us swear our resolution.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, not an oath: if not the face of men,</LINE>
<LINE>The sufferance of our souls, the time's abuse,--</LINE>
<LINE>If these be motives weak, break off betimes,</LINE>
<LINE>And every man hence to his idle bed;</LINE>
<LINE>So let high-sighted tyranny range on,</LINE>
<LINE>Till each man drop by lottery. But if these,</LINE>
<LINE>As I am sure they do, bear fire enough</LINE>
<LINE>To kindle cowards and to steel with valour</LINE>
<LINE>The melting spirits of women, then, countrymen,</LINE>
<LINE>What need we any spur but our own cause,</LINE>
<LINE>To prick us to redress? what other bond</LINE>
<LINE>Than secret Romans, that have spoke the word,</LINE>
<LINE>And will not palter? and what other oath</LINE>
<LINE>Than honesty to honesty engaged,</LINE>
<LINE>That this shall be, or we will fall for it?</LINE>
<LINE>Swear priests and cowards and men cautelous,</LINE>
<LINE>Old feeble carrions and such suffering souls</LINE>
<LINE>That welcome wrongs; unto bad causes swear</LINE>
<LINE>Such creatures as men doubt; but do not stain</LINE>
<LINE>The even virtue of our enterprise,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor the insuppressive mettle of our spirits,</LINE>
<LINE>To think that or our cause or our performance</LINE>
<LINE>Did need an oath; when every drop of blood</LINE>
<LINE>That every Roman bears, and nobly bears,</LINE>
<LINE>Is guilty of a several bastardy,</LINE>
<LINE>If he do break the smallest particle</LINE>
<LINE>Of any promise that hath pass'd from him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But what of Cicero? shall we sound him?</LINE>
<LINE>I think he will stand very strong with us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let us not leave him out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, by no means.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>METELLUS CIMBER</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, let us have him, for his silver hairs</LINE>
<LINE>Will purchase us a good opinion</LINE>
<LINE>And buy men's voices to commend our deeds:</LINE>
<LINE>It shall be said, his judgment ruled our hands;</LINE>
<LINE>Our youths and wildness shall no whit appear,</LINE>
<LINE>But all be buried in his gravity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, name him not: let us not break with him;</LINE>
<LINE>For he will never follow any thing</LINE>
<LINE>That other men begin.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then leave him out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed he is not fit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall no man else be touch'd but only Caesar?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Decius, well urged: I think it is not meet,</LINE>
<LINE>Mark Antony, so well beloved of Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>Should outlive Caesar: we shall find of him</LINE>
<LINE>A shrewd contriver; and, you know, his means,</LINE>
<LINE>If he improve them, may well stretch so far</LINE>
<LINE>As to annoy us all: which to prevent,</LINE>
<LINE>Let Antony and Caesar fall together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Our course will seem too bloody, Caius Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>To cut the head off and then hack the limbs,</LINE>
<LINE>Like wrath in death and envy afterwards;</LINE>
<LINE>For Antony is but a limb of Caesar:</LINE>
<LINE>Let us be sacrificers, but not butchers, Caius.</LINE>
<LINE>We all stand up against the spirit of Caesar;</LINE>
<LINE>And in the spirit of men there is no blood:</LINE>
<LINE>O, that we then could come by Caesar's spirit,</LINE>
<LINE>And not dismember Caesar! But, alas,</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar must bleed for it! And, gentle friends,</LINE>
<LINE>Let's kill him boldly, but not wrathfully;</LINE>
<LINE>Let's carve him as a dish fit for the gods,</LINE>
<LINE>Not hew him as a carcass fit for hounds:</LINE>
<LINE>And let our hearts, as subtle masters do,</LINE>
<LINE>Stir up their servants to an act of rage,</LINE>
<LINE>And after seem to chide 'em. This shall make</LINE>
<LINE>Our purpose necessary and not envious:</LINE>
<LINE>Which so appearing to the common eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>We shall be call'd purgers, not murderers.</LINE>
<LINE>And for Mark Antony, think not of him;</LINE>
<LINE>For he can do no more than Caesar's arm</LINE>
<LINE>When Caesar's head is off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet I fear him;</LINE>
<LINE>For in the ingrafted love he bears to Caesar--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, good Cassius, do not think of him:</LINE>
<LINE>If he love Caesar, all that he can do</LINE>
<LINE>Is to himself, take thought and die for Caesar:</LINE>
<LINE>And that were much he should; for he is given</LINE>
<LINE>To sports, to wildness and much company.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TREBONIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is no fear in him; let him not die;</LINE>
<LINE>For he will live, and laugh at this hereafter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Clock strikes</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace! count the clock.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The clock hath stricken three.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TREBONIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis time to part.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But it is doubtful yet,</LINE>
<LINE>Whether Caesar will come forth to-day, or no;</LINE>
<LINE>For he is superstitious grown of late,</LINE>
<LINE>Quite from the main opinion he held once</LINE>
<LINE>Of fantasy, of dreams and ceremonies:</LINE>
<LINE>It may be, these apparent prodigies,</LINE>
<LINE>The unaccustom'd terror of this night,</LINE>
<LINE>And the persuasion of his augurers,</LINE>
<LINE>May hold him from the Capitol to-day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never fear that: if he be so resolved,</LINE>
<LINE>I can o'ersway him; for he loves to hear</LINE>
<LINE>That unicorns may be betray'd with trees,</LINE>
<LINE>And bears with glasses, elephants with holes,</LINE>
<LINE>Lions with toils and men with flatterers;</LINE>
<LINE>But when I tell him he hates flatterers,</LINE>
<LINE>He says he does, being then most flattered.</LINE>
<LINE>Let me work;</LINE>
<LINE>For I can give his humour the true bent,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will bring him to the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, we will all of us be there to fetch him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By the eighth hour: is that the uttermost?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be that the uttermost, and fail not then.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>METELLUS CIMBER</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caius Ligarius doth bear Caesar hard,</LINE>
<LINE>Who rated him for speaking well of Pompey:</LINE>
<LINE>I wonder none of you have thought of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, good Metellus, go along by him:</LINE>
<LINE>He loves me well, and I have given him reasons;</LINE>
<LINE>Send him but hither, and I'll fashion him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The morning comes upon 's: we'll leave you, Brutus.</LINE>
<LINE>And, friends, disperse yourselves; but all remember</LINE>
<LINE>What you have said, and show yourselves true Romans.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good gentlemen, look fresh and merrily;</LINE>
<LINE>Let not our looks put on our purposes,</LINE>
<LINE>But bear it as our Roman actors do,</LINE>
<LINE>With untired spirits and formal constancy:</LINE>
<LINE>And so good morrow to you every one.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt all but BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Boy! Lucius! Fast asleep? It is no matter;</LINE>
<LINE>Enjoy the honey-heavy dew of slumber:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast no figures nor no fantasies,</LINE>
<LINE>Which busy care draws in the brains of men;</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore thou sleep'st so sound.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter PORTIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brutus, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Portia, what mean you? wherefore rise you now?</LINE>
<LINE>It is not for your health thus to commit</LINE>
<LINE>Your weak condition to the raw cold morning.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor for yours neither. You've ungently, Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>Stole from my bed: and yesternight, at supper,</LINE>
<LINE>You suddenly arose, and walk'd about,</LINE>
<LINE>Musing and sighing, with your arms across,</LINE>
<LINE>And when I ask'd you what the matter was,</LINE>
<LINE>You stared upon me with ungentle looks;</LINE>
<LINE>I urged you further; then you scratch'd your head,</LINE>
<LINE>And too impatiently stamp'd with your foot;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet I insisted, yet you answer'd not,</LINE>
<LINE>But, with an angry wafture of your hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Gave sign for me to leave you: so I did;</LINE>
<LINE>Fearing to strengthen that impatience</LINE>
<LINE>Which seem'd too much enkindled, and withal</LINE>
<LINE>Hoping it was but an effect of humour,</LINE>
<LINE>Which sometime hath his hour with every man.</LINE>
<LINE>It will not let you eat, nor talk, nor sleep,</LINE>
<LINE>And could it work so much upon your shape</LINE>
<LINE>As it hath much prevail'd on your condition,</LINE>
<LINE>I should not know you, Brutus. Dear my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Make me acquainted with your cause of grief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not well in health, and that is all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brutus is wise, and, were he not in health,</LINE>
<LINE>He would embrace the means to come by it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, so I do. Good Portia, go to bed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is Brutus sick? and is it physical</LINE>
<LINE>To walk unbraced and suck up the humours</LINE>
<LINE>Of the dank morning? What, is Brutus sick,</LINE>
<LINE>And will he steal out of his wholesome bed,</LINE>
<LINE>To dare the vile contagion of the night</LINE>
<LINE>And tempt the rheumy and unpurged air</LINE>
<LINE>To add unto his sickness? No, my Brutus;</LINE>
<LINE>You have some sick offence within your mind,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, by the right and virtue of my place,</LINE>
<LINE>I ought to know of: and, upon my knees,</LINE>
<LINE>I charm you, by my once-commended beauty,</LINE>
<LINE>By all your vows of love and that great vow</LINE>
<LINE>Which did incorporate and make us one,</LINE>
<LINE>That you unfold to me, yourself, your half,</LINE>
<LINE>Why you are heavy, and what men to-night</LINE>
<LINE>Have had to resort to you: for here have been</LINE>
<LINE>Some six or seven, who did hide their faces</LINE>
<LINE>Even from darkness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kneel not, gentle Portia.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I should not need, if you were gentle Brutus.</LINE>
<LINE>Within the bond of marriage, tell me, Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>Is it excepted I should know no secrets</LINE>
<LINE>That appertain to you? Am I yourself</LINE>
<LINE>But, as it were, in sort or limitation,</LINE>
<LINE>To keep with you at meals, comfort your bed,</LINE>
<LINE>And talk to you sometimes? Dwell I but in the suburbs</LINE>
<LINE>Of your good pleasure? If it be no more,</LINE>
<LINE>Portia is Brutus' harlot, not his wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are my true and honourable wife,</LINE>
<LINE>As dear to me as are the ruddy drops</LINE>
<LINE>That visit my sad heart</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If this were true, then should I know this secret.</LINE>
<LINE>I grant I am a woman; but withal</LINE>
<LINE>A woman that Lord Brutus took to wife:</LINE>
<LINE>I grant I am a woman; but withal</LINE>
<LINE>A woman well-reputed, Cato's daughter.</LINE>
<LINE>Think you I am no stronger than my sex,</LINE>
<LINE>Being so father'd and so husbanded?</LINE>
<LINE>Tell me your counsels, I will not disclose 'em:</LINE>
<LINE>I have made strong proof of my constancy,</LINE>
<LINE>Giving myself a voluntary wound</LINE>
<LINE>Here, in the thigh: can I bear that with patience.</LINE>
<LINE>And not my husband's secrets?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O ye gods,</LINE>
<LINE>Render me worthy of this noble wife!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Knocking within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hark, hark! one knocks: Portia, go in awhile;</LINE>
<LINE>And by and by thy bosom shall partake</LINE>
<LINE>The secrets of my heart.</LINE>
<LINE>All my engagements I will construe to thee,</LINE>
<LINE>All the charactery of my sad brows:</LINE>
<LINE>Leave me with haste.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit PORTIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Lucius, who's that knocks?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter LUCIUS with LIGARIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is a sick man that would speak with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caius Ligarius, that Metellus spake of.</LINE>
<LINE>Boy, stand aside. Caius Ligarius! how?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LIGARIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Vouchsafe good morrow from a feeble tongue.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, what a time have you chose out, brave Caius,</LINE>
<LINE>To wear a kerchief! Would you were not sick!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LIGARIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not sick, if Brutus have in hand</LINE>
<LINE>Any exploit worthy the name of honour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Such an exploit have I in hand, Ligarius,</LINE>
<LINE>Had you a healthful ear to hear of it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LIGARIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By all the gods that Romans bow before,</LINE>
<LINE>I here discard my sickness! Soul of Rome!</LINE>
<LINE>Brave son, derived from honourable loins!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou, like an exorcist, hast conjured up</LINE>
<LINE>My mortified spirit. Now bid me run,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will strive with things impossible;</LINE>
<LINE>Yea, get the better of them. What's to do?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A piece of work that will make sick men whole.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LIGARIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But are not some whole that we must make sick?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That must we also. What it is, my Caius,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall unfold to thee, as we are going</LINE>
<LINE>To whom it must be done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LIGARIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Set on your foot,</LINE>
<LINE>And with a heart new-fired I follow you,</LINE>
<LINE>To do I know not what: but it sufficeth</LINE>
<LINE>That Brutus leads me on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Follow me, then.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  CAESAR's house.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Thunder and lightning. Enter CAESAR, in his
night-gown</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor heaven nor earth have been at peace to-night:</LINE>
<LINE>Thrice hath Calpurnia in her sleep cried out,</LINE>
<LINE>'Help, ho! they murder Caesar!' Who's within?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter a Servant</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go bid the priests do present sacrifice</LINE>
<LINE>And bring me their opinions of success.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CALPURNIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CALPURNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What mean you, Caesar? think you to walk forth?</LINE>
<LINE>You shall not stir out of your house to-day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar shall forth: the things that threaten'd me</LINE>
<LINE>Ne'er look'd but on my back; when they shall see</LINE>
<LINE>The face of Caesar, they are vanished.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CALPURNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar, I never stood on ceremonies,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet now they fright me. There is one within,</LINE>
<LINE>Besides the things that we have heard and seen,</LINE>
<LINE>Recounts most horrid sights seen by the watch.</LINE>
<LINE>A lioness hath whelped in the streets;</LINE>
<LINE>And graves have yawn'd, and yielded up their dead;</LINE>
<LINE>Fierce fiery warriors fought upon the clouds,</LINE>
<LINE>In ranks and squadrons and right form of war,</LINE>
<LINE>Which drizzled blood upon the Capitol;</LINE>
<LINE>The noise of battle hurtled in the air,</LINE>
<LINE>Horses did neigh, and dying men did groan,</LINE>
<LINE>And ghosts did shriek and squeal about the streets.</LINE>
<LINE>O Caesar! these things are beyond all use,</LINE>
<LINE>And I do fear them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What can be avoided</LINE>
<LINE>Whose end is purposed by the mighty gods?</LINE>
<LINE>Yet Caesar shall go forth; for these predictions</LINE>
<LINE>Are to the world in general as to Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CALPURNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When beggars die, there are no comets seen;</LINE>
<LINE>The heavens themselves blaze forth the death of princes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cowards die many times before their deaths;</LINE>
<LINE>The valiant never taste of death but once.</LINE>
<LINE>Of all the wonders that I yet have heard.</LINE>
<LINE>It seems to me most strange that men should fear;</LINE>
<LINE>Seeing that death, a necessary end,</LINE>
<LINE>Will come when it will come.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter Servant</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What say the augurers?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They would not have you to stir forth to-day.</LINE>
<LINE>Plucking the entrails of an offering forth,</LINE>
<LINE>They could not find a heart within the beast.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The gods do this in shame of cowardice:</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar should be a beast without a heart,</LINE>
<LINE>If he should stay at home to-day for fear.</LINE>
<LINE>No, Caesar shall not: danger knows full well</LINE>
<LINE>That Caesar is more dangerous than he:</LINE>
<LINE>We are two lions litter'd in one day,</LINE>
<LINE>And I the elder and more terrible:</LINE>
<LINE>And Caesar shall go forth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CALPURNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Your wisdom is consumed in confidence.</LINE>
<LINE>Do not go forth to-day: call it my fear</LINE>
<LINE>That keeps you in the house, and not your own.</LINE>
<LINE>We'll send Mark Antony to the senate-house:</LINE>
<LINE>And he shall say you are not well to-day:</LINE>
<LINE>Let me, upon my knee, prevail in this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark Antony shall say I am not well,</LINE>
<LINE>And, for thy humour, I will stay at home.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter DECIUS BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here's Decius Brutus, he shall tell them so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar, all hail! good morrow, worthy Caesar:</LINE>
<LINE>I come to fetch you to the senate-house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And you are come in very happy time,</LINE>
<LINE>To bear my greeting to the senators</LINE>
<LINE>And tell them that I will not come to-day:</LINE>
<LINE>Cannot, is false, and that I dare not, falser:</LINE>
<LINE>I will not come to-day: tell them so, Decius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CALPURNIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say he is sick.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall Caesar send a lie?</LINE>
<LINE>Have I in conquest stretch'd mine arm so far,</LINE>
<LINE>To be afraid to tell graybeards the truth?</LINE>
<LINE>Decius, go tell them Caesar will not come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most mighty Caesar, let me know some cause,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest I be laugh'd at when I tell them so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The cause is in my will: I will not come;</LINE>
<LINE>That is enough to satisfy the senate.</LINE>
<LINE>But for your private satisfaction,</LINE>
<LINE>Because I love you, I will let you know:</LINE>
<LINE>Calpurnia here, my wife, stays me at home:</LINE>
<LINE>She dreamt to-night she saw my statua,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, like a fountain with an hundred spouts,</LINE>
<LINE>Did run pure blood: and many lusty Romans</LINE>
<LINE>Came smiling, and did bathe their hands in it:</LINE>
<LINE>And these does she apply for warnings, and portents,</LINE>
<LINE>And evils imminent; and on her knee</LINE>
<LINE>Hath begg'd that I will stay at home to-day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This dream is all amiss interpreted;</LINE>
<LINE>It was a vision fair and fortunate:</LINE>
<LINE>Your statue spouting blood in many pipes,</LINE>
<LINE>In which so many smiling Romans bathed,</LINE>
<LINE>Signifies that from you great Rome shall suck</LINE>
<LINE>Reviving blood, and that great men shall press</LINE>
<LINE>For tinctures, stains, relics and cognizance.</LINE>
<LINE>This by Calpurnia's dream is signified.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And this way have you well expounded it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have, when you have heard what I can say:</LINE>
<LINE>And know it now: the senate have concluded</LINE>
<LINE>To give this day a crown to mighty Caesar.</LINE>
<LINE>If you shall send them word you will not come,</LINE>
<LINE>Their minds may change. Besides, it were a mock</LINE>
<LINE>Apt to be render'd, for some one to say</LINE>
<LINE>'Break up the senate till another time,</LINE>
<LINE>When Caesar's wife shall meet with better dreams.'</LINE>
<LINE>If Caesar hide himself, shall they not whisper</LINE>
<LINE>'Lo, Caesar is afraid'?</LINE>
<LINE>Pardon me, Caesar; for my dear dear love</LINE>
<LINE>To our proceeding bids me tell you this;</LINE>
<LINE>And reason to my love is liable.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How foolish do your fears seem now, Calpurnia!</LINE>
<LINE>I am ashamed I did yield to them.</LINE>
<LINE>Give me my robe, for I will go.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter PUBLIUS, BRUTUS, LIGARIUS, METELLUS, CASCA,
TREBONIUS, and CINNA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And look where Publius is come to fetch me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good morrow, Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Welcome, Publius.</LINE>
<LINE>What, Brutus, are you stirr'd so early too?</LINE>
<LINE>Good morrow, Casca. Caius Ligarius,</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar was ne'er so much your enemy</LINE>
<LINE>As that same ague which hath made you lean.</LINE>
<LINE>What is 't o'clock?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar, 'tis strucken eight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I thank you for your pains and courtesy.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter ANTONY</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>See! Antony, that revels long o' nights,</LINE>
<LINE>Is notwithstanding up. Good morrow, Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So to most noble Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bid them prepare within:</LINE>
<LINE>I am to blame to be thus waited for.</LINE>
<LINE>Now, Cinna: now, Metellus: what, Trebonius!</LINE>
<LINE>I have an hour's talk in store for you;</LINE>
<LINE>Remember that you call on me to-day:</LINE>
<LINE>Be near me, that I may remember you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TREBONIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar, I will:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>and so near will I be,</LINE>
<LINE>That your best friends shall wish I had been further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good friends, go in, and taste some wine with me;</LINE>
<LINE>And we, like friends, will straightway go together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Aside</STAGEDIR>  That every like is not the same, O Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>The heart of Brutus yearns to think upon!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  A street near the Capitol.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter ARTEMIDORUS, reading a paper</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ARTEMIDORUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Caesar, beware of Brutus; take heed of Cassius;</LINE>
<LINE>come not near Casca; have an eye to Cinna, trust not</LINE>
<LINE>Trebonius: mark well Metellus Cimber: Decius Brutus</LINE>
<LINE>loves thee not: thou hast wronged Caius Ligarius.</LINE>
<LINE>There is but one mind in all these men, and it is</LINE>
<LINE>bent against Caesar. If thou beest not immortal,</LINE>
<LINE>look about you: security gives way to conspiracy.</LINE>
<LINE>The mighty gods defend thee! Thy lover,</LINE>
<LINE>'ARTEMIDORUS.'</LINE>
<LINE>Here will I stand till Caesar pass along,</LINE>
<LINE>And as a suitor will I give him this.</LINE>
<LINE>My heart laments that virtue cannot live</LINE>
<LINE>Out of the teeth of emulation.</LINE>
<LINE>If thou read this, O Caesar, thou mayst live;</LINE>
<LINE>If not, the Fates with traitors do contrive.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE IV.  Another part of the same street, before the house of BRUTUS.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter PORTIA and LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee, boy, run to the senate-house;</LINE>
<LINE>Stay not to answer me, but get thee gone:</LINE>
<LINE>Why dost thou stay?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To know my errand, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would have had thee there, and here again,</LINE>
<LINE>Ere I can tell thee what thou shouldst do there.</LINE>
<LINE>O constancy, be strong upon my side,</LINE>
<LINE>Set a huge mountain 'tween my heart and tongue!</LINE>
<LINE>I have a man's mind, but a woman's might.</LINE>
<LINE>How hard it is for women to keep counsel!</LINE>
<LINE>Art thou here yet?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, what should I do?</LINE>
<LINE>Run to the Capitol, and nothing else?</LINE>
<LINE>And so return to you, and nothing else?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, bring me word, boy, if thy lord look well,</LINE>
<LINE>For he went sickly forth: and take good note</LINE>
<LINE>What Caesar doth, what suitors press to him.</LINE>
<LINE>Hark, boy! what noise is that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hear none, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, listen well;</LINE>
<LINE>I heard a bustling rumour, like a fray,</LINE>
<LINE>And the wind brings it from the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sooth, madam, I hear nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter the Soothsayer</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come hither, fellow: which way hast thou been?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At mine own house, good lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is't o'clock?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>About the ninth hour, lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is Caesar yet gone to the Capitol?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, not yet: I go to take my stand,</LINE>
<LINE>To see him pass on to the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou hast some suit to Caesar, hast thou not?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That I have, lady: if it will please Caesar</LINE>
<LINE>To be so good to Caesar as to hear me,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall beseech him to befriend himself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, know'st thou any harm's intended towards him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>None that I know will be, much that I fear may chance.</LINE>
<LINE>Good morrow to you. Here the street is narrow:</LINE>
<LINE>The throng that follows Caesar at the heels,</LINE>
<LINE>Of senators, of praetors, common suitors,</LINE>
<LINE>Will crowd a feeble man almost to death:</LINE>
<LINE>I'll get me to a place more void, and there</LINE>
<LINE>Speak to great Caesar as he comes along.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PORTIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I must go in. Ay me, how weak a thing</LINE>
<LINE>The heart of woman is! O Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>The heavens speed thee in thine enterprise!</LINE>
<LINE>Sure, the boy heard me: Brutus hath a suit</LINE>
<LINE>That Caesar will not grant. O, I grow faint.</LINE>
<LINE>Run, Lucius, and commend me to my lord;</LINE>
<LINE>Say I am merry: come to me again,</LINE>
<LINE>And bring me word what he doth say to thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt severally</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT III</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Rome. Before the Capitol; the Senate sitting above.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>A crowd of people; among them ARTEMIDORUS and the
Soothsayer. Flourish. Enter CAESAR, BRUTUS,
CASSIUS, CASCA, DECIUS BRUTUS, METELLUS CIMBER,
TREBONIUS, CINNA, ANTONY, LEPIDUS, POPILIUS,
PUBLIUS, and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To the Soothsayer</STAGEDIR>  The ides of March are come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Soothsayer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, Caesar; but not gone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ARTEMIDORUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hail, Caesar! read this schedule.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Trebonius doth desire you to o'erread,</LINE>
<LINE>At your best leisure, this his humble suit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ARTEMIDORUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Caesar, read mine first; for mine's a suit</LINE>
<LINE>That touches Caesar nearer: read it, great Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What touches us ourself shall be last served.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ARTEMIDORUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Delay not, Caesar; read it instantly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, is the fellow mad?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PUBLIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sirrah, give place.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, urge you your petitions in the street?</LINE>
<LINE>Come to the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>CAESAR goes up to the Senate-House, the rest
following</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>POPILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I wish your enterprise to-day may thrive.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What enterprise, Popilius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>POPILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fare you well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Advances to CAESAR</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What said Popilius Lena?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He wish'd to-day our enterprise might thrive.</LINE>
<LINE>I fear our purpose is discovered.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look, how he makes to Caesar; mark him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Casca, be sudden, for we fear prevention.</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus, what shall be done? If this be known,</LINE>
<LINE>Cassius or Caesar never shall turn back,</LINE>
<LINE>For I will slay myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassius, be constant:</LINE>
<LINE>Popilius Lena speaks not of our purposes;</LINE>
<LINE>For, look, he smiles, and Caesar doth not change.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Trebonius knows his time; for, look you, Brutus.</LINE>
<LINE>He draws Mark Antony out of the way.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt ANTONY and TREBONIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is Metellus Cimber? Let him go,</LINE>
<LINE>And presently prefer his suit to Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is address'd: press near and second him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Casca, you are the first that rears your hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are we all ready? What is now amiss</LINE>
<LINE>That Caesar and his senate must redress?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>METELLUS CIMBER</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most high, most mighty, and most puissant Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>Metellus Cimber throws before thy seat</LINE>
<LINE>An humble heart,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Kneeling</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I must prevent thee, Cimber.</LINE>
<LINE>These couchings and these lowly courtesies</LINE>
<LINE>Might fire the blood of ordinary men,</LINE>
<LINE>And turn pre-ordinance and first decree</LINE>
<LINE>Into the law of children. Be not fond,</LINE>
<LINE>To think that Caesar bears such rebel blood</LINE>
<LINE>That will be thaw'd from the true quality</LINE>
<LINE>With that which melteth fools; I mean, sweet words,</LINE>
<LINE>Low-crooked court'sies and base spaniel-fawning.</LINE>
<LINE>Thy brother by decree is banished:</LINE>
<LINE>If thou dost bend and pray and fawn for him,</LINE>
<LINE>I spurn thee like a cur out of my way.</LINE>
<LINE>Know, Caesar doth not wrong, nor without cause</LINE>
<LINE>Will he be satisfied.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>METELLUS CIMBER</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is there no voice more worthy than my own</LINE>
<LINE>To sound more sweetly in great Caesar's ear</LINE>
<LINE>For the repealing of my banish'd brother?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I kiss thy hand, but not in flattery, Caesar;</LINE>
<LINE>Desiring thee that Publius Cimber may</LINE>
<LINE>Have an immediate freedom of repeal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, Brutus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon, Caesar; Caesar, pardon:</LINE>
<LINE>As low as to thy foot doth Cassius fall,</LINE>
<LINE>To beg enfranchisement for Publius Cimber.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I could be well moved, if I were as you:</LINE>
<LINE>If I could pray to move, prayers would move me:</LINE>
<LINE>But I am constant as the northern star,</LINE>
<LINE>Of whose true-fix'd and resting quality</LINE>
<LINE>There is no fellow in the firmament.</LINE>
<LINE>The skies are painted with unnumber'd sparks,</LINE>
<LINE>They are all fire and every one doth shine,</LINE>
<LINE>But there's but one in all doth hold his place:</LINE>
<LINE>So in the world; 'tis furnish'd well with men,</LINE>
<LINE>And men are flesh and blood, and apprehensive;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet in the number I do know but one</LINE>
<LINE>That unassailable holds on his rank,</LINE>
<LINE>Unshaked of motion: and that I am he,</LINE>
<LINE>Let me a little show it, even in this;</LINE>
<LINE>That I was constant Cimber should be banish'd,</LINE>
<LINE>And constant do remain to keep him so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Caesar,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hence! wilt thou lift up Olympus?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Great Caesar,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Doth not Brutus bootless kneel?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Speak, hands for me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>CASCA first, then the other Conspirators and
BRUTUS stab CAESAR</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CAESAR</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Et tu, Brute! Then fall, Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Dies</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Liberty! Freedom! Tyranny is dead!</LINE>
<LINE>Run hence, proclaim, cry it about the streets.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Some to the common pulpits, and cry out</LINE>
<LINE>'Liberty, freedom, and enfranchisement!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>People and senators, be not affrighted;</LINE>
<LINE>Fly not; stand stiff: ambition's debt is paid.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to the pulpit, Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And Cassius too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where's Publius?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, quite confounded with this mutiny.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>METELLUS CIMBER</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand fast together, lest some friend of Caesar's</LINE>
<LINE>Should chance--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Talk not of standing. Publius, good cheer;</LINE>
<LINE>There is no harm intended to your person,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor to no Roman else: so tell them, Publius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And leave us, Publius; lest that the people,</LINE>
<LINE>Rushing on us, should do your age some mischief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do so: and let no man abide this deed,</LINE>
<LINE>But we the doers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter TREBONIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is Antony?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TREBONIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fled to his house amazed:</LINE>
<LINE>Men, wives and children stare, cry out and run</LINE>
<LINE>As it were doomsday.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fates, we will know your pleasures:</LINE>
<LINE>That we shall die, we know; 'tis but the time</LINE>
<LINE>And drawing days out, that men stand upon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, he that cuts off twenty years of life</LINE>
<LINE>Cuts off so many years of fearing death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Grant that, and then is death a benefit:</LINE>
<LINE>So are we Caesar's friends, that have abridged</LINE>
<LINE>His time of fearing death. Stoop, Romans, stoop,</LINE>
<LINE>And let us bathe our hands in Caesar's blood</LINE>
<LINE>Up to the elbows, and besmear our swords:</LINE>
<LINE>Then walk we forth, even to the market-place,</LINE>
<LINE>And, waving our red weapons o'er our heads,</LINE>
<LINE>Let's all cry 'Peace, freedom and liberty!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stoop, then, and wash. How many ages hence</LINE>
<LINE>Shall this our lofty scene be acted over</LINE>
<LINE>In states unborn and accents yet unknown!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How many times shall Caesar bleed in sport,</LINE>
<LINE>That now on Pompey's basis lies along</LINE>
<LINE>No worthier than the dust!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So oft as that shall be,</LINE>
<LINE>So often shall the knot of us be call'd</LINE>
<LINE>The men that gave their country liberty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DECIUS BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, shall we forth?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, every man away:</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus shall lead; and we will grace his heels</LINE>
<LINE>With the most boldest and best hearts of Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter a Servant</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Soft! who comes here? A friend of Antony's.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus, Brutus, did my master bid me kneel:</LINE>
<LINE>Thus did Mark Antony bid me fall down;</LINE>
<LINE>And, being prostrate, thus he bade me say:</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus is noble, wise, valiant, and honest;</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar was mighty, bold, royal, and loving:</LINE>
<LINE>Say I love Brutus, and I honour him;</LINE>
<LINE>Say I fear'd Caesar, honour'd him and loved him.</LINE>
<LINE>If Brutus will vouchsafe that Antony</LINE>
<LINE>May safely come to him, and be resolved</LINE>
<LINE>How Caesar hath deserved to lie in death,</LINE>
<LINE>Mark Antony shall not love Caesar dead</LINE>
<LINE>So well as Brutus living; but will follow</LINE>
<LINE>The fortunes and affairs of noble Brutus</LINE>
<LINE>Thorough the hazards of this untrod state</LINE>
<LINE>With all true faith. So says my master Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy master is a wise and valiant Roman;</LINE>
<LINE>I never thought him worse.</LINE>
<LINE>Tell him, so please him come unto this place,</LINE>
<LINE>He shall be satisfied; and, by my honour,</LINE>
<LINE>Depart untouch'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll fetch him presently.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know that we shall have him well to friend.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I wish we may: but yet have I a mind</LINE>
<LINE>That fears him much; and my misgiving still</LINE>
<LINE>Falls shrewdly to the purpose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But here comes Antony.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter ANTONY</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Welcome, Mark Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O mighty Caesar! dost thou lie so low?</LINE>
<LINE>Are all thy conquests, glories, triumphs, spoils,</LINE>
<LINE>Shrunk to this little measure? Fare thee well.</LINE>
<LINE>I know not, gentlemen, what you intend,</LINE>
<LINE>Who else must be let blood, who else is rank:</LINE>
<LINE>If I myself, there is no hour so fit</LINE>
<LINE>As Caesar's death hour, nor no instrument</LINE>
<LINE>Of half that worth as those your swords, made rich</LINE>
<LINE>With the most noble blood of all this world.</LINE>
<LINE>I do beseech ye, if you bear me hard,</LINE>
<LINE>Now, whilst your purpled hands do reek and smoke,</LINE>
<LINE>Fulfil your pleasure. Live a thousand years,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall not find myself so apt to die:</LINE>
<LINE>No place will please me so, no mean of death,</LINE>
<LINE>As here by Caesar, and by you cut off,</LINE>
<LINE>The choice and master spirits of this age.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Antony, beg not your death of us.</LINE>
<LINE>Though now we must appear bloody and cruel,</LINE>
<LINE>As, by our hands and this our present act,</LINE>
<LINE>You see we do, yet see you but our hands</LINE>
<LINE>And this the bleeding business they have done:</LINE>
<LINE>Our hearts you see not; they are pitiful;</LINE>
<LINE>And pity to the general wrong of Rome--</LINE>
<LINE>As fire drives out fire, so pity pity--</LINE>
<LINE>Hath done this deed on Caesar. For your part,</LINE>
<LINE>To you our swords have leaden points, Mark Antony:</LINE>
<LINE>Our arms, in strength of malice, and our hearts</LINE>
<LINE>Of brothers' temper, do receive you in</LINE>
<LINE>With all kind love, good thoughts, and reverence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your voice shall be as strong as any man's</LINE>
<LINE>In the disposing of new dignities.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Only be patient till we have appeased</LINE>
<LINE>The multitude, beside themselves with fear,</LINE>
<LINE>And then we will deliver you the cause,</LINE>
<LINE>Why I, that did love Caesar when I struck him,</LINE>
<LINE>Have thus proceeded.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I doubt not of your wisdom.</LINE>
<LINE>Let each man render me his bloody hand:</LINE>
<LINE>First, Marcus Brutus, will I shake with you;</LINE>
<LINE>Next, Caius Cassius, do I take your hand;</LINE>
<LINE>Now, Decius Brutus, yours: now yours, Metellus;</LINE>
<LINE>Yours, Cinna; and, my valiant Casca, yours;</LINE>
<LINE>Though last, not last in love, yours, good Trebonius.</LINE>
<LINE>Gentlemen all,--alas, what shall I say?</LINE>
<LINE>My credit now stands on such slippery ground,</LINE>
<LINE>That one of two bad ways you must conceit me,</LINE>
<LINE>Either a coward or a flatterer.</LINE>
<LINE>That I did love thee, Caesar, O, 'tis true:</LINE>
<LINE>If then thy spirit look upon us now,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall it not grieve thee dearer than thy death,</LINE>
<LINE>To see thy thy Anthony making his peace,</LINE>
<LINE>Shaking the bloody fingers of thy foes,</LINE>
<LINE>Most noble! in the presence of thy corse?</LINE>
<LINE>Had I as many eyes as thou hast wounds,</LINE>
<LINE>Weeping as fast as they stream forth thy blood,</LINE>
<LINE>It would become me better than to close</LINE>
<LINE>In terms of friendship with thine enemies.</LINE>
<LINE>Pardon me, Julius! Here wast thou bay'd, brave hart;</LINE>
<LINE>Here didst thou fall; and here thy hunters stand,</LINE>
<LINE>Sign'd in thy spoil, and crimson'd in thy lethe.</LINE>
<LINE>O world, thou wast the forest to this hart;</LINE>
<LINE>And this, indeed, O world, the heart of thee.</LINE>
<LINE>How like a deer, strucken by many princes,</LINE>
<LINE>Dost thou here lie!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark Antony,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon me, Caius Cassius:</LINE>
<LINE>The enemies of Caesar shall say this;</LINE>
<LINE>Then, in a friend, it is cold modesty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I blame you not for praising Caesar so;</LINE>
<LINE>But what compact mean you to have with us?</LINE>
<LINE>Will you be prick'd in number of our friends;</LINE>
<LINE>Or shall we on, and not depend on you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therefore I took your hands, but was, indeed,</LINE>
<LINE>Sway'd from the point, by looking down on Caesar.</LINE>
<LINE>Friends am I with you all and love you all,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon this hope, that you shall give me reasons</LINE>
<LINE>Why and wherein Caesar was dangerous.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Or else were this a savage spectacle:</LINE>
<LINE>Our reasons are so full of good regard</LINE>
<LINE>That were you, Antony, the son of Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>You should be satisfied.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's all I seek:</LINE>
<LINE>And am moreover suitor that I may</LINE>
<LINE>Produce his body to the market-place;</LINE>
<LINE>And in the pulpit, as becomes a friend,</LINE>
<LINE>Speak in the order of his funeral.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall, Mark Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brutus, a word with you.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside to BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>You know not what you do: do not consent</LINE>
<LINE>That Antony speak in his funeral:</LINE>
<LINE>Know you how much the people may be moved</LINE>
<LINE>By that which he will utter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By your pardon;</LINE>
<LINE>I will myself into the pulpit first,</LINE>
<LINE>And show the reason of our Caesar's death:</LINE>
<LINE>What Antony shall speak, I will protest</LINE>
<LINE>He speaks by leave and by permission,</LINE>
<LINE>And that we are contented Caesar shall</LINE>
<LINE>Have all true rites and lawful ceremonies.</LINE>
<LINE>It shall advantage more than do us wrong.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not what may fall; I like it not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark Antony, here, take you Caesar's body.</LINE>
<LINE>You shall not in your funeral speech blame us,</LINE>
<LINE>But speak all good you can devise of Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>And say you do't by our permission;</LINE>
<LINE>Else shall you not have any hand at all</LINE>
<LINE>About his funeral: and you shall speak</LINE>
<LINE>In the same pulpit whereto I am going,</LINE>
<LINE>After my speech is ended.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be it so.</LINE>
<LINE>I do desire no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prepare the body then, and follow us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt all but ANTONY</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, pardon me, thou bleeding piece of earth,</LINE>
<LINE>That I am meek and gentle with these butchers!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art the ruins of the noblest man</LINE>
<LINE>That ever lived in the tide of times.</LINE>
<LINE>Woe to the hand that shed this costly blood!</LINE>
<LINE>Over thy wounds now do I prophesy,--</LINE>
<LINE>Which, like dumb mouths, do ope their ruby lips,</LINE>
<LINE>To beg the voice and utterance of my tongue--</LINE>
<LINE>A curse shall light upon the limbs of men;</LINE>
<LINE>Domestic fury and fierce civil strife</LINE>
<LINE>Shall cumber all the parts of Italy;</LINE>
<LINE>Blood and destruction shall be so in use</LINE>
<LINE>And dreadful objects so familiar</LINE>
<LINE>That mothers shall but smile when they behold</LINE>
<LINE>Their infants quarter'd with the hands of war;</LINE>
<LINE>All pity choked with custom of fell deeds:</LINE>
<LINE>And Caesar's spirit, ranging for revenge,</LINE>
<LINE>With Ate by his side come hot from hell,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall in these confines with a monarch's voice</LINE>
<LINE>Cry  'Havoc,' and let slip the dogs of war;</LINE>
<LINE>That this foul deed shall smell above the earth</LINE>
<LINE>With carrion men, groaning for burial.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a Servant</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>You serve Octavius Caesar, do you not?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do, Mark Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar did write for him to come to Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He did receive his letters, and is coming;</LINE>
<LINE>And bid me say to you by word of mouth--</LINE>
<LINE>O Caesar!--</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Seeing the body</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy heart is big, get thee apart and weep.</LINE>
<LINE>Passion, I see, is catching; for mine eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Seeing those beads of sorrow stand in thine,</LINE>
<LINE>Began to water. Is thy master coming?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He lies to-night within seven leagues of Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Post back with speed, and tell him what hath chanced:</LINE>
<LINE>Here is a mourning Rome, a dangerous Rome,</LINE>
<LINE>No Rome of safety for Octavius yet;</LINE>
<LINE>Hie hence, and tell him so. Yet, stay awhile;</LINE>
<LINE>Thou shalt not back till I have borne this corse</LINE>
<LINE>Into the market-place: there shall I try</LINE>
<LINE>In my oration, how the people take</LINE>
<LINE>The cruel issue of these bloody men;</LINE>
<LINE>According to the which, thou shalt discourse</LINE>
<LINE>To young Octavius of the state of things.</LINE>
<LINE>Lend me your hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt with CAESAR's body</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  The Forum.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter BRUTUS and CASSIUS, and a throng of Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will be satisfied; let us be satisfied.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then follow me, and give me audience, friends.</LINE>
<LINE>Cassius, go you into the other street,</LINE>
<LINE>And part the numbers.</LINE>
<LINE>Those that will hear me speak, let 'em stay here;</LINE>
<LINE>Those that will follow Cassius, go with him;</LINE>
<LINE>And public reasons shall be rendered</LINE>
<LINE>Of Caesar's death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will hear Brutus speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will hear Cassius; and compare their reasons,</LINE>
<LINE>When severally we hear them rendered.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit CASSIUS, with some of the Citizens. BRUTUS
goes into the pulpit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The noble Brutus is ascended: silence!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be patient till the last.</LINE>
<LINE>Romans, countrymen, and lovers! hear me for my</LINE>
<LINE>cause, and be silent, that you may hear: believe me</LINE>
<LINE>for mine honour, and have respect to mine honour, that</LINE>
<LINE>you may believe: censure me in your wisdom, and</LINE>
<LINE>awake your senses, that you may the better judge.</LINE>
<LINE>If there be any in this assembly, any dear friend of</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar's, to him I say, that Brutus' love to Caesar</LINE>
<LINE>was no less than his. If then that friend demand</LINE>
<LINE>why Brutus rose against Caesar, this is my answer:</LINE>
<LINE>--Not that I loved Caesar less, but that I loved</LINE>
<LINE>Rome more. Had you rather Caesar were living and</LINE>
<LINE>die all slaves, than that Caesar were dead, to live</LINE>
<LINE>all free men? As Caesar loved me, I weep for him;</LINE>
<LINE>as he was fortunate, I rejoice at it; as he was</LINE>
<LINE>valiant, I honour him: but, as he was ambitious, I</LINE>
<LINE>slew him. There is tears for his love; joy for his</LINE>
<LINE>fortune; honour for his valour; and death for his</LINE>
<LINE>ambition. Who is here so base that would be a</LINE>
<LINE>bondman? If any, speak; for him have I offended.</LINE>
<LINE>Who is here so rude that would not be a Roman? If</LINE>
<LINE>any, speak; for him have I offended. Who is here so</LINE>
<LINE>vile that will not love his country? If any, speak;</LINE>
<LINE>for him have I offended. I pause for a reply.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>None, Brutus, none.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then none have I offended. I have done no more to</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar than you shall do to Brutus. The question of</LINE>
<LINE>his death is enrolled in the Capitol; his glory not</LINE>
<LINE>extenuated, wherein he was worthy, nor his offences</LINE>
<LINE>enforced, for which he suffered death.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter ANTONY and others, with CAESAR's body</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Here comes his body, mourned by Mark Antony: who,</LINE>
<LINE>though he had no hand in his death, shall receive</LINE>
<LINE>the benefit of his dying, a place in the</LINE>
<LINE>commonwealth; as which of you shall not? With this</LINE>
<LINE>I depart,--that, as I slew my best lover for the</LINE>
<LINE>good of Rome, I have the same dagger for myself,</LINE>
<LINE>when it shall please my country to need my death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Live, Brutus! live, live!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bring him with triumph home unto his house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give him a statue with his ancestors.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let him be Caesar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar's better parts</LINE>
<LINE>Shall be crown'd in Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll bring him to his house</LINE>
<LINE>With shouts and clamours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My countrymen,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, silence! Brutus speaks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good countrymen, let me depart alone,</LINE>
<LINE>And, for my sake, stay here with Antony:</LINE>
<LINE>Do grace to Caesar's corpse, and grace his speech</LINE>
<LINE>Tending to Caesar's glories; which Mark Antony,</LINE>
<LINE>By our permission, is allow'd to make.</LINE>
<LINE>I do entreat you, not a man depart,</LINE>
<LINE>Save I alone, till Antony have spoke.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stay, ho! and let us hear Mark Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let him go up into the public chair;</LINE>
<LINE>We'll hear him. Noble Antony, go up.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For Brutus' sake, I am beholding to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Goes into the pulpit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What does he say of Brutus?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He says, for Brutus' sake,</LINE>
<LINE>He finds himself beholding to us all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Twere best he speak no harm of Brutus here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This Caesar was a tyrant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, that's certain:</LINE>
<LINE>We are blest that Rome is rid of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace! let us hear what Antony can say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You gentle Romans,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, ho! let us hear him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears;</LINE>
<LINE>I come to bury Caesar, not to praise him.</LINE>
<LINE>The evil that men do lives after them;</LINE>
<LINE>The good is oft interred with their bones;</LINE>
<LINE>So let it be with Caesar. The noble Brutus</LINE>
<LINE>Hath told you Caesar was ambitious:</LINE>
<LINE>If it were so, it was a grievous fault,</LINE>
<LINE>And grievously hath Caesar answer'd it.</LINE>
<LINE>Here, under leave of Brutus and the rest--</LINE>
<LINE>For Brutus is an honourable man;</LINE>
<LINE>So are they all, all honourable men--</LINE>
<LINE>Come I to speak in Caesar's funeral.</LINE>
<LINE>He was my friend, faithful and just to me:</LINE>
<LINE>But Brutus says he was ambitious;</LINE>
<LINE>And Brutus is an honourable man.</LINE>
<LINE>He hath brought many captives home to Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Whose ransoms did the general coffers fill:</LINE>
<LINE>Did this in Caesar seem ambitious?</LINE>
<LINE>When that the poor have cried, Caesar hath wept:</LINE>
<LINE>Ambition should be made of sterner stuff:</LINE>
<LINE>Yet Brutus says he was ambitious;</LINE>
<LINE>And Brutus is an honourable man.</LINE>
<LINE>You all did see that on the Lupercal</LINE>
<LINE>I thrice presented him a kingly crown,</LINE>
<LINE>Which he did thrice refuse: was this ambition?</LINE>
<LINE>Yet Brutus says he was ambitious;</LINE>
<LINE>And, sure, he is an honourable man.</LINE>
<LINE>I speak not to disprove what Brutus spoke,</LINE>
<LINE>But here I am to speak what I do know.</LINE>
<LINE>You all did love him once, not without cause:</LINE>
<LINE>What cause withholds you then, to mourn for him?</LINE>
<LINE>O judgment! thou art fled to brutish beasts,</LINE>
<LINE>And men have lost their reason. Bear with me;</LINE>
<LINE>My heart is in the coffin there with Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>And I must pause till it come back to me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Methinks there is much reason in his sayings.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If thou consider rightly of the matter,</LINE>
<LINE>Caesar has had great wrong.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has he, masters?</LINE>
<LINE>I fear there will a worse come in his place.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark'd ye his words? He would not take the crown;</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore 'tis certain he was not ambitious.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it be found so, some will dear abide it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Poor soul! his eyes are red as fire with weeping.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There's not a nobler man in Rome than Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now mark him, he begins again to speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But yesterday the word of Caesar might</LINE>
<LINE>Have stood against the world; now lies he there.</LINE>
<LINE>And none so poor to do him reverence.</LINE>
<LINE>O masters, if I were disposed to stir</LINE>
<LINE>Your hearts and minds to mutiny and rage,</LINE>
<LINE>I should do Brutus wrong, and Cassius wrong,</LINE>
<LINE>Who, you all know, are honourable men:</LINE>
<LINE>I will not do them wrong; I rather choose</LINE>
<LINE>To wrong the dead, to wrong myself and you,</LINE>
<LINE>Than I will wrong such honourable men.</LINE>
<LINE>But here's a parchment with the seal of Caesar;</LINE>
<LINE>I found it in his closet, 'tis his will:</LINE>
<LINE>Let but the commons hear this testament--</LINE>
<LINE>Which, pardon me, I do not mean to read--</LINE>
<LINE>And they would go and kiss dead Caesar's wounds</LINE>
<LINE>And dip their napkins in his sacred blood,</LINE>
<LINE>Yea, beg a hair of him for memory,</LINE>
<LINE>And, dying, mention it within their wills,</LINE>
<LINE>Bequeathing it as a rich legacy</LINE>
<LINE>Unto their issue.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll hear the will: read it, Mark Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The will, the will! we will hear Caesar's will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have patience, gentle friends, I must not read it;</LINE>
<LINE>It is not meet you know how Caesar loved you.</LINE>
<LINE>You are not wood, you are not stones, but men;</LINE>
<LINE>And, being men, bearing the will of Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>It will inflame you, it will make you mad:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis good you know not that you are his heirs;</LINE>
<LINE>For, if you should, O, what would come of it!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Read the will; we'll hear it, Antony;</LINE>
<LINE>You shall read us the will, Caesar's will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you be patient? will you stay awhile?</LINE>
<LINE>I have o'ershot myself to tell you of it:</LINE>
<LINE>I fear I wrong the honourable men</LINE>
<LINE>Whose daggers have stabb'd Caesar; I do fear it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They were traitors: honourable men!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The will! the testament!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They were villains, murderers: the will! read the will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You will compel me, then, to read the will?</LINE>
<LINE>Then make a ring about the corpse of Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>And let me show you him that made the will.</LINE>
<LINE>Shall I descend? and will you give me leave?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Several Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come down.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Descend.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall have leave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>ANTONY comes down</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A ring; stand round.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand from the hearse, stand from the body.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Room for Antony, most noble Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, press not so upon me; stand far off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Several Citizens</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand back; room; bear back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you have tears, prepare to shed them now.</LINE>
<LINE>You all do know this mantle: I remember</LINE>
<LINE>The first time ever Caesar put it on;</LINE>
<LINE>'Twas on a summer's evening, in his tent,</LINE>
<LINE>That day he overcame the Nervii:</LINE>
<LINE>Look, in this place ran Cassius' dagger through:</LINE>
<LINE>See what a rent the envious Casca made:</LINE>
<LINE>Through this the well-beloved Brutus stabb'd;</LINE>
<LINE>And as he pluck'd his cursed steel away,</LINE>
<LINE>Mark how the blood of Caesar follow'd it,</LINE>
<LINE>As rushing out of doors, to be resolved</LINE>
<LINE>If Brutus so unkindly knock'd, or no;</LINE>
<LINE>For Brutus, as you know, was Caesar's angel:</LINE>
<LINE>Judge, O you gods, how dearly Caesar loved him!</LINE>
<LINE>This was the most unkindest cut of all;</LINE>
<LINE>For when the noble Caesar saw him stab,</LINE>
<LINE>Ingratitude, more strong than traitors' arms,</LINE>
<LINE>Quite vanquish'd him: then burst his mighty heart;</LINE>
<LINE>And, in his mantle muffling up his face,</LINE>
<LINE>Even at the base of Pompey's statua,</LINE>
<LINE>Which all the while ran blood, great Caesar fell.</LINE>
<LINE>O, what a fall was there, my countrymen!</LINE>
<LINE>Then I, and you, and all of us fell down,</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst bloody treason flourish'd over us.</LINE>
<LINE>O, now you weep; and, I perceive, you feel</LINE>
<LINE>The dint of pity: these are gracious drops.</LINE>
<LINE>Kind souls, what, weep you when you but behold</LINE>
<LINE>Our Caesar's vesture wounded? Look you here,</LINE>
<LINE>Here is himself, marr'd, as you see, with traitors.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O piteous spectacle!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O noble Caesar!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O woful day!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O traitors, villains!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O most bloody sight!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We will be revenged.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Revenge! About! Seek! Burn! Fire! Kill! Slay!</LINE>
<LINE>Let not a traitor live!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stay, countrymen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace there! hear the noble Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll hear him, we'll follow him, we'll die with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good friends, sweet friends, let me not stir you up</LINE>
<LINE>To such a sudden flood of mutiny.</LINE>
<LINE>They that have done this deed are honourable:</LINE>
<LINE>What private griefs they have, alas, I know not,</LINE>
<LINE>That made them do it: they are wise and honourable,</LINE>
<LINE>And will, no doubt, with reasons answer you.</LINE>
<LINE>I come not, friends, to steal away your hearts:</LINE>
<LINE>I am no orator, as Brutus is;</LINE>
<LINE>But, as you know me all, a plain blunt man,</LINE>
<LINE>That love my friend; and that they know full well</LINE>
<LINE>That gave me public leave to speak of him:</LINE>
<LINE>For I have neither wit, nor words, nor worth,</LINE>
<LINE>Action, nor utterance, nor the power of speech,</LINE>
<LINE>To stir men's blood: I only speak right on;</LINE>
<LINE>I tell you that which you yourselves do know;</LINE>
<LINE>Show you sweet Caesar's wounds, poor poor dumb mouths,</LINE>
<LINE>And bid them speak for me: but were I Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>And Brutus Antony, there were an Antony</LINE>
<LINE>Would ruffle up your spirits and put a tongue</LINE>
<LINE>In every wound of Caesar that should move</LINE>
<LINE>The stones of Rome to rise and mutiny.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll mutiny.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll burn the house of Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away, then! come, seek the conspirators.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet hear me, countrymen; yet hear me speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, ho! Hear Antony. Most noble Antony!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, friends, you go to do you know not what:</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein hath Caesar thus deserved your loves?</LINE>
<LINE>Alas, you know not: I must tell you then:</LINE>
<LINE>You have forgot the will I told you of.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most true. The will! Let's stay and hear the will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is the will, and under Caesar's seal.</LINE>
<LINE>To every Roman citizen he gives,</LINE>
<LINE>To every several man, seventy-five drachmas.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most noble Caesar! We'll revenge his death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O royal Caesar!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear me with patience.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Moreover, he hath left you all his walks,</LINE>
<LINE>His private arbours and new-planted orchards,</LINE>
<LINE>On this side Tiber; he hath left them you,</LINE>
<LINE>And to your heirs for ever, common pleasures,</LINE>
<LINE>To walk abroad, and recreate yourselves.</LINE>
<LINE>Here was a Caesar! when comes such another?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never, never. Come, away, away!</LINE>
<LINE>We'll burn his body in the holy place,</LINE>
<LINE>And with the brands fire the traitors' houses.</LINE>
<LINE>Take up the body.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go fetch fire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pluck down benches.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pluck down forms, windows, any thing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Citizens with the body</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now let it work. Mischief, thou art afoot,</LINE>
<LINE>Take thou what course thou wilt!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a Servant</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now, fellow!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, Octavius is already come to Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He and Lepidus are at Caesar's house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And thither will I straight to visit him:</LINE>
<LINE>He comes upon a wish. Fortune is merry,</LINE>
<LINE>And in this mood will give us any thing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Servant</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I heard him say, Brutus and Cassius</LINE>
<LINE>Are rid like madmen through the gates of Rome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Belike they had some notice of the people,</LINE>
<LINE>How I had moved them. Bring me to Octavius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CINNA the poet</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I dreamt to-night that I did feast with Caesar,</LINE>
<LINE>And things unlucky charge my fantasy:</LINE>
<LINE>I have no will to wander forth of doors,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet something leads me forth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter Citizens</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is your name?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whither are you going?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where do you dwell?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you a married man or a bachelor?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Answer every man directly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and briefly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and wisely.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and truly, you were best.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is my name? Whither am I going? Where do I</LINE>
<LINE>dwell? Am I a married man or a bachelor? Then, to</LINE>
<LINE>answer every man directly and briefly, wisely and</LINE>
<LINE>truly: wisely I say, I am a bachelor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's as much as to say, they are fools that marry:</LINE>
<LINE>you'll bear me a bang for that, I fear. Proceed; directly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Directly, I am going to Caesar's funeral.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As a friend or an enemy?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As a friend.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That matter is answered directly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For your dwelling,--briefly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Briefly, I dwell by the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your name, sir, truly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, my name is Cinna.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tear him to pieces; he's a conspirator.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am Cinna the poet, I am Cinna the poet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tear him for his bad verses, tear him for his bad verses.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CINNA THE POET</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not Cinna the conspirator.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is no matter, his name's Cinna; pluck but his</LINE>
<LINE>name out of his heart, and turn him going.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Citizen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tear him, tear him! Come, brands ho! fire-brands:</LINE>
<LINE>to Brutus', to Cassius'; burn all: some to Decius'</LINE>
<LINE>house, and some to Casca's; some to Ligarius': away, go!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT IV</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  A house in Rome.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>ANTONY, OCTAVIUS, and LEPIDUS, seated at a table</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These many, then, shall die; their names are prick'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your brother too must die; consent you, Lepidus?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEPIDUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do consent--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prick him down, Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEPIDUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Upon condition Publius shall not live,</LINE>
<LINE>Who is your sister's son, Mark Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He shall not live; look, with a spot I damn him.</LINE>
<LINE>But, Lepidus, go you to Caesar's house;</LINE>
<LINE>Fetch the will hither, and we shall determine</LINE>
<LINE>How to cut off some charge in legacies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LEPIDUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, shall I find you here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Or here, or at the Capitol.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit LEPIDUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is a slight unmeritable man,</LINE>
<LINE>Meet to be sent on errands: is it fit,</LINE>
<LINE>The three-fold world divided, he should stand</LINE>
<LINE>One of the three to share it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So you thought him;</LINE>
<LINE>And took his voice who should be prick'd to die,</LINE>
<LINE>In our black sentence and proscription.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Octavius, I have seen more days than you:</LINE>
<LINE>And though we lay these honours on this man,</LINE>
<LINE>To ease ourselves of divers slanderous loads,</LINE>
<LINE>He shall but bear them as the ass bears gold,</LINE>
<LINE>To groan and sweat under the business,</LINE>
<LINE>Either led or driven, as we point the way;</LINE>
<LINE>And having brought our treasure where we will,</LINE>
<LINE>Then take we down his load, and turn him off,</LINE>
<LINE>Like to the empty ass, to shake his ears,</LINE>
<LINE>And graze in commons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You may do your will;</LINE>
<LINE>But he's a tried and valiant soldier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So is my horse, Octavius; and for that</LINE>
<LINE>I do appoint him store of provender:</LINE>
<LINE>It is a creature that I teach to fight,</LINE>
<LINE>To wind, to stop, to run directly on,</LINE>
<LINE>His corporal motion govern'd by my spirit.</LINE>
<LINE>And, in some taste, is Lepidus but so;</LINE>
<LINE>He must be taught and train'd and bid go forth;</LINE>
<LINE>A barren-spirited fellow; one that feeds</LINE>
<LINE>On abjects, orts and imitations,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, out of use and staled by other men,</LINE>
<LINE>Begin his fashion: do not talk of him,</LINE>
<LINE>But as a property. And now, Octavius,</LINE>
<LINE>Listen great things:--Brutus and Cassius</LINE>
<LINE>Are levying powers: we must straight make head:</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore let our alliance be combined,</LINE>
<LINE>Our best friends made, our means stretch'd</LINE>
<LINE>And let us presently go sit in council,</LINE>
<LINE>How covert matters may be best disclosed,</LINE>
<LINE>And open perils surest answered.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let us do so: for we are at the stake,</LINE>
<LINE>And bay'd about with many enemies;</LINE>
<LINE>And some that smile have in their hearts, I fear,</LINE>
<LINE>Millions of mischiefs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  Camp near Sardis. Before BRUTUS's tent.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Drum. Enter BRUTUS, LUCILIUS, LUCIUS, and
Soldiers; TITINIUS and PINDARUS meeting them</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give the word, ho! and stand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What now, Lucilius! is Cassius near?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is at hand; and Pindarus is come</LINE>
<LINE>To do you salutation from his master.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He greets me well. Your master, Pindarus,</LINE>
<LINE>In his own change, or by ill officers,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath given me some worthy cause to wish</LINE>
<LINE>Things done, undone: but, if he be at hand,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall be satisfied.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PINDARUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not doubt</LINE>
<LINE>But that my noble master will appear</LINE>
<LINE>Such as he is, full of regard and honour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is not doubted. A word, Lucilius;</LINE>
<LINE>How he received you, let me be resolved.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With courtesy and with respect enough;</LINE>
<LINE>But not with such familiar instances,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor with such free and friendly conference,</LINE>
<LINE>As he hath used of old.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou hast described</LINE>
<LINE>A hot friend cooling: ever note, Lucilius,</LINE>
<LINE>When love begins to sicken and decay,</LINE>
<LINE>It useth an enforced ceremony.</LINE>
<LINE>There are no tricks in plain and simple faith;</LINE>
<LINE>But hollow men, like horses hot at hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Make gallant show and promise of their mettle;</LINE>
<LINE>But when they should endure the bloody spur,</LINE>
<LINE>They fall their crests, and, like deceitful jades,</LINE>
<LINE>Sink in the trial. Comes his army on?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They mean this night in Sardis to be quarter'd;</LINE>
<LINE>The greater part, the horse in general,</LINE>
<LINE>Are come with Cassius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hark! he is arrived.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Low march within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>March gently on to meet him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIUS and his powers</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand, ho! Speak the word along.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most noble brother, you have done me wrong.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Judge me, you gods! wrong I mine enemies?</LINE>
<LINE>And, if not so, how should I wrong a brother?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brutus, this sober form of yours hides wrongs;</LINE>
<LINE>And when you do them--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassius, be content.</LINE>
<LINE>Speak your griefs softly: I do know you well.</LINE>
<LINE>Before the eyes of both our armies here,</LINE>
<LINE>Which should perceive nothing but love from us,</LINE>
<LINE>Let us not wrangle: bid them move away;</LINE>
<LINE>Then in my tent, Cassius, enlarge your griefs,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will give you audience.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pindarus,</LINE>
<LINE>Bid our commanders lead their charges off</LINE>
<LINE>A little from this ground.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lucilius, do you the like; and let no man</LINE>
<LINE>Come to our tent till we have done our conference.</LINE>
<LINE>Let Lucius and Titinius guard our door.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  Brutus's tent.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter BRUTUS and CASSIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That you have wrong'd me doth appear in this:</LINE>
<LINE>You have condemn'd and noted Lucius Pella</LINE>
<LINE>For taking bribes here of the Sardians;</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein my letters, praying on his side,</LINE>
<LINE>Because I knew the man, were slighted off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You wronged yourself to write in such a case.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In such a time as this it is not meet</LINE>
<LINE>That every nice offence should bear his comment.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me tell you, Cassius, you yourself</LINE>
<LINE>Are much condemn'd to have an itching palm;</LINE>
<LINE>To sell and mart your offices for gold</LINE>
<LINE>To undeservers.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I an itching palm!</LINE>
<LINE>You know that you are Brutus that speak this,</LINE>
<LINE>Or, by the gods, this speech were else your last.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The name of Cassius honours this corruption,</LINE>
<LINE>And chastisement doth therefore hide his head.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Chastisement!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Remember March, the ides of March remember:</LINE>
<LINE>Did not great Julius bleed for justice' sake?</LINE>
<LINE>What villain touch'd his body, that did stab,</LINE>
<LINE>And not for justice? What, shall one of us</LINE>
<LINE>That struck the foremost man of all this world</LINE>
<LINE>But for supporting robbers, shall we now</LINE>
<LINE>Contaminate our fingers with base bribes,</LINE>
<LINE>And sell the mighty space of our large honours</LINE>
<LINE>For so much trash as may be grasped thus?</LINE>
<LINE>I had rather be a dog, and bay the moon,</LINE>
<LINE>Than such a Roman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brutus, bay not me;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll not endure it: you forget yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>To hedge me in; I am a soldier, I,</LINE>
<LINE>Older in practise, abler than yourself</LINE>
<LINE>To make conditions.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to; you are not, Cassius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I say you are not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Urge me no more, I shall forget myself;</LINE>
<LINE>Have mind upon your health, tempt me no further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away, slight man!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't possible?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear me, for I will speak.</LINE>
<LINE>Must I give way and room to your rash choler?</LINE>
<LINE>Shall I be frighted when a madman stares?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O ye gods, ye gods! must I endure all this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All this! ay, more: fret till your proud heart break;</LINE>
<LINE>Go show your slaves how choleric you are,</LINE>
<LINE>And make your bondmen tremble. Must I budge?</LINE>
<LINE>Must I observe you? must I stand and crouch</LINE>
<LINE>Under your testy humour? By the gods</LINE>
<LINE>You shall digest the venom of your spleen,</LINE>
<LINE>Though it do split you; for, from this day forth,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll use you for my mirth, yea, for my laughter,</LINE>
<LINE>When you are waspish.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is it come to this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You say you are a better soldier:</LINE>
<LINE>Let it appear so; make your vaunting true,</LINE>
<LINE>And it shall please me well: for mine own part,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall be glad to learn of noble men.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You wrong me every way; you wrong me, Brutus;</LINE>
<LINE>I said, an elder soldier, not a better:</LINE>
<LINE>Did I say 'better'?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you did, I care not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When Caesar lived, he durst not thus have moved me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, peace! you durst not so have tempted him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I durst not!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, durst not tempt him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For your life you durst not!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not presume too much upon my love;</LINE>
<LINE>I may do that I shall be sorry for.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have done that you should be sorry for.</LINE>
<LINE>There is no terror, Cassius, in your threats,</LINE>
<LINE>For I am arm'd so strong in honesty</LINE>
<LINE>That they pass by me as the idle wind,</LINE>
<LINE>Which I respect not. I did send to you</LINE>
<LINE>For certain sums of gold, which you denied me:</LINE>
<LINE>For I can raise no money by vile means:</LINE>
<LINE>By heaven, I had rather coin my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>And drop my blood for drachmas, than to wring</LINE>
<LINE>From the hard hands of peasants their vile trash</LINE>
<LINE>By any indirection: I did send</LINE>
<LINE>To you for gold to pay my legions,</LINE>
<LINE>Which you denied me: was that done like Cassius?</LINE>
<LINE>Should I have answer'd Caius Cassius so?</LINE>
<LINE>When Marcus Brutus grows so covetous,</LINE>
<LINE>To lock such rascal counters from his friends,</LINE>
<LINE>Be ready, gods, with all your thunderbolts;</LINE>
<LINE>Dash him to pieces!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I denied you not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You did.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I did not: he was but a fool that brought</LINE>
<LINE>My answer back. Brutus hath rived my heart:</LINE>
<LINE>A friend should bear his friend's infirmities,</LINE>
<LINE>But Brutus makes mine greater than they are.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not, till you practise them on me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You love me not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not like your faults.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A friendly eye could never see such faults.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A flatterer's would not, though they do appear</LINE>
<LINE>As huge as high Olympus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, Antony, and young Octavius, come,</LINE>
<LINE>Revenge yourselves alone on Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>For Cassius is aweary of the world;</LINE>
<LINE>Hated by one he loves; braved by his brother;</LINE>
<LINE>Cheque'd like a bondman; all his faults observed,</LINE>
<LINE>Set in a note-book, learn'd, and conn'd by rote,</LINE>
<LINE>To cast into my teeth. O, I could weep</LINE>
<LINE>My spirit from mine eyes! There is my dagger,</LINE>
<LINE>And here my naked breast; within, a heart</LINE>
<LINE>Dearer than Plutus' mine, richer than gold:</LINE>
<LINE>If that thou be'st a Roman, take it forth;</LINE>
<LINE>I, that denied thee gold, will give my heart:</LINE>
<LINE>Strike, as thou didst at Caesar; for, I know,</LINE>
<LINE>When thou didst hate him worst, thou lovedst him better</LINE>
<LINE>Than ever thou lovedst Cassius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sheathe your dagger:</LINE>
<LINE>Be angry when you will, it shall have scope;</LINE>
<LINE>Do what you will, dishonour shall be humour.</LINE>
<LINE>O Cassius, you are yoked with a lamb</LINE>
<LINE>That carries anger as the flint bears fire;</LINE>
<LINE>Who, much enforced, shows a hasty spark,</LINE>
<LINE>And straight is cold again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath Cassius lived</LINE>
<LINE>To be but mirth and laughter to his Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>When grief, and blood ill-temper'd, vexeth him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>When I spoke that, I was ill-temper'd too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you confess so much? Give me your hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And my heart too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Brutus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have not you love enough to bear with me,</LINE>
<LINE>When that rash humour which my mother gave me</LINE>
<LINE>Makes me forgetful?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, Cassius; and, from henceforth,</LINE>
<LINE>When you are over-earnest with your Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>He'll think your mother chides, and leave you so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Poet</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  Let me go in to see the generals;</LINE>
<LINE>There is some grudge between 'em, 'tis not meet</LINE>
<LINE>They be alone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  You shall not come to them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Poet</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  Nothing but death shall stay me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter Poet, followed by LUCILIUS, TITINIUS, and LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now! what's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Poet</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For shame, you generals! what do you mean?</LINE>
<LINE>Love, and be friends, as two such men should be;</LINE>
<LINE>For I have seen more years, I'm sure, than ye.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha, ha! how vilely doth this cynic rhyme!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get you hence, sirrah; saucy fellow, hence!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bear with him, Brutus; 'tis his fashion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll know his humour, when he knows his time:</LINE>
<LINE>What should the wars do with these jigging fools?</LINE>
<LINE>Companion, hence!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away, away, be gone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit Poet</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lucilius and Titinius, bid the commanders</LINE>
<LINE>Prepare to lodge their companies to-night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And come yourselves, and bring Messala with you</LINE>
<LINE>Immediately to us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt LUCILIUS and TITINIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lucius, a bowl of wine!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I did not think you could have been so angry.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Cassius, I am sick of many griefs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Of your philosophy you make no use,</LINE>
<LINE>If you give place to accidental evils.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No man bears sorrow better. Portia is dead.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! Portia!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She is dead.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How 'scaped I killing when I cross'd you so?</LINE>
<LINE>O insupportable and touching loss!</LINE>
<LINE>Upon what sickness?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Impatient of my absence,</LINE>
<LINE>And grief that young Octavius with Mark Antony</LINE>
<LINE>Have made themselves so strong:--for with her death</LINE>
<LINE>That tidings came;--with this she fell distract,</LINE>
<LINE>And, her attendants absent, swallow'd fire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And died so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O ye immortal gods!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter LUCIUS, with wine and taper</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Speak no more of her. Give me a bowl of wine.</LINE>
<LINE>In this I bury all unkindness, Cassius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My heart is thirsty for that noble pledge.</LINE>
<LINE>Fill, Lucius, till the wine o'erswell the cup;</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot drink too much of Brutus' love.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come in, Titinius!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter TITINIUS, with MESSALA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Welcome, good Messala.</LINE>
<LINE>Now sit we close about this taper here,</LINE>
<LINE>And call in question our necessities.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Portia, art thou gone?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more, I pray you.</LINE>
<LINE>Messala, I have here received letters,</LINE>
<LINE>That young Octavius and Mark Antony</LINE>
<LINE>Come down upon us with a mighty power,</LINE>
<LINE>Bending their expedition toward Philippi.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Myself have letters of the selfsame tenor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With what addition?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That by proscription and bills of outlawry,</LINE>
<LINE>Octavius, Antony, and Lepidus,</LINE>
<LINE>Have put to death an hundred senators.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Therein our letters do not well agree;</LINE>
<LINE>Mine speak of seventy senators that died</LINE>
<LINE>By their proscriptions, Cicero being one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cicero one!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cicero is dead,</LINE>
<LINE>And by that order of proscription.</LINE>
<LINE>Had you your letters from your wife, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, Messala.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor nothing in your letters writ of her?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing, Messala.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That, methinks, is strange.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why ask you? hear you aught of her in yours?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, as you are a Roman, tell me true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then like a Roman bear the truth I tell:</LINE>
<LINE>For certain she is dead, and by strange manner.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, farewell, Portia. We must die, Messala:</LINE>
<LINE>With meditating that she must die once,</LINE>
<LINE>I have the patience to endure it now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even so great men great losses should endure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have as much of this in art as you,</LINE>
<LINE>But yet my nature could not bear it so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, to our work alive. What do you think</LINE>
<LINE>Of marching to Philippi presently?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not think it good.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your reason?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This it is:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis better that the enemy seek us:</LINE>
<LINE>So shall he waste his means, weary his soldiers,</LINE>
<LINE>Doing himself offence; whilst we, lying still,</LINE>
<LINE>Are full of rest, defense, and nimbleness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good reasons must, of force, give place to better.</LINE>
<LINE>The people 'twixt Philippi and this ground</LINE>
<LINE>Do stand but in a forced affection;</LINE>
<LINE>For they have grudged us contribution:</LINE>
<LINE>The enemy, marching along by them,</LINE>
<LINE>By them shall make a fuller number up,</LINE>
<LINE>Come on refresh'd, new-added, and encouraged;</LINE>
<LINE>From which advantage shall we cut him off,</LINE>
<LINE>If at Philippi we do face him there,</LINE>
<LINE>These people at our back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hear me, good brother.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Under your pardon. You must note beside,</LINE>
<LINE>That we have tried the utmost of our friends,</LINE>
<LINE>Our legions are brim-full, our cause is ripe:</LINE>
<LINE>The enemy increaseth every day;</LINE>
<LINE>We, at the height, are ready to decline.</LINE>
<LINE>There is a tide in the affairs of men,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, taken at the flood, leads on to fortune;</LINE>
<LINE>Omitted, all the voyage of their life</LINE>
<LINE>Is bound in shallows and in miseries.</LINE>
<LINE>On such a full sea are we now afloat;</LINE>
<LINE>And we must take the current when it serves,</LINE>
<LINE>Or lose our ventures.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then, with your will, go on;</LINE>
<LINE>We'll along ourselves, and meet them at Philippi.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The deep of night is crept upon our talk,</LINE>
<LINE>And nature must obey necessity;</LINE>
<LINE>Which we will niggard with a little rest.</LINE>
<LINE>There is no more to say?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more. Good night:</LINE>
<LINE>Early to-morrow will we rise, and hence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lucius!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>My gown.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit LUCIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Farewell, good Messala:</LINE>
<LINE>Good night, Titinius. Noble, noble Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>Good night, and good repose.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my dear brother!</LINE>
<LINE>This was an ill beginning of the night:</LINE>
<LINE>Never come such division 'tween our souls!</LINE>
<LINE>Let it not, Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Every thing is well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good night, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good night, good brother.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good night, Lord Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, every one.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt all but BRUTUS</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter LUCIUS, with the gown</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Give me the gown. Where is thy instrument?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here in the tent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, thou speak'st drowsily?</LINE>
<LINE>Poor knave, I blame thee not; thou art o'er-watch'd.</LINE>
<LINE>Call Claudius and some other of my men:</LINE>
<LINE>I'll have them sleep on cushions in my tent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Varro and Claudius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter VARRO and CLAUDIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VARRO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Calls my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you, sirs, lie in my tent and sleep;</LINE>
<LINE>It may be I shall raise you by and by</LINE>
<LINE>On business to my brother Cassius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VARRO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So please you, we will stand and watch your pleasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not have it so: lie down, good sirs;</LINE>
<LINE>It may be I shall otherwise bethink me.</LINE>
<LINE>Look, Lucius, here's the book I sought for so;</LINE>
<LINE>I put it in the pocket of my gown.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>VARRO and CLAUDIUS lie down</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I was sure your lordship did not give it me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bear with me, good boy, I am much forgetful.</LINE>
<LINE>Canst thou hold up thy heavy eyes awhile,</LINE>
<LINE>And touch thy instrument a strain or two?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, my lord, an't please you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It does, my boy:</LINE>
<LINE>I trouble thee too much, but thou art willing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is my duty, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I should not urge thy duty past thy might;</LINE>
<LINE>I know young bloods look for a time of rest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have slept, my lord, already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It was well done; and thou shalt sleep again;</LINE>
<LINE>I will not hold thee long: if I do live,</LINE>
<LINE>I will be good to thee.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Music, and a song</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>This is a sleepy tune. O murderous slumber,</LINE>
<LINE>Lay'st thou thy leaden mace upon my boy,</LINE>
<LINE>That plays thee music? Gentle knave, good night;</LINE>
<LINE>I will not do thee so much wrong to wake thee:</LINE>
<LINE>If thou dost nod, thou break'st thy instrument;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll take it from thee; and, good boy, good night.</LINE>
<LINE>Let me see, let me see; is not the leaf turn'd down</LINE>
<LINE>Where I left reading? Here it is, I think.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter the Ghost of CAESAR</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How ill this taper burns! Ha! who comes here?</LINE>
<LINE>I think it is the weakness of mine eyes</LINE>
<LINE>That shapes this monstrous apparition.</LINE>
<LINE>It comes upon me. Art thou any thing?</LINE>
<LINE>Art thou some god, some angel, or some devil,</LINE>
<LINE>That makest my blood cold and my hair to stare?</LINE>
<LINE>Speak to me what thou art.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GHOST</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy evil spirit, Brutus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why comest thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GHOST</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To tell thee thou shalt see me at Philippi.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well; then I shall see thee again?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GHOST</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, at Philippi.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, I will see thee at Philippi, then.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Ghost</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Now I have taken heart thou vanishest:</LINE>
<LINE>Ill spirit, I would hold more talk with thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Boy, Lucius! Varro! Claudius! Sirs, awake! Claudius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The strings, my lord, are false.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He thinks he still is at his instrument.</LINE>
<LINE>Lucius, awake!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Didst thou dream, Lucius, that thou so criedst out?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, I do not know that I did cry.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, that thou didst: didst thou see any thing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sleep again, Lucius. Sirrah Claudius!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To VARRO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Fellow thou, awake!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VARRO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLAUDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why did you so cry out, sirs, in your sleep?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VARRO</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>CLAUDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did we, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay: saw you any thing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VARRO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, my lord, I saw nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLAUDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor I, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go and commend me to my brother Cassius;</LINE>
<LINE>Bid him set on his powers betimes before,</LINE>
<LINE>And we will follow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VARRO</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>CLAUDIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It shall be done, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT V</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  The plains of Philippi.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OCTAVIUS, ANTONY, and their army</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, Antony, our hopes are answered:</LINE>
<LINE>You said the enemy would not come down,</LINE>
<LINE>But keep the hills and upper regions;</LINE>
<LINE>It proves not so: their battles are at hand;</LINE>
<LINE>They mean to warn us at Philippi here,</LINE>
<LINE>Answering before we do demand of them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tut, I am in their bosoms, and I know</LINE>
<LINE>Wherefore they do it: they could be content</LINE>
<LINE>To visit other places; and come down</LINE>
<LINE>With fearful bravery, thinking by this face</LINE>
<LINE>To fasten in our thoughts that they have courage;</LINE>
<LINE>But 'tis not so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prepare you, generals:</LINE>
<LINE>The enemy comes on in gallant show;</LINE>
<LINE>Their bloody sign of battle is hung out,</LINE>
<LINE>And something to be done immediately.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Octavius, lead your battle softly on,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon the left hand of the even field.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Upon the right hand I; keep thou the left.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why do you cross me in this exigent?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not cross you; but I will do so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>March</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Drum. Enter BRUTUS, CASSIUS, and their Army;
LUCILIUS, TITINIUS, MESSALA, and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They stand, and would have parley.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand fast, Titinius: we must out and talk.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mark Antony, shall we give sign of battle?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, Caesar, we will answer on their charge.</LINE>
<LINE>Make forth; the generals would have some words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stir not until the signal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Words before blows: is it so, countrymen?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not that we love words better, as you do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good words are better than bad strokes, Octavius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In your bad strokes, Brutus, you give good words:</LINE>
<LINE>Witness the hole you made in Caesar's heart,</LINE>
<LINE>Crying 'Long live! hail, Caesar!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Antony,</LINE>
<LINE>The posture of your blows are yet unknown;</LINE>
<LINE>But for your words, they rob the Hybla bees,</LINE>
<LINE>And leave them honeyless.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not stingless too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, yes, and soundless too;</LINE>
<LINE>For you have stol'n their buzzing, Antony,</LINE>
<LINE>And very wisely threat before you sting.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Villains, you did not so, when your vile daggers</LINE>
<LINE>Hack'd one another in the sides of Caesar:</LINE>
<LINE>You show'd your teeth like apes, and fawn'd like hounds,</LINE>
<LINE>And bow'd like bondmen, kissing Caesar's feet;</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst damned Casca, like a cur, behind</LINE>
<LINE>Struck Caesar on the neck. O you flatterers!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Flatterers! Now, Brutus, thank yourself:</LINE>
<LINE>This tongue had not offended so to-day,</LINE>
<LINE>If Cassius might have ruled.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, the cause: if arguing make us sweat,</LINE>
<LINE>The proof of it will turn to redder drops. Look;</LINE>
<LINE>I draw a sword against conspirators;</LINE>
<LINE>When think you that the sword goes up again?</LINE>
<LINE>Never, till Caesar's three and thirty wounds</LINE>
<LINE>Be well avenged; or till another Caesar</LINE>
<LINE>Have added slaughter to the sword of traitors.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Caesar, thou canst not die by traitors' hands,</LINE>
<LINE>Unless thou bring'st them with thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So I hope;</LINE>
<LINE>I was not born to die on Brutus' sword.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, if thou wert the noblest of thy strain,</LINE>
<LINE>Young man, thou couldst not die more honourable.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A peevish schoolboy, worthless of such honour,</LINE>
<LINE>Join'd with a masker and a reveller!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Old Cassius still!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, Antony, away!</LINE>
<LINE>Defiance, traitors, hurl we in your teeth:</LINE>
<LINE>If you dare fight to-day, come to the field;</LINE>
<LINE>If not, when you have stomachs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt OCTAVIUS, ANTONY, and their army</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, now, blow wind, swell billow and swim bark!</LINE>
<LINE>The storm is up, and all is on the hazard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ho, Lucilius! hark, a word with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Standing forth</STAGEDIR> My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>BRUTUS and LUCILIUS converse apart</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Messala!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Standing forth</STAGEDIR>  What says my general?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Messala,</LINE>
<LINE>This is my birth-day; as this very day</LINE>
<LINE>Was Cassius born. Give me thy hand, Messala:</LINE>
<LINE>Be thou my witness that against my will,</LINE>
<LINE>As Pompey was, am I compell'd to set</LINE>
<LINE>Upon one battle all our liberties.</LINE>
<LINE>You know that I held Epicurus strong</LINE>
<LINE>And his opinion: now I change my mind,</LINE>
<LINE>And partly credit things that do presage.</LINE>
<LINE>Coming from Sardis, on our former ensign</LINE>
<LINE>Two mighty eagles fell, and there they perch'd,</LINE>
<LINE>Gorging and feeding from our soldiers' hands;</LINE>
<LINE>Who to Philippi here consorted us:</LINE>
<LINE>This morning are they fled away and gone;</LINE>
<LINE>And in their steads do ravens, crows and kites,</LINE>
<LINE>Fly o'er our heads and downward look on us,</LINE>
<LINE>As we were sickly prey: their shadows seem</LINE>
<LINE>A canopy most fatal, under which</LINE>
<LINE>Our army lies, ready to give up the ghost.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Believe not so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I but believe it partly;</LINE>
<LINE>For I am fresh of spirit and resolved</LINE>
<LINE>To meet all perils very constantly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even so, Lucilius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, most noble Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>The gods to-day stand friendly, that we may,</LINE>
<LINE>Lovers in peace, lead on our days to age!</LINE>
<LINE>But since the affairs of men rest still incertain,</LINE>
<LINE>Let's reason with the worst that may befall.</LINE>
<LINE>If we do lose this battle, then is this</LINE>
<LINE>The very last time we shall speak together:</LINE>
<LINE>What are you then determined to do?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even by the rule of that philosophy</LINE>
<LINE>By which I did blame Cato for the death</LINE>
<LINE>Which he did give himself, I know not how,</LINE>
<LINE>But I do find it cowardly and vile,</LINE>
<LINE>For fear of what might fall, so to prevent</LINE>
<LINE>The time of life: arming myself with patience</LINE>
<LINE>To stay the providence of some high powers</LINE>
<LINE>That govern us below.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then, if we lose this battle,</LINE>
<LINE>You are contented to be led in triumph</LINE>
<LINE>Thorough the streets of Rome?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, Cassius, no: think not, thou noble Roman,</LINE>
<LINE>That ever Brutus will go bound to Rome;</LINE>
<LINE>He bears too great a mind. But this same day</LINE>
<LINE>Must end that work the ides of March begun;</LINE>
<LINE>And whether we shall meet again I know not.</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore our everlasting farewell take:</LINE>
<LINE>For ever, and for ever, farewell, Cassius!</LINE>
<LINE>If we do meet again, why, we shall smile;</LINE>
<LINE>If not, why then, this parting was well made.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For ever, and for ever, farewell, Brutus!</LINE>
<LINE>If we do meet again, we'll smile indeed;</LINE>
<LINE>If not, 'tis true this parting was well made.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, then, lead on. O, that a man might know</LINE>
<LINE>The end of this day's business ere it come!</LINE>
<LINE>But it sufficeth that the day will end,</LINE>
<LINE>And then the end is known. Come, ho! away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  The same. The field of battle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Alarum. Enter BRUTUS and MESSALA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ride, ride, Messala, ride, and give these bills</LINE>
<LINE>Unto the legions on the other side.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Loud alarum</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Let them set on at once; for I perceive</LINE>
<LINE>But cold demeanor in Octavius' wing,</LINE>
<LINE>And sudden push gives them the overthrow.</LINE>
<LINE>Ride, ride, Messala: let them all come down.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  Another part of the field.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Alarums. Enter CASSIUS and TITINIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, look, Titinius, look, the villains fly!</LINE>
<LINE>Myself have to mine own turn'd enemy:</LINE>
<LINE>This ensign here of mine was turning back;</LINE>
<LINE>I slew the coward, and did take it from him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Cassius, Brutus gave the word too early;</LINE>
<LINE>Who, having some advantage on Octavius,</LINE>
<LINE>Took it too eagerly: his soldiers fell to spoil,</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst we by Antony are all enclosed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter PINDARUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PINDARUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fly further off, my lord, fly further off;</LINE>
<LINE>Mark Antony is in your tents, my lord</LINE>
<LINE>Fly, therefore, noble Cassius, fly far off.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This hill is far enough. Look, look, Titinius;</LINE>
<LINE>Are those my tents where I perceive the fire?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They are, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Titinius, if thou lovest me,</LINE>
<LINE>Mount thou my horse, and hide thy spurs in him,</LINE>
<LINE>Till he have brought thee up to yonder troops,</LINE>
<LINE>And here again; that I may rest assured</LINE>
<LINE>Whether yond troops are friend or enemy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will be here again, even with a thought.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go, Pindarus, get higher on that hill;</LINE>
<LINE>My sight was ever thick; regard Titinius,</LINE>
<LINE>And tell me what thou notest about the field.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>PINDARUS ascends the hill</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>This day I breathed first: time is come round,</LINE>
<LINE>And where I did begin, there shall I end;</LINE>
<LINE>My life is run his compass. Sirrah, what news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PINDARUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Above</STAGEDIR>  O my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PINDARUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Above</STAGEDIR>  Titinius is enclosed round about</LINE>
<LINE>With horsemen, that make to him on the spur;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet he spurs on. Now they are almost on him.</LINE>
<LINE>Now, Titinius! Now some light. O, he lights too.</LINE>
<LINE>He's ta'en.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Shout</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And, hark! they shout for joy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come down, behold no more.</LINE>
<LINE>O, coward that I am, to live so long,</LINE>
<LINE>To see my best friend ta'en before my face!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>PINDARUS descends</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Come hither, sirrah:</LINE>
<LINE>In Parthia did I take thee prisoner;</LINE>
<LINE>And then I swore thee, saving of thy life,</LINE>
<LINE>That whatsoever I did bid thee do,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou shouldst attempt it. Come now, keep thine oath;</LINE>
<LINE>Now be a freeman: and with this good sword,</LINE>
<LINE>That ran through Caesar's bowels, search this bosom.</LINE>
<LINE>Stand not to answer: here, take thou the hilts;</LINE>
<LINE>And, when my face is cover'd, as 'tis now,</LINE>
<LINE>Guide thou the sword.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>PINDARUS stabs him</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Caesar, thou art revenged,</LINE>
<LINE>Even with the sword that kill'd thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Dies</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>PINDARUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So, I am free; yet would not so have been,</LINE>
<LINE>Durst I have done my will. O Cassius,</LINE>
<LINE>Far from this country Pindarus shall run,</LINE>
<LINE>Where never Roman shall take note of him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter TITINIUS with MESSALA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is but change, Titinius; for Octavius</LINE>
<LINE>Is overthrown by noble Brutus' power,</LINE>
<LINE>As Cassius' legions are by Antony.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These tidings will well comfort Cassius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where did you leave him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All disconsolate,</LINE>
<LINE>With Pindarus his bondman, on this hill.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is not that he that lies upon the ground?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He lies not like the living. O my heart!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is not that he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, this was he, Messala,</LINE>
<LINE>But Cassius is no more. O setting sun,</LINE>
<LINE>As in thy red rays thou dost sink to-night,</LINE>
<LINE>So in his red blood Cassius' day is set;</LINE>
<LINE>The sun of Rome is set! Our day is gone;</LINE>
<LINE>Clouds, dews, and dangers come; our deeds are done!</LINE>
<LINE>Mistrust of my success hath done this deed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mistrust of good success hath done this deed.</LINE>
<LINE>O hateful error, melancholy's child,</LINE>
<LINE>Why dost thou show to the apt thoughts of men</LINE>
<LINE>The things that are not? O error, soon conceived,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou never comest unto a happy birth,</LINE>
<LINE>But kill'st the mother that engender'd thee!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, Pindarus! where art thou, Pindarus?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Seek him, Titinius, whilst I go to meet</LINE>
<LINE>The noble Brutus, thrusting this report</LINE>
<LINE>Into his ears; I may say, thrusting it;</LINE>
<LINE>For piercing steel and darts envenomed</LINE>
<LINE>Shall be as welcome to the ears of Brutus</LINE>
<LINE>As tidings of this sight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>TITINIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hie you, Messala,</LINE>
<LINE>And I will seek for Pindarus the while.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit MESSALA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Why didst thou send me forth, brave Cassius?</LINE>
<LINE>Did I not meet thy friends? and did not they</LINE>
<LINE>Put on my brows this wreath of victory,</LINE>
<LINE>And bid me give it thee? Didst thou not hear their shouts?</LINE>
<LINE>Alas, thou hast misconstrued every thing!</LINE>
<LINE>But, hold thee, take this garland on thy brow;</LINE>
<LINE>Thy Brutus bid me give it thee, and I</LINE>
<LINE>Will do his bidding. Brutus, come apace,</LINE>
<LINE>And see how I regarded Caius Cassius.</LINE>
<LINE>By your leave, gods:--this is a Roman's part</LINE>
<LINE>Come, Cassius' sword, and find Titinius' heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Kills himself</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Alarum. Re-enter MESSALA, with BRUTUS, CATO,
STRATO, VOLUMNIUS, and LUCILIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where, where, Messala, doth his body lie?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lo, yonder, and Titinius mourning it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Titinius' face is upward.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CATO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is slain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Julius Caesar, thou art mighty yet!</LINE>
<LINE>Thy spirit walks abroad and turns our swords</LINE>
<LINE>In our own proper entrails.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Low alarums</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CATO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Brave Titinius!</LINE>
<LINE>Look, whether he have not crown'd dead Cassius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are yet two Romans living such as these?</LINE>
<LINE>The last of all the Romans, fare thee well!</LINE>
<LINE>It is impossible that ever Rome</LINE>
<LINE>Should breed thy fellow. Friends, I owe more tears</LINE>
<LINE>To this dead man than you shall see me pay.</LINE>
<LINE>I shall find time, Cassius, I shall find time.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, therefore, and to Thasos send his body:</LINE>
<LINE>His funerals shall not be in our camp,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest it discomfort us. Lucilius, come;</LINE>
<LINE>And come, young Cato; let us to the field.</LINE>
<LINE>Labeo and Flavius, set our battles on:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis three o'clock; and, Romans, yet ere night</LINE>
<LINE>We shall try fortune in a second fight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE IV.  Another part of the field.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Alarum. Enter fighting, Soldiers of both armies;
then BRUTUS, CATO, LUCILIUS, and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet, countrymen, O, yet hold up your heads!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CATO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What bastard doth not? Who will go with me?</LINE>
<LINE>I will proclaim my name about the field:</LINE>
<LINE>I am the son of Marcus Cato, ho!</LINE>
<LINE>A foe to tyrants, and my country's friend;</LINE>
<LINE>I am the son of Marcus Cato, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I am Brutus, Marcus Brutus, I;</LINE>
<LINE>Brutus, my country's friend; know me for Brutus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O young and noble Cato, art thou down?</LINE>
<LINE>Why, now thou diest as bravely as Titinius;</LINE>
<LINE>And mayst be honour'd, being Cato's son.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yield, or thou diest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Only I yield to die:</LINE>
<LINE>There is so much that thou wilt kill me straight;</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Offering money</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Kill Brutus, and be honour'd in his death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We must not. A noble prisoner!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Room, ho! Tell Antony, Brutus is ta'en.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Soldier</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll tell the news. Here comes the general.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter ANTONY</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Brutus is ta'en, Brutus is ta'en, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Safe, Antony; Brutus is safe enough:</LINE>
<LINE>I dare assure thee that no enemy</LINE>
<LINE>Shall ever take alive the noble Brutus:</LINE>
<LINE>The gods defend him from so great a shame!</LINE>
<LINE>When you do find him, or alive or dead,</LINE>
<LINE>He will be found like Brutus, like himself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is not Brutus, friend; but, I assure you,</LINE>
<LINE>A prize no less in worth: keep this man safe;</LINE>
<LINE>Give him all kindness: I had rather have</LINE>
<LINE>Such men my friends than enemies. Go on,</LINE>
<LINE>And see whether Brutus be alive or dead;</LINE>
<LINE>And bring us word unto Octavius' tent</LINE>
<LINE>How every thing is chanced.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE V.  Another part of the field.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter BRUTUS, DARDANIUS, CLITUS, STRATO, and
VOLUMNIUS</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, poor remains of friends, rest on this rock.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Statilius show'd the torch-light, but, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>He came not back: he is or ta'en or slain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sit thee down, Clitus: slaying is the word;</LINE>
<LINE>It is a deed in fashion. Hark thee, Clitus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Whispers</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, I, my lord? No, not for all the world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace then! no words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll rather kill myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hark thee, Dardanius.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Whispers</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DARDANIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall I do such a deed?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Dardanius!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DARDANIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Clitus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What ill request did Brutus make to thee?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DARDANIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To kill him, Clitus. Look, he meditates.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now is that noble vessel full of grief,</LINE>
<LINE>That it runs over even at his eyes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come hither, good Volumnius; list a word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What says my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, this, Volumnius:</LINE>
<LINE>The ghost of Caesar hath appear'd to me</LINE>
<LINE>Two several times by night; at Sardis once,</LINE>
<LINE>And, this last night, here in Philippi fields:</LINE>
<LINE>I know my hour is come.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not so, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, I am sure it is, Volumnius.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou seest the world, Volumnius, how it goes;</LINE>
<LINE>Our enemies have beat us to the pit:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Low alarums</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>It is more worthy to leap in ourselves,</LINE>
<LINE>Than tarry till they push us. Good Volumnius,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou know'st that we two went to school together:</LINE>
<LINE>Even for that our love of old, I prithee,</LINE>
<LINE>Hold thou my sword-hilts, whilst I run on it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>VOLUMNIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's not an office for a friend, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Alarum still</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fly, fly, my lord; there is no tarrying here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell to you; and you; and you, Volumnius.</LINE>
<LINE>Strato, thou hast been all this while asleep;</LINE>
<LINE>Farewell to thee too, Strato. Countrymen,</LINE>
<LINE>My heart doth joy that yet in all my life</LINE>
<LINE>I found no man but he was true to me.</LINE>
<LINE>I shall have glory by this losing day</LINE>
<LINE>More than Octavius and Mark Antony</LINE>
<LINE>By this vile conquest shall attain unto.</LINE>
<LINE>So fare you well at once; for Brutus' tongue</LINE>
<LINE>Hath almost ended his life's history:</LINE>
<LINE>Night hangs upon mine eyes; my bones would rest,</LINE>
<LINE>That have but labour'd to attain this hour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Alarum. Cry within, 'Fly, fly, fly!'</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CLITUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fly, my lord, fly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hence! I will follow.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt CLITUS, DARDANIUS, and VOLUMNIUS</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I prithee, Strato, stay thou by thy lord:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art a fellow of a good respect;</LINE>
<LINE>Thy life hath had some smatch of honour in it:</LINE>
<LINE>Hold then my sword, and turn away thy face,</LINE>
<LINE>While I do run upon it. Wilt thou, Strato?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STRATO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give me your hand first. Fare you well, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRUTUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, good Strato.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Runs on his sword</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Caesar, now be still:</LINE>
<LINE>I kill'd not thee with half so good a will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Dies</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Alarum. Retreat. Enter OCTAVIUS, ANTONY, MESSALA,
LUCILIUS, and the army</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What man is that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My master's man. Strato, where is thy master?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STRATO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Free from the bondage you are in, Messala:</LINE>
<LINE>The conquerors can but make a fire of him;</LINE>
<LINE>For Brutus only overcame himself,</LINE>
<LINE>And no man else hath honour by his death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LUCILIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So Brutus should be found. I thank thee, Brutus,</LINE>
<LINE>That thou hast proved Lucilius' saying true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All that served Brutus, I will entertain them.</LINE>
<LINE>Fellow, wilt thou bestow thy time with me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STRATO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, if Messala will prefer me to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do so, good Messala.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How died my master, Strato?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>STRATO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I held the sword, and he did run on it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MESSALA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Octavius, then take him to follow thee,</LINE>
<LINE>That did the latest service to my master.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>ANTONY</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This was the noblest Roman of them all:</LINE>
<LINE>All the conspirators save only he</LINE>
<LINE>Did that they did in envy of great Caesar;</LINE>
<LINE>He only, in a general honest thought</LINE>
<LINE>And common good to all, made one of them.</LINE>
<LINE>His life was gentle, and the elements</LINE>
<LINE>So mix'd in him that Nature might stand up</LINE>
<LINE>And say to all the world 'This was a man!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OCTAVIUS</SPEAKER>
<LINE>According to his virtue let us use him,</LINE>
<LINE>With all respect and rites of burial.</LINE>
<LINE>Within my tent his bones to-night shall lie,</LINE>
<LINE>Most like a soldier, order'd honourably.</LINE>
<LINE>So call the field to rest; and let's away,</LINE>
<LINE>To part the glories of this happy day.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>
</ACT>
</PLAY>
