<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="shakes.css"?>
<!-- <!DOCTYPE PLAY SYSTEM "play.dtd"> -->

<PLAY>
<TITLE>The Tragedy of Othello, the Moor of Venice</TITLE>

<!--

<P>Text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</P>
<P>XML markup by Jon Bosak, 1996-1998.</P>
<P>XML Styling done by Ajay Juneja, 1999.<P>
<P>This work may be freely copied and distributed worldwide.</P>

-->

<PERSONAE>
<TITLE>Dramatis Personae</TITLE>

<PERSONA>DUKE OF VENICE</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>BRABANTIO, a senator.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Other Senators.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>GRATIANO, brother to Brabantio.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>LODOVICO, kinsman to Brabantio.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>OTHELLO, a noble Moor in the service of the Venetian state.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>CASSIO, his lieutenant.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>IAGO, his ancient.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>RODERIGO, a Venetian gentleman.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>MONTANO, Othello's predecessor in the government of Cyprus.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Clown, servant to Othello. </PERSONA>
<PERSONA>DESDEMONA, daughter to Brabantio and wife to Othello.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>EMILIA, wife to Iago.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>BIANCA, mistress to Cassio.</PERSONA>
<PERSONA>Sailor, Messenger, Herald, Officers, Gentlemen, Musicians, and Attendants.</PERSONA>
</PERSONAE>

<SCNDESCR>SCENE  Venice: a Sea-port in Cyprus.</SCNDESCR>

<PLAYSUBT>OTHELLO</PLAYSUBT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT I</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Venice. A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter RODERIGO and IAGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Tush! never tell me; I take it much unkindly</LINE>
<LINE>That thou, Iago, who hast had my purse</LINE>
<LINE>As if the strings were thine, shouldst know of this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Sblood, but you will not hear me:</LINE>
<LINE>If ever I did dream of such a matter, Abhor me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou told'st me thou didst hold him in thy hate.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Despise me, if I do not. Three great ones of the city,</LINE>
<LINE>In personal suit to make me his lieutenant,</LINE>
<LINE>Off-capp'd to him: and, by the faith of man,</LINE>
<LINE>I know my price, I am worth no worse a place:</LINE>
<LINE>But he; as loving his own pride and purposes,</LINE>
<LINE>Evades them, with a bombast circumstance</LINE>
<LINE>Horribly stuff'd with epithets of war;</LINE>
<LINE>And, in conclusion,</LINE>
<LINE>Nonsuits my mediators; for, 'Certes,' says he,</LINE>
<LINE>'I have already chose my officer.'</LINE>
<LINE>And what was he?</LINE>
<LINE>Forsooth, a great arithmetician,</LINE>
<LINE>One Michael Cassio, a Florentine,</LINE>
<LINE>A fellow almost damn'd in a fair wife;</LINE>
<LINE>That never set a squadron in the field,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor the division of a battle knows</LINE>
<LINE>More than a spinster; unless the bookish theoric,</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein the toged consuls can propose</LINE>
<LINE>As masterly as he: mere prattle, without practise,</LINE>
<LINE>Is all his soldiership. But he, sir, had the election:</LINE>
<LINE>And I, of whom his eyes had seen the proof</LINE>
<LINE>At Rhodes, at Cyprus and on other grounds</LINE>
<LINE>Christian and heathen, must be be-lee'd and calm'd</LINE>
<LINE>By debitor and creditor: this counter-caster,</LINE>
<LINE>He, in good time, must his lieutenant be,</LINE>
<LINE>And I--God bless the mark!--his Moorship's ancient.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By heaven, I rather would have been his hangman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, there's no remedy; 'tis the curse of service,</LINE>
<LINE>Preferment goes by letter and affection,</LINE>
<LINE>And not by old gradation, where each second</LINE>
<LINE>Stood heir to the first. Now, sir, be judge yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>Whether I in any just term am affined</LINE>
<LINE>To love the Moor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would not follow him then.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, sir, content you;</LINE>
<LINE>I follow him to serve my turn upon him:</LINE>
<LINE>We cannot all be masters, nor all masters</LINE>
<LINE>Cannot be truly follow'd. You shall mark</LINE>
<LINE>Many a duteous and knee-crooking knave,</LINE>
<LINE>That, doting on his own obsequious bondage,</LINE>
<LINE>Wears out his time, much like his master's ass,</LINE>
<LINE>For nought but provender, and when he's old, cashier'd:</LINE>
<LINE>Whip me such honest knaves. Others there are</LINE>
<LINE>Who, trimm'd in forms and visages of duty,</LINE>
<LINE>Keep yet their hearts attending on themselves,</LINE>
<LINE>And, throwing but shows of service on their lords,</LINE>
<LINE>Do well thrive by them and when they have lined</LINE>
<LINE>their coats</LINE>
<LINE>Do themselves homage: these fellows have some soul;</LINE>
<LINE>And such a one do I profess myself. For, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>It is as sure as you are Roderigo,</LINE>
<LINE>Were I the Moor, I would not be Iago:</LINE>
<LINE>In following him, I follow but myself;</LINE>
<LINE>Heaven is my judge, not I for love and duty,</LINE>
<LINE>But seeming so, for my peculiar end:</LINE>
<LINE>For when my outward action doth demonstrate</LINE>
<LINE>The native act and figure of my heart</LINE>
<LINE>In compliment extern, 'tis not long after</LINE>
<LINE>But I will wear my heart upon my sleeve</LINE>
<LINE>For daws to peck at: I am not what I am.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What a full fortune does the thicklips owe</LINE>
<LINE>If he can carry't thus!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call up her father,</LINE>
<LINE>Rouse him: make after him, poison his delight,</LINE>
<LINE>Proclaim him in the streets; incense her kinsmen,</LINE>
<LINE>And, though he in a fertile climate dwell,</LINE>
<LINE>Plague him with flies: though that his joy be joy,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet throw such changes of vexation on't,</LINE>
<LINE>As it may lose some colour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is her father's house; I'll call aloud.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do, with like timorous accent and dire yell</LINE>
<LINE>As when, by night and negligence, the fire</LINE>
<LINE>Is spied in populous cities.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, ho, Brabantio! Signior Brabantio, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Awake! what, ho, Brabantio! thieves! thieves! thieves!</LINE>
<LINE>Look to your house, your daughter and your bags!</LINE>
<LINE>Thieves! thieves!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>BRABANTIO appears above, at a window</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the reason of this terrible summons?</LINE>
<LINE>What is the matter there?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Signior, is all your family within?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are your doors lock'd?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, wherefore ask you this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Zounds, sir, you're robb'd; for shame, put on</LINE>
<LINE>your gown;</LINE>
<LINE>Your heart is burst, you have lost half your soul;</LINE>
<LINE>Even now, now, very now, an old black ram</LINE>
<LINE>Is topping your white ewe. Arise, arise;</LINE>
<LINE>Awake the snorting citizens with the bell,</LINE>
<LINE>Or else the devil will make a grandsire of you:</LINE>
<LINE>Arise, I say.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, have you lost your wits?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most reverend signior, do you know my voice?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not I what are you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My name is Roderigo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The worser welcome:</LINE>
<LINE>I have charged thee not to haunt about my doors:</LINE>
<LINE>In honest plainness thou hast heard me say</LINE>
<LINE>My daughter is not for thee; and now, in madness,</LINE>
<LINE>Being full of supper and distempering draughts,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon malicious bravery, dost thou come</LINE>
<LINE>To start my quiet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, sir, sir,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But thou must needs be sure</LINE>
<LINE>My spirit and my place have in them power</LINE>
<LINE>To make this bitter to thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Patience, good sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What tell'st thou me of robbing? this is Venice;</LINE>
<LINE>My house is not a grange.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most grave Brabantio,</LINE>
<LINE>In simple and pure soul I come to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Zounds, sir, you are one of those that will not</LINE>
<LINE>serve God, if the devil bid you. Because we come to</LINE>
<LINE>do you service and you think we are ruffians, you'll</LINE>
<LINE>have your daughter covered with a Barbary horse;</LINE>
<LINE>you'll have your nephews neigh to you; you'll have</LINE>
<LINE>coursers for cousins and gennets for germans.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What profane wretch art thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am one, sir, that comes to tell you your daughter</LINE>
<LINE>and the Moor are now making the beast with two backs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art a villain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are--a senator.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This thou shalt answer; I know thee, Roderigo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, I will answer any thing. But, I beseech you,</LINE>
<LINE>If't be your pleasure and most wise consent,</LINE>
<LINE>As partly I find it is, that your fair daughter,</LINE>
<LINE>At this odd-even and dull watch o' the night,</LINE>
<LINE>Transported, with no worse nor better guard</LINE>
<LINE>But with a knave of common hire, a gondolier,</LINE>
<LINE>To the gross clasps of a lascivious Moor--</LINE>
<LINE>If this be known to you and your allowance,</LINE>
<LINE>We then have done you bold and saucy wrongs;</LINE>
<LINE>But if you know not this, my manners tell me</LINE>
<LINE>We have your wrong rebuke. Do not believe</LINE>
<LINE>That, from the sense of all civility,</LINE>
<LINE>I thus would play and trifle with your reverence:</LINE>
<LINE>Your daughter, if you have not given her leave,</LINE>
<LINE>I say again, hath made a gross revolt;</LINE>
<LINE>Tying her duty, beauty, wit and fortunes</LINE>
<LINE>In an extravagant and wheeling stranger</LINE>
<LINE>Of here and every where. Straight satisfy yourself:</LINE>
<LINE>If she be in her chamber or your house,</LINE>
<LINE>Let loose on me the justice of the state</LINE>
<LINE>For thus deluding you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Strike on the tinder, ho!</LINE>
<LINE>Give me a taper! call up all my people!</LINE>
<LINE>This accident is not unlike my dream:</LINE>
<LINE>Belief of it oppresses me already.</LINE>
<LINE>Light, I say! light!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit above</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell; for I must leave you:</LINE>
<LINE>It seems not meet, nor wholesome to my place,</LINE>
<LINE>To be produced--as, if I stay, I shall--</LINE>
<LINE>Against the Moor: for, I do know, the state,</LINE>
<LINE>However this may gall him with some cheque,</LINE>
<LINE>Cannot with safety cast him, for he's embark'd</LINE>
<LINE>With such loud reason to the Cyprus wars,</LINE>
<LINE>Which even now stand in act, that, for their souls,</LINE>
<LINE>Another of his fathom they have none,</LINE>
<LINE>To lead their business: in which regard,</LINE>
<LINE>Though I do hate him as I do hell-pains.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, for necessity of present life,</LINE>
<LINE>I must show out a flag and sign of love,</LINE>
<LINE>Which is indeed but sign. That you shall surely find him,</LINE>
<LINE>Lead to the Sagittary the raised search;</LINE>
<LINE>And there will I be with him. So, farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter, below, BRABANTIO, and Servants with torches</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is too true an evil: gone she is;</LINE>
<LINE>And what's to come of my despised time</LINE>
<LINE>Is nought but bitterness. Now, Roderigo,</LINE>
<LINE>Where didst thou see her? O unhappy girl!</LINE>
<LINE>With the Moor, say'st thou? Who would be a father!</LINE>
<LINE>How didst thou know 'twas she? O she deceives me</LINE>
<LINE>Past thought! What said she to you? Get more tapers:</LINE>
<LINE>Raise all my kindred. Are they married, think you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, I think they are.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O heaven! How got she out? O treason of the blood!</LINE>
<LINE>Fathers, from hence trust not your daughters' minds</LINE>
<LINE>By what you see them act. Is there not charms</LINE>
<LINE>By which the property of youth and maidhood</LINE>
<LINE>May be abused? Have you not read, Roderigo,</LINE>
<LINE>Of some such thing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, sir, I have indeed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Call up my brother. O, would you had had her!</LINE>
<LINE>Some one way, some another. Do you know</LINE>
<LINE>Where we may apprehend her and the Moor?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think I can discover him, if you please,</LINE>
<LINE>To get good guard and go along with me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, lead on. At every house I'll call;</LINE>
<LINE>I may command at most. Get weapons, ho!</LINE>
<LINE>And raise some special officers of night.</LINE>
<LINE>On, good Roderigo: I'll deserve your pains.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  Another street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO, IAGO, and Attendants with torches</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Though in the trade of war I have slain men,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet do I hold it very stuff o' the conscience</LINE>
<LINE>To do no contrived murder: I lack iniquity</LINE>
<LINE>Sometimes to do me service: nine or ten times</LINE>
<LINE>I had thought to have yerk'd him here under the ribs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis better as it is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, but he prated,</LINE>
<LINE>And spoke such scurvy and provoking terms</LINE>
<LINE>Against your honour</LINE>
<LINE>That, with the little godliness I have,</LINE>
<LINE>I did full hard forbear him. But, I pray you, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Are you fast married? Be assured of this,</LINE>
<LINE>That the magnifico is much beloved,</LINE>
<LINE>And hath in his effect a voice potential</LINE>
<LINE>As double as the duke's: he will divorce you;</LINE>
<LINE>Or put upon you what restraint and grievance</LINE>
<LINE>The law, with all his might to enforce it on,</LINE>
<LINE>Will give him cable.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let him do his spite:</LINE>
<LINE>My services which I have done the signiory</LINE>
<LINE>Shall out-tongue his complaints. 'Tis yet to know,--</LINE>
<LINE>Which, when I know that boasting is an honour,</LINE>
<LINE>I shall promulgate--I fetch my life and being</LINE>
<LINE>From men of royal siege, and my demerits</LINE>
<LINE>May speak unbonneted to as proud a fortune</LINE>
<LINE>As this that I have reach'd: for know, Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>But that I love the gentle Desdemona,</LINE>
<LINE>I would not my unhoused free condition</LINE>
<LINE>Put into circumscription and confine</LINE>
<LINE>For the sea's worth. But, look! what lights come yond?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Those are the raised father and his friends:</LINE>
<LINE>You were best go in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not I I must be found:</LINE>
<LINE>My parts, my title and my perfect soul</LINE>
<LINE>Shall manifest me rightly. Is it they?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By Janus, I think no.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIO, and certain Officers with torches</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The servants of the duke, and my lieutenant.</LINE>
<LINE>The goodness of the night upon you, friends!</LINE>
<LINE>What is the news?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The duke does greet you, general,</LINE>
<LINE>And he requires your haste-post-haste appearance,</LINE>
<LINE>Even on the instant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter, think you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Something from Cyprus as I may divine:</LINE>
<LINE>It is a business of some heat: the galleys</LINE>
<LINE>Have sent a dozen sequent messengers</LINE>
<LINE>This very night at one another's heels,</LINE>
<LINE>And many of the consuls, raised and met,</LINE>
<LINE>Are at the duke's already: you have been</LINE>
<LINE>hotly call'd for;</LINE>
<LINE>When, being not at your lodging to be found,</LINE>
<LINE>The senate hath sent about three several guests</LINE>
<LINE>To search you out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis well I am found by you.</LINE>
<LINE>I will but spend a word here in the house,</LINE>
<LINE>And go with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ancient, what makes he here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, he to-night hath boarded a land carack:</LINE>
<LINE>If it prove lawful prize, he's made for ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not understand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's married.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To who?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter OTHELLO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, to--Come, captain, will you go?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here comes another troop to seek for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is Brabantio. General, be advised;</LINE>
<LINE>He comes to bad intent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter BRABANTIO, RODERIGO, and Officers with
torches and weapons</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Holla! stand there!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Signior, it is the Moor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Down with him, thief!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>They draw on both sides</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You, Roderigo! come, sir, I am for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Keep up your bright swords, for the dew will rust them.</LINE>
<LINE>Good signior, you shall more command with years</LINE>
<LINE>Than with your weapons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O thou foul thief, where hast thou stow'd my daughter?</LINE>
<LINE>Damn'd as thou art, thou hast enchanted her;</LINE>
<LINE>For I'll refer me to all things of sense,</LINE>
<LINE>If she in chains of magic were not bound,</LINE>
<LINE>Whether a maid so tender, fair and happy,</LINE>
<LINE>So opposite to marriage that she shunned</LINE>
<LINE>The wealthy curled darlings of our nation,</LINE>
<LINE>Would ever have, to incur a general mock,</LINE>
<LINE>Run from her guardage to the sooty bosom</LINE>
<LINE>Of such a thing as thou, to fear, not to delight.</LINE>
<LINE>Judge me the world, if 'tis not gross in sense</LINE>
<LINE>That thou hast practised on her with foul charms,</LINE>
<LINE>Abused her delicate youth with drugs or minerals</LINE>
<LINE>That weaken motion: I'll have't disputed on;</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis probable and palpable to thinking.</LINE>
<LINE>I therefore apprehend and do attach thee</LINE>
<LINE>For an abuser of the world, a practiser</LINE>
<LINE>Of arts inhibited and out of warrant.</LINE>
<LINE>Lay hold upon him: if he do resist,</LINE>
<LINE>Subdue him at his peril.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hold your hands,</LINE>
<LINE>Both you of my inclining, and the rest:</LINE>
<LINE>Were it my cue to fight, I should have known it</LINE>
<LINE>Without a prompter. Where will you that I go</LINE>
<LINE>To answer this your charge?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To prison, till fit time</LINE>
<LINE>Of law and course of direct session</LINE>
<LINE>Call thee to answer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What if I do obey?</LINE>
<LINE>How may the duke be therewith satisfied,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose messengers are here about my side,</LINE>
<LINE>Upon some present business of the state</LINE>
<LINE>To bring me to him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis true, most worthy signior;</LINE>
<LINE>The duke's in council and your noble self,</LINE>
<LINE>I am sure, is sent for.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How! the duke in council!</LINE>
<LINE>In this time of the night! Bring him away:</LINE>
<LINE>Mine's not an idle cause: the duke himself,</LINE>
<LINE>Or any of my brothers of the state,</LINE>
<LINE>Cannot but feel this wrong as 'twere their own;</LINE>
<LINE>For if such actions may have passage free,</LINE>
<LINE>Bond-slaves and pagans shall our statesmen be.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  A council-chamber.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>The DUKE and Senators sitting at a table; Officers
attending</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is no composition in these news</LINE>
<LINE>That gives them credit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, they are disproportion'd;</LINE>
<LINE>My letters say a hundred and seven galleys.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And mine, a hundred and forty.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And mine, two hundred:</LINE>
<LINE>But though they jump not on a just account,--</LINE>
<LINE>As in these cases, where the aim reports,</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis oft with difference--yet do they all confirm</LINE>
<LINE>A Turkish fleet, and bearing up to Cyprus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, it is possible enough to judgment:</LINE>
<LINE>I do not so secure me in the error,</LINE>
<LINE>But the main article I do approve</LINE>
<LINE>In fearful sense.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Sailor</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  What, ho! what, ho! what, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A messenger from the galleys.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter a Sailor</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, what's the business?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Sailor</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The Turkish preparation makes for Rhodes;</LINE>
<LINE>So was I bid report here to the state</LINE>
<LINE>By Signior Angelo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How say you by this change?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This cannot be,</LINE>
<LINE>By no assay of reason: 'tis a pageant,</LINE>
<LINE>To keep us in false gaze. When we consider</LINE>
<LINE>The importancy of Cyprus to the Turk,</LINE>
<LINE>And let ourselves again but understand,</LINE>
<LINE>That as it more concerns the Turk than Rhodes,</LINE>
<LINE>So may he with more facile question bear it,</LINE>
<LINE>For that it stands not in such warlike brace,</LINE>
<LINE>But altogether lacks the abilities</LINE>
<LINE>That Rhodes is dress'd in: if we make thought of this,</LINE>
<LINE>We must not think the Turk is so unskilful</LINE>
<LINE>To leave that latest which concerns him first,</LINE>
<LINE>Neglecting an attempt of ease and gain,</LINE>
<LINE>To wake and wage a danger profitless.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, in all confidence, he's not for Rhodes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Officer</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here is more news.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter a Messenger</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The Ottomites, reverend and gracious,</LINE>
<LINE>Steering with due course towards the isle of Rhodes,</LINE>
<LINE>Have there injointed them with an after fleet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, so I thought. How many, as you guess?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Messenger</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Of thirty sail: and now they do restem</LINE>
<LINE>Their backward course, bearing with frank appearance</LINE>
<LINE>Their purposes toward Cyprus. Signior Montano,</LINE>
<LINE>Your trusty and most valiant servitor,</LINE>
<LINE>With his free duty recommends you thus,</LINE>
<LINE>And prays you to believe him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis certain, then, for Cyprus.</LINE>
<LINE>Marcus Luccicos, is not he in town?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's now in Florence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Write from us to him; post-post-haste dispatch.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here comes Brabantio and the valiant Moor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter BRABANTIO, OTHELLO, IAGO, RODERIGO, and Officers</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Valiant Othello, we must straight employ you</LINE>
<LINE>Against the general enemy Ottoman.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To BRABANTIO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I did not see you; welcome, gentle signior;</LINE>
<LINE>We lack'd your counsel and your help tonight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So did I yours. Good your grace, pardon me;</LINE>
<LINE>Neither my place nor aught I heard of business</LINE>
<LINE>Hath raised me from my bed, nor doth the general care</LINE>
<LINE>Take hold on me, for my particular grief</LINE>
<LINE>Is of so flood-gate and o'erbearing nature</LINE>
<LINE>That it engluts and swallows other sorrows</LINE>
<LINE>And it is still itself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, what's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My daughter! O, my daughter!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dead?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, to me;</LINE>
<LINE>She is abused, stol'n from me, and corrupted</LINE>
<LINE>By spells and medicines bought of mountebanks;</LINE>
<LINE>For nature so preposterously to err,</LINE>
<LINE>Being not deficient, blind, or lame of sense,</LINE>
<LINE>Sans witchcraft could not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whoe'er he be that in this foul proceeding</LINE>
<LINE>Hath thus beguiled your daughter of herself</LINE>
<LINE>And you of her, the bloody book of law</LINE>
<LINE>You shall yourself read in the bitter letter</LINE>
<LINE>After your own sense, yea, though our proper son</LINE>
<LINE>Stood in your action.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Humbly I thank your grace.</LINE>
<LINE>Here is the man, this Moor, whom now, it seems,</LINE>
<LINE>Your special mandate for the state-affairs</LINE>
<LINE>Hath hither brought.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<SPEAKER>Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We are very sorry for't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To OTHELLO</STAGEDIR>  What, in your own part, can you say to this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing, but this is so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most potent, grave, and reverend signiors,</LINE>
<LINE>My very noble and approved good masters,</LINE>
<LINE>That I have ta'en away this old man's daughter,</LINE>
<LINE>It is most true; true, I have married her:</LINE>
<LINE>The very head and front of my offending</LINE>
<LINE>Hath this extent, no more. Rude am I in my speech,</LINE>
<LINE>And little bless'd with the soft phrase of peace:</LINE>
<LINE>For since these arms of mine had seven years' pith,</LINE>
<LINE>Till now some nine moons wasted, they have used</LINE>
<LINE>Their dearest action in the tented field,</LINE>
<LINE>And little of this great world can I speak,</LINE>
<LINE>More than pertains to feats of broil and battle,</LINE>
<LINE>And therefore little shall I grace my cause</LINE>
<LINE>In speaking for myself. Yet, by your gracious patience,</LINE>
<LINE>I will a round unvarnish'd tale deliver</LINE>
<LINE>Of my whole course of love; what drugs, what charms,</LINE>
<LINE>What conjuration and what mighty magic,</LINE>
<LINE>For such proceeding I am charged withal,</LINE>
<LINE>I won his daughter.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A maiden never bold;</LINE>
<LINE>Of spirit so still and quiet, that her motion</LINE>
<LINE>Blush'd at herself; and she, in spite of nature,</LINE>
<LINE>Of years, of country, credit, every thing,</LINE>
<LINE>To fall in love with what she fear'd to look on!</LINE>
<LINE>It is a judgment maim'd and most imperfect</LINE>
<LINE>That will confess perfection so could err</LINE>
<LINE>Against all rules of nature, and must be driven</LINE>
<LINE>To find out practises of cunning hell,</LINE>
<LINE>Why this should be. I therefore vouch again</LINE>
<LINE>That with some mixtures powerful o'er the blood,</LINE>
<LINE>Or with some dram conjured to this effect,</LINE>
<LINE>He wrought upon her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To vouch this, is no proof,</LINE>
<LINE>Without more wider and more overt test</LINE>
<LINE>Than these thin habits and poor likelihoods</LINE>
<LINE>Of modern seeming do prefer against him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But, Othello, speak:</LINE>
<LINE>Did you by indirect and forced courses</LINE>
<LINE>Subdue and poison this young maid's affections?</LINE>
<LINE>Or came it by request and such fair question</LINE>
<LINE>As soul to soul affordeth?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do beseech you,</LINE>
<LINE>Send for the lady to the Sagittary,</LINE>
<LINE>And let her speak of me before her father:</LINE>
<LINE>If you do find me foul in her report,</LINE>
<LINE>The trust, the office I do hold of you,</LINE>
<LINE>Not only take away, but let your sentence</LINE>
<LINE>Even fall upon my life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fetch Desdemona hither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ancient, conduct them: you best know the place.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt IAGO and Attendants</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And, till she come, as truly as to heaven</LINE>
<LINE>I do confess the vices of my blood,</LINE>
<LINE>So justly to your grave ears I'll present</LINE>
<LINE>How I did thrive in this fair lady's love,</LINE>
<LINE>And she in mine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say it, Othello.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Her father loved me; oft invited me;</LINE>
<LINE>Still question'd me the story of my life,</LINE>
<LINE>From year to year, the battles, sieges, fortunes,</LINE>
<LINE>That I have passed.</LINE>
<LINE>I ran it through, even from my boyish days,</LINE>
<LINE>To the very moment that he bade me tell it;</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein I spake of most disastrous chances,</LINE>
<LINE>Of moving accidents by flood and field</LINE>
<LINE>Of hair-breadth scapes i' the imminent deadly breach,</LINE>
<LINE>Of being taken by the insolent foe</LINE>
<LINE>And sold to slavery, of my redemption thence</LINE>
<LINE>And portance in my travels' history:</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein of antres vast and deserts idle,</LINE>
<LINE>Rough quarries, rocks and hills whose heads touch heaven</LINE>
<LINE>It was my hint to speak,--such was the process;</LINE>
<LINE>And of the Cannibals that each other eat,</LINE>
<LINE>The Anthropophagi and men whose heads</LINE>
<LINE>Do grow beneath their shoulders. This to hear</LINE>
<LINE>Would Desdemona seriously incline:</LINE>
<LINE>But still the house-affairs would draw her thence:</LINE>
<LINE>Which ever as she could with haste dispatch,</LINE>
<LINE>She'ld come again, and with a greedy ear</LINE>
<LINE>Devour up my discourse: which I observing,</LINE>
<LINE>Took once a pliant hour, and found good means</LINE>
<LINE>To draw from her a prayer of earnest heart</LINE>
<LINE>That I would all my pilgrimage dilate,</LINE>
<LINE>Whereof by parcels she had something heard,</LINE>
<LINE>But not intentively: I did consent,</LINE>
<LINE>And often did beguile her of her tears,</LINE>
<LINE>When I did speak of some distressful stroke</LINE>
<LINE>That my youth suffer'd. My story being done,</LINE>
<LINE>She gave me for my pains a world of sighs:</LINE>
<LINE>She swore, in faith, twas strange, 'twas passing strange,</LINE>
<LINE>'Twas pitiful, 'twas wondrous pitiful:</LINE>
<LINE>She wish'd she had not heard it, yet she wish'd</LINE>
<LINE>That heaven had made her such a man: she thank'd me,</LINE>
<LINE>And bade me, if I had a friend that loved her,</LINE>
<LINE>I should but teach him how to tell my story.</LINE>
<LINE>And that would woo her. Upon this hint I spake:</LINE>
<LINE>She loved me for the dangers I had pass'd,</LINE>
<LINE>And I loved her that she did pity them.</LINE>
<LINE>This only is the witchcraft I have used:</LINE>
<LINE>Here comes the lady; let her witness it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter DESDEMONA, IAGO, and Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think this tale would win my daughter too.</LINE>
<LINE>Good Brabantio,</LINE>
<LINE>Take up this mangled matter at the best:</LINE>
<LINE>Men do their broken weapons rather use</LINE>
<LINE>Than their bare hands.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you, hear her speak:</LINE>
<LINE>If she confess that she was half the wooer,</LINE>
<LINE>Destruction on my head, if my bad blame</LINE>
<LINE>Light on the man! Come hither, gentle mistress:</LINE>
<LINE>Do you perceive in all this noble company</LINE>
<LINE>Where most you owe obedience?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My noble father,</LINE>
<LINE>I do perceive here a divided duty:</LINE>
<LINE>To you I am bound for life and education;</LINE>
<LINE>My life and education both do learn me</LINE>
<LINE>How to respect you; you are the lord of duty;</LINE>
<LINE>I am hitherto your daughter: but here's my husband,</LINE>
<LINE>And so much duty as my mother show'd</LINE>
<LINE>To you, preferring you before her father,</LINE>
<LINE>So much I challenge that I may profess</LINE>
<LINE>Due to the Moor my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>God be wi' you! I have done.</LINE>
<LINE>Please it your grace, on to the state-affairs:</LINE>
<LINE>I had rather to adopt a child than get it.</LINE>
<LINE>Come hither, Moor:</LINE>
<LINE>I here do give thee that with all my heart</LINE>
<LINE>Which, but thou hast already, with all my heart</LINE>
<LINE>I would keep from thee. For your sake, jewel,</LINE>
<LINE>I am glad at soul I have no other child:</LINE>
<LINE>For thy escape would teach me tyranny,</LINE>
<LINE>To hang clogs on them. I have done, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me speak like yourself, and lay a sentence,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, as a grise or step, may help these lovers</LINE>
<LINE>Into your favour.</LINE>
<LINE>When remedies are past, the griefs are ended</LINE>
<LINE>By seeing the worst, which late on hopes depended.</LINE>
<LINE>To mourn a mischief that is past and gone</LINE>
<LINE>Is the next way to draw new mischief on.</LINE>
<LINE>What cannot be preserved when fortune takes</LINE>
<LINE>Patience her injury a mockery makes.</LINE>
<LINE>The robb'd that smiles steals something from the thief;</LINE>
<LINE>He robs himself that spends a bootless grief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So let the Turk of Cyprus us beguile;</LINE>
<LINE>We lose it not, so long as we can smile.</LINE>
<LINE>He bears the sentence well that nothing bears</LINE>
<LINE>But the free comfort which from thence he hears,</LINE>
<LINE>But he bears both the sentence and the sorrow</LINE>
<LINE>That, to pay grief, must of poor patience borrow.</LINE>
<LINE>These sentences, to sugar, or to gall,</LINE>
<LINE>Being strong on both sides, are equivocal:</LINE>
<LINE>But words are words; I never yet did hear</LINE>
<LINE>That the bruised heart was pierced through the ear.</LINE>
<LINE>I humbly beseech you, proceed to the affairs of state.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The Turk with a most mighty preparation makes for</LINE>
<LINE>Cyprus. Othello, the fortitude of the place is best</LINE>
<LINE>known to you; and though we have there a substitute</LINE>
<LINE>of most allowed sufficiency, yet opinion, a</LINE>
<LINE>sovereign mistress of effects, throws a more safer</LINE>
<LINE>voice on you: you must therefore be content to</LINE>
<LINE>slubber the gloss of your new fortunes with this</LINE>
<LINE>more stubborn and boisterous expedition.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The tyrant custom, most grave senators,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath made the flinty and steel couch of war</LINE>
<LINE>My thrice-driven bed of down: I do agnise</LINE>
<LINE>A natural and prompt alacrity</LINE>
<LINE>I find in hardness, and do undertake</LINE>
<LINE>These present wars against the Ottomites.</LINE>
<LINE>Most humbly therefore bending to your state,</LINE>
<LINE>I crave fit disposition for my wife.</LINE>
<LINE>Due reference of place and exhibition,</LINE>
<LINE>With such accommodation and besort</LINE>
<LINE>As levels with her breeding.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you please,</LINE>
<LINE>Be't at her father's.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll not have it so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor I; I would not there reside,</LINE>
<LINE>To put my father in impatient thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>By being in his eye. Most gracious duke,</LINE>
<LINE>To my unfolding lend your prosperous ear;</LINE>
<LINE>And let me find a charter in your voice,</LINE>
<LINE>To assist my simpleness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What would You, Desdemona?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That I did love the Moor to live with him,</LINE>
<LINE>My downright violence and storm of fortunes</LINE>
<LINE>May trumpet to the world: my heart's subdued</LINE>
<LINE>Even to the very quality of my lord:</LINE>
<LINE>I saw Othello's visage in his mind,</LINE>
<LINE>And to his honour and his valiant parts</LINE>
<LINE>Did I my soul and fortunes consecrate.</LINE>
<LINE>So that, dear lords, if I be left behind,</LINE>
<LINE>A moth of peace, and he go to the war,</LINE>
<LINE>The rites for which I love him are bereft me,</LINE>
<LINE>And I a heavy interim shall support</LINE>
<LINE>By his dear absence. Let me go with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let her have your voices.</LINE>
<LINE>Vouch with me, heaven, I therefore beg it not,</LINE>
<LINE>To please the palate of my appetite,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor to comply with heat--the young affects</LINE>
<LINE>In me defunct--and proper satisfaction.</LINE>
<LINE>But to be free and bounteous to her mind:</LINE>
<LINE>And heaven defend your good souls, that you think</LINE>
<LINE>I will your serious and great business scant</LINE>
<LINE>For she is with me: no, when light-wing'd toys</LINE>
<LINE>Of feather'd Cupid seal with wanton dullness</LINE>
<LINE>My speculative and officed instruments,</LINE>
<LINE>That my disports corrupt and taint my business,</LINE>
<LINE>Let housewives make a skillet of my helm,</LINE>
<LINE>And all indign and base adversities</LINE>
<LINE>Make head against my estimation!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be it as you shall privately determine,</LINE>
<LINE>Either for her stay or going: the affair cries haste,</LINE>
<LINE>And speed must answer it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You must away to-night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With all my heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At nine i' the morning here we'll meet again.</LINE>
<LINE>Othello, leave some officer behind,</LINE>
<LINE>And he shall our commission bring to you;</LINE>
<LINE>With such things else of quality and respect</LINE>
<LINE>As doth import you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So please your grace, my ancient;</LINE>
<LINE>A man he is of honest and trust:</LINE>
<LINE>To his conveyance I assign my wife,</LINE>
<LINE>With what else needful your good grace shall think</LINE>
<LINE>To be sent after me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DUKE OF VENICE</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let it be so.</LINE>
<LINE>Good night to every one.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To BRABANTIO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And, noble signior,</LINE>
<LINE>If virtue no delighted beauty lack,</LINE>
<LINE>Your son-in-law is far more fair than black.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Senator</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Adieu, brave Moor, use Desdemona well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BRABANTIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look to her, Moor, if thou hast eyes to see:</LINE>
<LINE>She has deceived her father, and may thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt DUKE OF VENICE, Senators, Officers, &amp;c</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My life upon her faith! Honest Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>My Desdemona must I leave to thee:</LINE>
<LINE>I prithee, let thy wife attend on her:</LINE>
<LINE>And bring them after in the best advantage.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, Desdemona: I have but an hour</LINE>
<LINE>Of love, of worldly matters and direction,</LINE>
<LINE>To spend with thee: we must obey the time.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt OTHELLO and DESDEMONA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Iago,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What say'st thou, noble heart?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What will I do, thinkest thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, go to bed, and sleep.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will incontinently drown myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If thou dost, I shall never love thee after. Why,</LINE>
<LINE>thou silly gentleman!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is silliness to live when to live is torment; and</LINE>
<LINE>then have we a prescription to die when death is our physician.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O villainous! I have looked upon the world for four</LINE>
<LINE>times seven years; and since I could distinguish</LINE>
<LINE>betwixt a benefit and an injury, I never found man</LINE>
<LINE>that knew how to love himself. Ere I would say, I</LINE>
<LINE>would drown myself for the love of a guinea-hen, I</LINE>
<LINE>would change my humanity with a baboon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What should I do? I confess it is my shame to be so</LINE>
<LINE>fond; but it is not in my virtue to amend it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Virtue! a fig! 'tis in ourselves that we are thus</LINE>
<LINE>or thus. Our bodies are our gardens, to the which</LINE>
<LINE>our wills are gardeners: so that if we will plant</LINE>
<LINE>nettles, or sow lettuce, set hyssop and weed up</LINE>
<LINE>thyme, supply it with one gender of herbs, or</LINE>
<LINE>distract it with many, either to have it sterile</LINE>
<LINE>with idleness, or manured with industry, why, the</LINE>
<LINE>power and corrigible authority of this lies in our</LINE>
<LINE>wills. If the balance of our lives had not one</LINE>
<LINE>scale of reason to poise another of sensuality, the</LINE>
<LINE>blood and baseness of our natures would conduct us</LINE>
<LINE>to most preposterous conclusions: but we have</LINE>
<LINE>reason to cool our raging motions, our carnal</LINE>
<LINE>stings, our unbitted lusts, whereof I take this that</LINE>
<LINE>you call love to be a sect or scion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It cannot be.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is merely a lust of the blood and a permission of</LINE>
<LINE>the will. Come, be a man. Drown thyself! drown</LINE>
<LINE>cats and blind puppies. I have professed me thy</LINE>
<LINE>friend and I confess me knit to thy deserving with</LINE>
<LINE>cables of perdurable toughness; I could never</LINE>
<LINE>better stead thee than now. Put money in thy</LINE>
<LINE>purse; follow thou the wars; defeat thy favour with</LINE>
<LINE>an usurped beard; I say, put money in thy purse. It</LINE>
<LINE>cannot be that Desdemona should long continue her</LINE>
<LINE>love to the Moor,-- put money in thy purse,--nor he</LINE>
<LINE>his to her: it was a violent commencement, and thou</LINE>
<LINE>shalt see an answerable sequestration:--put but</LINE>
<LINE>money in thy purse. These Moors are changeable in</LINE>
<LINE>their wills: fill thy purse with money:--the food</LINE>
<LINE>that to him now is as luscious as locusts, shall be</LINE>
<LINE>to him shortly as bitter as coloquintida. She must</LINE>
<LINE>change for youth: when she is sated with his body,</LINE>
<LINE>she will find the error of her choice: she must</LINE>
<LINE>have change, she must: therefore put money in thy</LINE>
<LINE>purse. If thou wilt needs damn thyself, do it a</LINE>
<LINE>more delicate way than drowning. Make all the money</LINE>
<LINE>thou canst: if sanctimony and a frail vow betwixt</LINE>
<LINE>an erring barbarian and a supersubtle Venetian not</LINE>
<LINE>too hard for my wits and all the tribe of hell, thou</LINE>
<LINE>shalt enjoy her; therefore make money. A pox of</LINE>
<LINE>drowning thyself! it is clean out of the way: seek</LINE>
<LINE>thou rather to be hanged in compassing thy joy than</LINE>
<LINE>to be drowned and go without her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wilt thou be fast to my hopes, if I depend on</LINE>
<LINE>the issue?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art sure of me:--go, make money:--I have told</LINE>
<LINE>thee often, and I re-tell thee again and again, I</LINE>
<LINE>hate the Moor: my cause is hearted; thine hath no</LINE>
<LINE>less reason. Let us be conjunctive in our revenge</LINE>
<LINE>against him: if thou canst cuckold him, thou dost</LINE>
<LINE>thyself a pleasure, me a sport. There are many</LINE>
<LINE>events in the womb of time which will be delivered.</LINE>
<LINE>Traverse! go, provide thy money. We will have more</LINE>
<LINE>of this to-morrow. Adieu.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where shall we meet i' the morning?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>At my lodging.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll be with thee betimes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to; farewell. Do you hear, Roderigo?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What say you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No more of drowning, do you hear?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am changed: I'll go sell all my land.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thus do I ever make my fool my purse:</LINE>
<LINE>For I mine own gain'd knowledge should profane,</LINE>
<LINE>If I would time expend with such a snipe.</LINE>
<LINE>But for my sport and profit. I hate the Moor:</LINE>
<LINE>And it is thought abroad, that 'twixt my sheets</LINE>
<LINE>He has done my office: I know not if't be true;</LINE>
<LINE>But I, for mere suspicion in that kind,</LINE>
<LINE>Will do as if for surety. He holds me well;</LINE>
<LINE>The better shall my purpose work on him.</LINE>
<LINE>Cassio's a proper man: let me see now:</LINE>
<LINE>To get his place and to plume up my will</LINE>
<LINE>In double knavery--How, how? Let's see:--</LINE>
<LINE>After some time, to abuse Othello's ear</LINE>
<LINE>That he is too familiar with his wife.</LINE>
<LINE>He hath a person and a smooth dispose</LINE>
<LINE>To be suspected, framed to make women false.</LINE>
<LINE>The Moor is of a free and open nature,</LINE>
<LINE>That thinks men honest that but seem to be so,</LINE>
<LINE>And will as tenderly be led by the nose</LINE>
<LINE>As asses are.</LINE>
<LINE>I have't. It is engender'd. Hell and night</LINE>
<LINE>Must bring this monstrous birth to the world's light.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT II</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  A Sea-port in Cyprus. An open place near the quay.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter MONTANO and two Gentlemen</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What from the cape can you discern at sea?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing at all: it is a highwrought flood;</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot, 'twixt the heaven and the main,</LINE>
<LINE>Descry a sail.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Methinks the wind hath spoke aloud at land;</LINE>
<LINE>A fuller blast ne'er shook our battlements:</LINE>
<LINE>If it hath ruffian'd so upon the sea,</LINE>
<LINE>What ribs of oak, when mountains melt on them,</LINE>
<LINE>Can hold the mortise? What shall we hear of this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A segregation of the Turkish fleet:</LINE>
<LINE>For do but stand upon the foaming shore,</LINE>
<LINE>The chidden billow seems to pelt the clouds;</LINE>
<LINE>The wind-shaked surge, with high and monstrous mane,</LINE>
<LINE>seems to cast water on the burning bear,</LINE>
<LINE>And quench the guards of the ever-fixed pole:</LINE>
<LINE>I never did like molestation view</LINE>
<LINE>On the enchafed flood.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If that the Turkish fleet</LINE>
<LINE>Be not enshelter'd and embay'd, they are drown'd:</LINE>
<LINE>It is impossible they bear it out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter a third Gentleman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>News, lads! our wars are done.</LINE>
<LINE>The desperate tempest hath so bang'd the Turks,</LINE>
<LINE>That their designment halts: a noble ship of Venice</LINE>
<LINE>Hath seen a grievous wreck and sufferance</LINE>
<LINE>On most part of their fleet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How! is this true?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The ship is here put in,</LINE>
<LINE>A Veronesa; Michael Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>Lieutenant to the warlike Moor Othello,</LINE>
<LINE>Is come on shore: the Moor himself at sea,</LINE>
<LINE>And is in full commission here for Cyprus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad on't; 'tis a worthy governor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But this same Cassio, though he speak of comfort</LINE>
<LINE>Touching the Turkish loss, yet he looks sadly,</LINE>
<LINE>And prays the Moor be safe; for they were parted</LINE>
<LINE>With foul and violent tempest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray heavens he be;</LINE>
<LINE>For I have served him, and the man commands</LINE>
<LINE>Like a full soldier. Let's to the seaside, ho!</LINE>
<LINE>As well to see the vessel that's come in</LINE>
<LINE>As to throw out our eyes for brave Othello,</LINE>
<LINE>Even till we make the main and the aerial blue</LINE>
<LINE>An indistinct regard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Third Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, let's do so:</LINE>
<LINE>For every minute is expectancy</LINE>
<LINE>Of more arrivance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thanks, you the valiant of this warlike isle,</LINE>
<LINE>That so approve the Moor! O, let the heavens</LINE>
<LINE>Give him defence against the elements,</LINE>
<LINE>For I have lost us him on a dangerous sea.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is he well shipp'd?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>His bark is stoutly timber'd, his pilot</LINE>
<LINE>Of very expert and approved allowance;</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore my hopes, not surfeited to death,</LINE>
<LINE>Stand in bold cure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>A cry within 'A sail, a sail, a sail!'</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a fourth Gentleman</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What noise?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Fourth Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The town is empty; on the brow o' the sea</LINE>
<LINE>Stand ranks of people, and they cry 'A sail!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My hopes do shape him for the governor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Guns heard</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Gentlemen</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They do discharge their shot of courtesy:</LINE>
<LINE>Our friends at least.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you, sir, go forth,</LINE>
<LINE>And give us truth who 'tis that is arrived.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But, good lieutenant, is your general wived?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most fortunately: he hath achieved a maid</LINE>
<LINE>That paragons description and wild fame;</LINE>
<LINE>One that excels the quirks of blazoning pens,</LINE>
<LINE>And in the essential vesture of creation</LINE>
<LINE>Does tire the ingener.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter second Gentleman</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now! who has put in?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis one Iago, ancient to the general.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Has had most favourable and happy speed:</LINE>
<LINE>Tempests themselves, high seas, and howling winds,</LINE>
<LINE>The gutter'd rocks and congregated sands--</LINE>
<LINE>Traitors ensteep'd to clog the guiltless keel,--</LINE>
<LINE>As having sense of beauty, do omit</LINE>
<LINE>Their mortal natures, letting go safely by</LINE>
<LINE>The divine Desdemona.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is she?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She that I spake of, our great captain's captain,</LINE>
<LINE>Left in the conduct of the bold Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose footing here anticipates our thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>A se'nnight's speed. Great Jove, Othello guard,</LINE>
<LINE>And swell his sail with thine own powerful breath,</LINE>
<LINE>That he may bless this bay with his tall ship,</LINE>
<LINE>Make love's quick pants in Desdemona's arms,</LINE>
<LINE>Give renew'd fire to our extincted spirits</LINE>
<LINE>And bring all Cyprus comfort!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter DESDEMONA, EMILIA, IAGO, RODERIGO, and
Attendants</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O, behold,</LINE>
<LINE>The riches of the ship is come on shore!</LINE>
<LINE>Ye men of Cyprus, let her have your knees.</LINE>
<LINE>Hail to thee, lady! and the grace of heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>Before, behind thee, and on every hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Enwheel thee round!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I thank you, valiant Cassio.</LINE>
<LINE>What tidings can you tell me of my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is not yet arrived: nor know I aught</LINE>
<LINE>But that he's well and will be shortly here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, but I fear--How lost you company?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The great contention of the sea and skies</LINE>
<LINE>Parted our fellowship--But, hark! a sail.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Within 'A sail, a sail!' Guns heard</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Second Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They give their greeting to the citadel;</LINE>
<LINE>This likewise is a friend.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>See for the news.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Gentleman</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Good ancient, you are welcome.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Welcome, mistress.</LINE>
<LINE>Let it not gall your patience, good Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>That I extend my manners; 'tis my breeding</LINE>
<LINE>That gives me this bold show of courtesy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Kissing her</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, would she give you so much of her lips</LINE>
<LINE>As of her tongue she oft bestows on me,</LINE>
<LINE>You'll have enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, she has no speech.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In faith, too much;</LINE>
<LINE>I find it still, when I have list to sleep:</LINE>
<LINE>Marry, before your ladyship, I grant,</LINE>
<LINE>She puts her tongue a little in her heart,</LINE>
<LINE>And chides with thinking.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have little cause to say so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come on, come on; you are pictures out of doors,</LINE>
<LINE>Bells in your parlors, wild-cats in your kitchens,</LINE>
<LINE>Saints m your injuries, devils being offended,</LINE>
<LINE>Players in your housewifery, and housewives' in your beds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, fie upon thee, slanderer!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, it is true, or else I am a Turk:</LINE>
<LINE>You rise to play and go to bed to work.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You shall not write my praise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, let me not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What wouldst thou write of me, if thou shouldst</LINE>
<LINE>praise me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O gentle lady, do not put me to't;</LINE>
<LINE>For I am nothing, if not critical.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come on assay. There's one gone to the harbour?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not merry; but I do beguile</LINE>
<LINE>The thing I am, by seeming otherwise.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, how wouldst thou praise me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am about it; but indeed my invention</LINE>
<LINE>Comes from my pate as birdlime does from frize;</LINE>
<LINE>It plucks out brains and all: but my Muse labours,</LINE>
<LINE>And thus she is deliver'd.</LINE>
<LINE>If she be fair and wise, fairness and wit,</LINE>
<LINE>The one's for use, the other useth it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well praised! How if she be black and witty?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If she be black, and thereto have a wit,</LINE>
<LINE>She'll find a white that shall her blackness fit.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worse and worse.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How if fair and foolish?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She never yet was foolish that was fair;</LINE>
<LINE>For even her folly help'd her to an heir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These are old fond paradoxes to make fools laugh i'</LINE>
<LINE>the alehouse. What miserable praise hast thou for</LINE>
<LINE>her that's foul and foolish?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There's none so foul and foolish thereunto,</LINE>
<LINE>But does foul pranks which fair and wise ones do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O heavy ignorance! thou praisest the worst best.</LINE>
<LINE>But what praise couldst thou bestow on a deserving</LINE>
<LINE>woman indeed, one that, in the authority of her</LINE>
<LINE>merit, did justly put on the vouch of very malice itself?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She that was ever fair and never proud,</LINE>
<LINE>Had tongue at will and yet was never loud,</LINE>
<LINE>Never lack'd gold and yet went never gay,</LINE>
<LINE>Fled from her wish and yet said 'Now I may,'</LINE>
<LINE>She that being anger'd, her revenge being nigh,</LINE>
<LINE>Bade her wrong stay and her displeasure fly,</LINE>
<LINE>She that in wisdom never was so frail</LINE>
<LINE>To change the cod's head for the salmon's tail;</LINE>
<LINE>She that could think and ne'er disclose her mind,</LINE>
<LINE>See suitors following and not look behind,</LINE>
<LINE>She was a wight, if ever such wight were,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To do what?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To suckle fools and chronicle small beer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O most lame and impotent conclusion! Do not learn</LINE>
<LINE>of him, Emilia, though he be thy husband. How say</LINE>
<LINE>you, Cassio? is he not a most profane and liberal</LINE>
<LINE>counsellor?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He speaks home, madam: You may relish him more in</LINE>
<LINE>the soldier than in the scholar.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Aside</STAGEDIR>  He takes her by the palm: ay, well said,</LINE>
<LINE>whisper: with as little a web as this will I</LINE>
<LINE>ensnare as great a fly as Cassio. Ay, smile upon</LINE>
<LINE>her, do; I will gyve thee in thine own courtship.</LINE>
<LINE>You say true; 'tis so, indeed: if such tricks as</LINE>
<LINE>these strip you out of your lieutenantry, it had</LINE>
<LINE>been better you had not kissed your three fingers so</LINE>
<LINE>oft, which now again you are most apt to play the</LINE>
<LINE>sir in. Very good; well kissed! an excellent</LINE>
<LINE>courtesy! 'tis so, indeed. Yet again your fingers</LINE>
<LINE>to your lips? would they were clyster-pipes for your sake!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Trumpet within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>The Moor! I know his trumpet.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis truly so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let's meet him and receive him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lo, where he comes!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO and Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my fair warrior!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My dear Othello!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It gives me wonder great as my content</LINE>
<LINE>To see you here before me. O my soul's joy!</LINE>
<LINE>If after every tempest come such calms,</LINE>
<LINE>May the winds blow till they have waken'd death!</LINE>
<LINE>And let the labouring bark climb hills of seas</LINE>
<LINE>Olympus-high and duck again as low</LINE>
<LINE>As hell's from heaven! If it were now to die,</LINE>
<LINE>'Twere now to be most happy; for, I fear,</LINE>
<LINE>My soul hath her content so absolute</LINE>
<LINE>That not another comfort like to this</LINE>
<LINE>Succeeds in unknown fate.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The heavens forbid</LINE>
<LINE>But that our loves and comforts should increase,</LINE>
<LINE>Even as our days do grow!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Amen to that, sweet powers!</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot speak enough of this content;</LINE>
<LINE>It stops me here; it is too much of joy:</LINE>
<LINE>And this, and this, the greatest discords be</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Kissing her</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>That e'er our hearts shall make!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Aside</STAGEDIR>  O, you are well tuned now!</LINE>
<LINE>But I'll set down the pegs that make this music,</LINE>
<LINE>As honest as I am.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, let us to the castle.</LINE>
<LINE>News, friends; our wars are done, the Turks</LINE>
<LINE>are drown'd.</LINE>
<LINE>How does my old acquaintance of this isle?</LINE>
<LINE>Honey, you shall be well desired in Cyprus;</LINE>
<LINE>I have found great love amongst them. O my sweet,</LINE>
<LINE>I prattle out of fashion, and I dote</LINE>
<LINE>In mine own comforts. I prithee, good Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>Go to the bay and disembark my coffers:</LINE>
<LINE>Bring thou the master to the citadel;</LINE>
<LINE>He is a good one, and his worthiness</LINE>
<LINE>Does challenge much respect. Come, Desdemona,</LINE>
<LINE>Once more, well met at Cyprus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt OTHELLO, DESDEMONA, and Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do thou meet me presently at the harbour. Come</LINE>
<LINE>hither. If thou be'st valiant,-- as, they say, base</LINE>
<LINE>men being in love have then a nobility in their</LINE>
<LINE>natures more than is native to them--list me. The</LINE>
<LINE>lieutenant tonight watches on the court of</LINE>
<LINE>guard:--first, I must tell thee this--Desdemona is</LINE>
<LINE>directly in love with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With him! why, 'tis not possible.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lay thy finger thus, and let thy soul be instructed.</LINE>
<LINE>Mark me with what violence she first loved the Moor,</LINE>
<LINE>but for bragging and telling her fantastical lies:</LINE>
<LINE>and will she love him still for prating? let not</LINE>
<LINE>thy discreet heart think it. Her eye must be fed;</LINE>
<LINE>and what delight shall she have to look on the</LINE>
<LINE>devil? When the blood is made dull with the act of</LINE>
<LINE>sport, there should be, again to inflame it and to</LINE>
<LINE>give satiety a fresh appetite, loveliness in favour,</LINE>
<LINE>sympathy in years, manners and beauties; all which</LINE>
<LINE>the Moor is defective in: now, for want of these</LINE>
<LINE>required conveniences, her delicate tenderness will</LINE>
<LINE>find itself abused, begin to heave the gorge,</LINE>
<LINE>disrelish and abhor the Moor; very nature will</LINE>
<LINE>instruct her in it and compel her to some second</LINE>
<LINE>choice. Now, sir, this granted,--as it is a most</LINE>
<LINE>pregnant and unforced position--who stands so</LINE>
<LINE>eminent in the degree of this fortune as Cassio</LINE>
<LINE>does? a knave very voluble; no further</LINE>
<LINE>conscionable than in putting on the mere form of</LINE>
<LINE>civil and humane seeming, for the better compassing</LINE>
<LINE>of his salt and most hidden loose affection? why,</LINE>
<LINE>none; why, none: a slipper and subtle knave, a</LINE>
<LINE>finder of occasions, that has an eye can stamp and</LINE>
<LINE>counterfeit advantages, though true advantage never</LINE>
<LINE>present itself; a devilish knave. Besides, the</LINE>
<LINE>knave is handsome, young, and hath all those</LINE>
<LINE>requisites in him that folly and green minds look</LINE>
<LINE>after: a pestilent complete knave; and the woman</LINE>
<LINE>hath found him already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot believe that in her; she's full of</LINE>
<LINE>most blessed condition.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Blessed fig's-end! the wine she drinks is made of</LINE>
<LINE>grapes: if she had been blessed, she would never</LINE>
<LINE>have loved the Moor. Blessed pudding! Didst thou</LINE>
<LINE>not see her paddle with the palm of his hand? didst</LINE>
<LINE>not mark that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, that I did; but that was but courtesy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lechery, by this hand; an index and obscure prologue</LINE>
<LINE>to the history of lust and foul thoughts. They met</LINE>
<LINE>so near with their lips that their breaths embraced</LINE>
<LINE>together. Villanous thoughts, Roderigo! when these</LINE>
<LINE>mutualities so marshal the way, hard at hand comes</LINE>
<LINE>the master and main exercise, the incorporate</LINE>
<LINE>conclusion, Pish! But, sir, be you ruled by me: I</LINE>
<LINE>have brought you from Venice. Watch you to-night;</LINE>
<LINE>for the command, I'll lay't upon you. Cassio knows</LINE>
<LINE>you not. I'll not be far from you: do you find</LINE>
<LINE>some occasion to anger Cassio, either by speaking</LINE>
<LINE>too loud, or tainting his discipline; or from what</LINE>
<LINE>other course you please, which the time shall more</LINE>
<LINE>favourably minister.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, he is rash and very sudden in choler, and haply</LINE>
<LINE>may strike at you: provoke him, that he may; for</LINE>
<LINE>even out of that will I cause these of Cyprus to</LINE>
<LINE>mutiny; whose qualification shall come into no true</LINE>
<LINE>taste again but by the displanting of Cassio. So</LINE>
<LINE>shall you have a shorter journey to your desires by</LINE>
<LINE>the means I shall then have to prefer them; and the</LINE>
<LINE>impediment most profitably removed, without the</LINE>
<LINE>which there were no expectation of our prosperity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will do this, if I can bring it to any</LINE>
<LINE>opportunity.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I warrant thee. Meet me by and by at the citadel:</LINE>
<LINE>I must fetch his necessaries ashore. Farewell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Adieu.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That Cassio loves her, I do well believe it;</LINE>
<LINE>That she loves him, 'tis apt and of great credit:</LINE>
<LINE>The Moor, howbeit that I endure him not,</LINE>
<LINE>Is of a constant, loving, noble nature,</LINE>
<LINE>And I dare think he'll prove to Desdemona</LINE>
<LINE>A most dear husband. Now, I do love her too;</LINE>
<LINE>Not out of absolute lust, though peradventure</LINE>
<LINE>I stand accountant for as great a sin,</LINE>
<LINE>But partly led to diet my revenge,</LINE>
<LINE>For that I do suspect the lusty Moor</LINE>
<LINE>Hath leap'd into my seat; the thought whereof</LINE>
<LINE>Doth, like a poisonous mineral, gnaw my inwards;</LINE>
<LINE>And nothing can or shall content my soul</LINE>
<LINE>Till I am even'd with him, wife for wife,</LINE>
<LINE>Or failing so, yet that I put the Moor</LINE>
<LINE>At least into a jealousy so strong</LINE>
<LINE>That judgment cannot cure. Which thing to do,</LINE>
<LINE>If this poor trash of Venice, whom I trash</LINE>
<LINE>For his quick hunting, stand the putting on,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll have our Michael Cassio on the hip,</LINE>
<LINE>Abuse him to the Moor in the rank garb--</LINE>
<LINE>For I fear Cassio with my night-cap too--</LINE>
<LINE>Make the Moor thank me, love me and reward me.</LINE>
<LINE>For making him egregiously an ass</LINE>
<LINE>And practising upon his peace and quiet</LINE>
<LINE>Even to madness. 'Tis here, but yet confused:</LINE>
<LINE>Knavery's plain face is never seen tin used.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter a Herald with a proclamation; People
following</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Herald</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is Othello's pleasure, our noble and valiant</LINE>
<LINE>general, that, upon certain tidings now arrived,</LINE>
<LINE>importing the mere perdition of the Turkish fleet,</LINE>
<LINE>every man put himself into triumph; some to dance,</LINE>
<LINE>some to make bonfires, each man to what sport and</LINE>
<LINE>revels his addiction leads him: for, besides these</LINE>
<LINE>beneficial news, it is the celebration of his</LINE>
<LINE>nuptial. So much was his pleasure should be</LINE>
<LINE>proclaimed. All offices are open, and there is full</LINE>
<LINE>liberty of feasting from this present hour of five</LINE>
<LINE>till the bell have told eleven. Heaven bless the</LINE>
<LINE>isle of Cyprus and our noble general Othello!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  A hall in the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO, DESDEMONA, CASSIO, and Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good Michael, look you to the guard to-night:</LINE>
<LINE>Let's teach ourselves that honourable stop,</LINE>
<LINE>Not to outsport discretion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Iago hath direction what to do;</LINE>
<LINE>But, notwithstanding, with my personal eye</LINE>
<LINE>Will I look to't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Iago is most honest.</LINE>
<LINE>Michael, good night: to-morrow with your earliest</LINE>
<LINE>Let me have speech with you.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To DESDEMONA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Come, my dear love,</LINE>
<LINE>The purchase made, the fruits are to ensue;</LINE>
<LINE>That profit's yet to come 'tween me and you.</LINE>
<LINE>Good night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt OTHELLO, DESDEMONA, and Attendants</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter IAGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Welcome, Iago; we must to the watch.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not this hour, lieutenant; 'tis not yet ten o' the</LINE>
<LINE>clock. Our general cast us thus early for the love</LINE>
<LINE>of his Desdemona; who let us not therefore blame:</LINE>
<LINE>he hath not yet made wanton the night with her; and</LINE>
<LINE>she is sport for Jove.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She's a most exquisite lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And, I'll warrant her, fun of game.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed, she's a most fresh and delicate creature.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What an eye she has! methinks it sounds a parley of</LINE>
<LINE>provocation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An inviting eye; and yet methinks right modest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And when she speaks, is it not an alarum to love?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She is indeed perfection.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, happiness to their sheets! Come, lieutenant, I</LINE>
<LINE>have a stoup of wine; and here without are a brace</LINE>
<LINE>of Cyprus gallants that would fain have a measure to</LINE>
<LINE>the health of black Othello.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not to-night, good Iago: I have very poor and</LINE>
<LINE>unhappy brains for drinking: I could well wish</LINE>
<LINE>courtesy would invent some other custom of</LINE>
<LINE>entertainment.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, they are our friends; but one cup: I'll drink for</LINE>
<LINE>you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have drunk but one cup to-night, and that was</LINE>
<LINE>craftily qualified too, and, behold, what innovation</LINE>
<LINE>it makes here: I am unfortunate in the infirmity,</LINE>
<LINE>and dare not task my weakness with any more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, man! 'tis a night of revels: the gallants</LINE>
<LINE>desire it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where are they?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here at the door; I pray you, call them in.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll do't; but it dislikes me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If I can fasten but one cup upon him,</LINE>
<LINE>With that which he hath drunk to-night already,</LINE>
<LINE>He'll be as full of quarrel and offence</LINE>
<LINE>As my young mistress' dog. Now, my sick fool Roderigo,</LINE>
<LINE>Whom love hath turn'd almost the wrong side out,</LINE>
<LINE>To Desdemona hath to-night caroused</LINE>
<LINE>Potations pottle-deep; and he's to watch:</LINE>
<LINE>Three lads of Cyprus, noble swelling spirits,</LINE>
<LINE>That hold their honours in a wary distance,</LINE>
<LINE>The very elements of this warlike isle,</LINE>
<LINE>Have I to-night fluster'd with flowing cups,</LINE>
<LINE>And they watch too. Now, 'mongst this flock of drunkards,</LINE>
<LINE>Am I to put our Cassio in some action</LINE>
<LINE>That may offend the isle.--But here they come:</LINE>
<LINE>If consequence do but approve my dream,</LINE>
<LINE>My boat sails freely, both with wind and stream.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter CASSIO; with him MONTANO and Gentlemen;
servants following with wine</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Fore God, they have given me a rouse already.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good faith, a little one; not past a pint, as I am</LINE>
<LINE>a soldier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Some wine, ho!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Sings</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>And let me the canakin clink, clink;</LINE>
<LINE>And let me the canakin clink</LINE>
<LINE>A soldier's a man;</LINE>
<LINE>A life's but a span;</LINE>
<LINE>Why, then, let a soldier drink.</LINE>
<LINE>Some wine, boys!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Fore God, an excellent song.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I learned it in England, where, indeed, they are</LINE>
<LINE>most potent in potting: your Dane, your German, and</LINE>
<LINE>your swag-bellied Hollander--Drink, ho!--are nothing</LINE>
<LINE>to your English.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is your Englishman so expert in his drinking?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, he drinks you, with facility, your Dane dead</LINE>
<LINE>drunk; he sweats not to overthrow your Almain; he</LINE>
<LINE>gives your Hollander a vomit, ere the next pottle</LINE>
<LINE>can be filled.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To the health of our general!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am for it, lieutenant; and I'll do you justice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O sweet England!</LINE>
<LINE>King Stephen was a worthy peer,</LINE>
<LINE>His breeches cost him but a crown;</LINE>
<LINE>He held them sixpence all too dear,</LINE>
<LINE>With that he call'd the tailor lown.</LINE>
<LINE>He was a wight of high renown,</LINE>
<LINE>And thou art but of low degree:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis pride that pulls the country down;</LINE>
<LINE>Then take thine auld cloak about thee.</LINE>
<LINE>Some wine, ho!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, this is a more exquisite song than the other.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you hear't again?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No; for I hold him to be unworthy of his place that</LINE>
<LINE>does those things. Well, God's above all; and there</LINE>
<LINE>be souls must be saved, and there be souls must not be saved.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It's true, good lieutenant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For mine own part,--no offence to the general, nor</LINE>
<LINE>any man of quality,--I hope to be saved.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so do I too, lieutenant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but, by your leave, not before me; the</LINE>
<LINE>lieutenant is to be saved before the ancient. Let's</LINE>
<LINE>have no more of this; let's to our affairs.--Forgive</LINE>
<LINE>us our sins!--Gentlemen, let's look to our business.</LINE>
<LINE>Do not think, gentlemen. I am drunk: this is my</LINE>
<LINE>ancient; this is my right hand, and this is my left:</LINE>
<LINE>I am not drunk now; I can stand well enough, and</LINE>
<LINE>speak well enough.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Excellent well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, very well then; you must not think then that I am drunk.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To the platform, masters; come, let's set the watch.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You see this fellow that is gone before;</LINE>
<LINE>He is a soldier fit to stand by Caesar</LINE>
<LINE>And give direction: and do but see his vice;</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis to his virtue a just equinox,</LINE>
<LINE>The one as long as the other: 'tis pity of him.</LINE>
<LINE>I fear the trust Othello puts him in.</LINE>
<LINE>On some odd time of his infirmity,</LINE>
<LINE>Will shake this island.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But is he often thus?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis evermore the prologue to his sleep:</LINE>
<LINE>He'll watch the horologe a double set,</LINE>
<LINE>If drink rock not his cradle.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were well</LINE>
<LINE>The general were put in mind of it.</LINE>
<LINE>Perhaps he sees it not; or his good nature</LINE>
<LINE>Prizes the virtue that appears in Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>And looks not on his evils: is not this true?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Aside to him</STAGEDIR>  How now, Roderigo!</LINE>
<LINE>I pray you, after the lieutenant; go.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And 'tis great pity that the noble Moor</LINE>
<LINE>Should hazard such a place as his own second</LINE>
<LINE>With one of an ingraft infirmity:</LINE>
<LINE>It were an honest action to say</LINE>
<LINE>So to the Moor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not I, for this fair island:</LINE>
<LINE>I do love Cassio well; and would do much</LINE>
<LINE>To cure him of this evil--But, hark! what noise?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Cry within: 'Help! help!'</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter CASSIO, driving in RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You rogue! you rascal!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter, lieutenant?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A knave teach me my duty!</LINE>
<LINE>I'll beat the knave into a twiggen bottle.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beat me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost thou prate, rogue?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Striking RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, good lieutenant;</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Staying him</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I pray you, sir, hold your hand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me go, sir,</LINE>
<LINE>Or I'll knock you o'er the mazzard.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come,</LINE>
<LINE>you're drunk.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Drunk!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>They fight</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Aside to RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>  Away, I say; go out, and cry a mutiny.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Nay, good lieutenant,--alas, gentlemen;--</LINE>
<LINE>Help, ho!--Lieutenant,--sir,--Montano,--sir;</LINE>
<LINE>Help, masters!--Here's a goodly watch indeed!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Bell rings</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Who's that which rings the bell?--Diablo, ho!</LINE>
<LINE>The town will rise: God's will, lieutenant, hold!</LINE>
<LINE>You will be shamed for ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter OTHELLO and Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter here?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Zounds, I bleed still; I am hurt to the death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Faints</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hold, for your lives!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hold, ho! Lieutenant,--sir--Montano,--gentlemen,--</LINE>
<LINE>Have you forgot all sense of place and duty?</LINE>
<LINE>Hold! the general speaks to you; hold, hold, for shame!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, how now, ho! from whence ariseth this?</LINE>
<LINE>Are we turn'd Turks, and to ourselves do that</LINE>
<LINE>Which heaven hath forbid the Ottomites?</LINE>
<LINE>For Christian shame, put by this barbarous brawl:</LINE>
<LINE>He that stirs next to carve for his own rage</LINE>
<LINE>Holds his soul light; he dies upon his motion.</LINE>
<LINE>Silence that dreadful bell: it frights the isle</LINE>
<LINE>From her propriety. What is the matter, masters?</LINE>
<LINE>Honest Iago, that look'st dead with grieving,</LINE>
<LINE>Speak, who began this? on thy love, I charge thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not know: friends all but now, even now,</LINE>
<LINE>In quarter, and in terms like bride and groom</LINE>
<LINE>Devesting them for bed; and then, but now--</LINE>
<LINE>As if some planet had unwitted men--</LINE>
<LINE>Swords out, and tilting one at other's breast,</LINE>
<LINE>In opposition bloody. I cannot speak</LINE>
<LINE>Any beginning to this peevish odds;</LINE>
<LINE>And would in action glorious I had lost</LINE>
<LINE>Those legs that brought me to a part of it!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How comes it, Michael, you are thus forgot?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you, pardon me; I cannot speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy Montano, you were wont be civil;</LINE>
<LINE>The gravity and stillness of your youth</LINE>
<LINE>The world hath noted, and your name is great</LINE>
<LINE>In mouths of wisest censure: what's the matter,</LINE>
<LINE>That you unlace your reputation thus</LINE>
<LINE>And spend your rich opinion for the name</LINE>
<LINE>Of a night-brawler? give me answer to it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Worthy Othello, I am hurt to danger:</LINE>
<LINE>Your officer, Iago, can inform you,--</LINE>
<LINE>While I spare speech, which something now</LINE>
<LINE>offends me,--</LINE>
<LINE>Of all that I do know: nor know I aught</LINE>
<LINE>By me that's said or done amiss this night;</LINE>
<LINE>Unless self-charity be sometimes a vice,</LINE>
<LINE>And to defend ourselves it be a sin</LINE>
<LINE>When violence assails us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now, by heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>My blood begins my safer guides to rule;</LINE>
<LINE>And passion, having my best judgment collied,</LINE>
<LINE>Assays to lead the way: if I once stir,</LINE>
<LINE>Or do but lift this arm, the best of you</LINE>
<LINE>Shall sink in my rebuke. Give me to know</LINE>
<LINE>How this foul rout began, who set it on;</LINE>
<LINE>And he that is approved in this offence,</LINE>
<LINE>Though he had twinn'd with me, both at a birth,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall lose me. What! in a town of war,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet wild, the people's hearts brimful of fear,</LINE>
<LINE>To manage private and domestic quarrel,</LINE>
<LINE>In night, and on the court and guard of safety!</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis monstrous. Iago, who began't?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If partially affined, or leagued in office,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou dost deliver more or less than truth,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou art no soldier.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Touch me not so near:</LINE>
<LINE>I had rather have this tongue cut from my mouth</LINE>
<LINE>Than it should do offence to Michael Cassio;</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, I persuade myself, to speak the truth</LINE>
<LINE>Shall nothing wrong him. Thus it is, general.</LINE>
<LINE>Montano and myself being in speech,</LINE>
<LINE>There comes a fellow crying out for help:</LINE>
<LINE>And Cassio following him with determined sword,</LINE>
<LINE>To execute upon him. Sir, this gentleman</LINE>
<LINE>Steps in to Cassio, and entreats his pause:</LINE>
<LINE>Myself the crying fellow did pursue,</LINE>
<LINE>Lest by his clamour--as it so fell out--</LINE>
<LINE>The town might fall in fright: he, swift of foot,</LINE>
<LINE>Outran my purpose; and I return'd the rather</LINE>
<LINE>For that I heard the clink and fall of swords,</LINE>
<LINE>And Cassio high in oath; which till to-night</LINE>
<LINE>I ne'er might say before. When I came back--</LINE>
<LINE>For this was brief--I found them close together,</LINE>
<LINE>At blow and thrust; even as again they were</LINE>
<LINE>When you yourself did part them.</LINE>
<LINE>More of this matter cannot I report:</LINE>
<LINE>But men are men; the best sometimes forget:</LINE>
<LINE>Though Cassio did some little wrong to him,</LINE>
<LINE>As men in rage strike those that wish them best,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet surely Cassio, I believe, received</LINE>
<LINE>From him that fled some strange indignity,</LINE>
<LINE>Which patience could not pass.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know, Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>Thy honesty and love doth mince this matter,</LINE>
<LINE>Making it light to Cassio. Cassio, I love thee</LINE>
<LINE>But never more be officer of mine.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter DESDEMONA, attended</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Look, if my gentle love be not raised up!</LINE>
<LINE>I'll make thee an example.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All's well now, sweeting; come away to bed.</LINE>
<LINE>Sir, for your hurts, myself will be your surgeon:</LINE>
<LINE>Lead him off.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To MONTANO, who is led off</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Iago, look with care about the town,</LINE>
<LINE>And silence those whom this vile brawl distracted.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, Desdemona: 'tis the soldiers' life</LINE>
<LINE>To have their balmy slumbers waked with strife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt all but IAGO and CASSIO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, are you hurt, lieutenant?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, past all surgery.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, heaven forbid!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Reputation, reputation, reputation! O, I have lost</LINE>
<LINE>my reputation! I have lost the immortal part of</LINE>
<LINE>myself, and what remains is bestial. My reputation,</LINE>
<LINE>Iago, my reputation!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As I am an honest man, I thought you had received</LINE>
<LINE>some bodily wound; there is more sense in that than</LINE>
<LINE>in reputation. Reputation is an idle and most false</LINE>
<LINE>imposition: oft got without merit, and lost without</LINE>
<LINE>deserving: you have lost no reputation at all,</LINE>
<LINE>unless you repute yourself such a loser. What, man!</LINE>
<LINE>there are ways to recover the general again: you</LINE>
<LINE>are but now cast in his mood, a punishment more in</LINE>
<LINE>policy than in malice, even so as one would beat his</LINE>
<LINE>offenceless dog to affright an imperious lion: sue</LINE>
<LINE>to him again, and he's yours.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will rather sue to be despised than to deceive so</LINE>
<LINE>good a commander with so slight, so drunken, and so</LINE>
<LINE>indiscreet an officer. Drunk? and speak parrot?</LINE>
<LINE>and squabble? swagger? swear? and discourse</LINE>
<LINE>fustian with one's own shadow? O thou invisible</LINE>
<LINE>spirit of wine, if thou hast no name to be known by,</LINE>
<LINE>let us call thee devil!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What was he that you followed with your sword? What</LINE>
<LINE>had he done to you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't possible?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I remember a mass of things, but nothing distinctly;</LINE>
<LINE>a quarrel, but nothing wherefore. O God, that men</LINE>
<LINE>should put an enemy in their mouths to steal away</LINE>
<LINE>their brains! that we should, with joy, pleasance</LINE>
<LINE>revel and applause, transform ourselves into beasts!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, but you are now well enough: how came you thus</LINE>
<LINE>recovered?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It hath pleased the devil drunkenness to give place</LINE>
<LINE>to the devil wrath; one unperfectness shows me</LINE>
<LINE>another, to make me frankly despise myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, you are too severe a moraler: as the time,</LINE>
<LINE>the place, and the condition of this country</LINE>
<LINE>stands, I could heartily wish this had not befallen;</LINE>
<LINE>but, since it is as it is, mend it for your own good.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will ask him for my place again; he shall tell me</LINE>
<LINE>I am a drunkard! Had I as many mouths as Hydra,</LINE>
<LINE>such an answer would stop them all. To be now a</LINE>
<LINE>sensible man, by and by a fool, and presently a</LINE>
<LINE>beast! O strange! Every inordinate cup is</LINE>
<LINE>unblessed and the ingredient is a devil.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come, good wine is a good familiar creature,</LINE>
<LINE>if it be well used: exclaim no more against it.</LINE>
<LINE>And, good lieutenant, I think you think I love you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have well approved it, sir. I drunk!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You or any man living may be drunk! at a time, man.</LINE>
<LINE>I'll tell you what you shall do. Our general's wife</LINE>
<LINE>is now the general: may say so in this respect, for</LINE>
<LINE>that he hath devoted and given up himself to the</LINE>
<LINE>contemplation, mark, and denotement of her parts and</LINE>
<LINE>graces: confess yourself freely to her; importune</LINE>
<LINE>her help to put you in your place again: she is of</LINE>
<LINE>so free, so kind, so apt, so blessed a disposition,</LINE>
<LINE>she holds it a vice in her goodness not to do more</LINE>
<LINE>than she is requested: this broken joint between</LINE>
<LINE>you and her husband entreat her to splinter; and, my</LINE>
<LINE>fortunes against any lay worth naming, this</LINE>
<LINE>crack of your love shall grow stronger than it was before.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You advise me well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I protest, in the sincerity of love and honest kindness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think it freely; and betimes in the morning I will</LINE>
<LINE>beseech the virtuous Desdemona to undertake for me:</LINE>
<LINE>I am desperate of my fortunes if they cheque me here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are in the right. Good night, lieutenant; I</LINE>
<LINE>must to the watch.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good night, honest Iago.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And what's he then that says I play the villain?</LINE>
<LINE>When this advice is free I give and honest,</LINE>
<LINE>Probal to thinking and indeed the course</LINE>
<LINE>To win the Moor again? For 'tis most easy</LINE>
<LINE>The inclining Desdemona to subdue</LINE>
<LINE>In any honest suit: she's framed as fruitful</LINE>
<LINE>As the free elements. And then for her</LINE>
<LINE>To win the Moor--were't to renounce his baptism,</LINE>
<LINE>All seals and symbols of redeemed sin,</LINE>
<LINE>His soul is so enfetter'd to her love,</LINE>
<LINE>That she may make, unmake, do what she list,</LINE>
<LINE>Even as her appetite shall play the god</LINE>
<LINE>With his weak function. How am I then a villain</LINE>
<LINE>To counsel Cassio to this parallel course,</LINE>
<LINE>Directly to his good? Divinity of hell!</LINE>
<LINE>When devils will the blackest sins put on,</LINE>
<LINE>They do suggest at first with heavenly shows,</LINE>
<LINE>As I do now: for whiles this honest fool</LINE>
<LINE>Plies Desdemona to repair his fortunes</LINE>
<LINE>And she for him pleads strongly to the Moor,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll pour this pestilence into his ear,</LINE>
<LINE>That she repeals him for her body's lust;</LINE>
<LINE>And by how much she strives to do him good,</LINE>
<LINE>She shall undo her credit with the Moor.</LINE>
<LINE>So will I turn her virtue into pitch,</LINE>
<LINE>And out of her own goodness make the net</LINE>
<LINE>That shall enmesh them all.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now, Roderigo!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do follow here in the chase, not like a hound that</LINE>
<LINE>hunts, but one that fills up the cry. My money is</LINE>
<LINE>almost spent; I have been to-night exceedingly well</LINE>
<LINE>cudgelled; and I think the issue will be, I shall</LINE>
<LINE>have so much experience for my pains, and so, with</LINE>
<LINE>no money at all and a little more wit, return again to Venice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How poor are they that have not patience!</LINE>
<LINE>What wound did ever heal but by degrees?</LINE>
<LINE>Thou know'st we work by wit, and not by witchcraft;</LINE>
<LINE>And wit depends on dilatory time.</LINE>
<LINE>Does't not go well? Cassio hath beaten thee.</LINE>
<LINE>And thou, by that small hurt, hast cashier'd Cassio:</LINE>
<LINE>Though other things grow fair against the sun,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet fruits that blossom first will first be ripe:</LINE>
<LINE>Content thyself awhile. By the mass, 'tis morning;</LINE>
<LINE>Pleasure and action make the hours seem short.</LINE>
<LINE>Retire thee; go where thou art billeted:</LINE>
<LINE>Away, I say; thou shalt know more hereafter:</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, get thee gone.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Two things are to be done:</LINE>
<LINE>My wife must move for Cassio to her mistress;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll set her on;</LINE>
<LINE>Myself the while to draw the Moor apart,</LINE>
<LINE>And bring him jump when he may Cassio find</LINE>
<LINE>Soliciting his wife: ay, that's the way</LINE>
<LINE>Dull not device by coldness and delay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT III</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Before the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIO and some Musicians</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Masters, play here; I will content your pains;</LINE>
<LINE>Something that's brief; and bid 'Good morrow, general.'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Music</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter Clown</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why masters, have your instruments been in Naples,</LINE>
<LINE>that they speak i' the nose thus?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Musician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How, sir, how!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are these, I pray you, wind-instruments?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Musician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, marry, are they, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, thereby hangs a tail.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Musician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Whereby hangs a tale, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry. sir, by many a wind-instrument that I know.</LINE>
<LINE>But, masters, here's money for you: and the general</LINE>
<LINE>so likes your music, that he desires you, for love's</LINE>
<LINE>sake, to make no more noise with it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Musician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, sir, we will not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you have any music that may not be heard, to't</LINE>
<LINE>again: but, as they say to hear music the general</LINE>
<LINE>does not greatly care.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>First Musician</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We have none such, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then put up your pipes in your bag, for I'll away:</LINE>
<LINE>go; vanish into air; away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt Musicians</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost thou hear, my honest friend?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, I hear not your honest friend; I hear you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, keep up thy quillets. There's a poor piece</LINE>
<LINE>of gold for thee: if the gentlewoman that attends</LINE>
<LINE>the general's wife be stirring, tell her there's</LINE>
<LINE>one Cassio entreats her a little favour of speech:</LINE>
<LINE>wilt thou do this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She is stirring, sir: if she will stir hither, I</LINE>
<LINE>shall seem to notify unto her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do, good my friend.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit Clown</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter IAGO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>In happy time, Iago.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have not been a-bed, then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, no; the day had broke</LINE>
<LINE>Before we parted. I have made bold, Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>To send in to your wife: my suit to her</LINE>
<LINE>Is, that she will to virtuous Desdemona</LINE>
<LINE>Procure me some access.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll send her to you presently;</LINE>
<LINE>And I'll devise a mean to draw the Moor</LINE>
<LINE>Out of the way, that your converse and business</LINE>
<LINE>May be more free.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I humbly thank you for't.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit IAGO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I never knew</LINE>
<LINE>A Florentine more kind and honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good morrow, good Lieutenant: I am sorry</LINE>
<LINE>For your displeasure; but all will sure be well.</LINE>
<LINE>The general and his wife are talking of it;</LINE>
<LINE>And she speaks for you stoutly: the Moor replies,</LINE>
<LINE>That he you hurt is of great fame in Cyprus,</LINE>
<LINE>And great affinity, and that in wholesome wisdom</LINE>
<LINE>He might not but refuse you; but he protests he loves you</LINE>
<LINE>And needs no other suitor but his likings</LINE>
<LINE>To take the safest occasion by the front</LINE>
<LINE>To bring you in again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet, I beseech you,</LINE>
<LINE>If you think fit, or that it may be done,</LINE>
<LINE>Give me advantage of some brief discourse</LINE>
<LINE>With Desdemona alone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray you, come in;</LINE>
<LINE>I will bestow you where you shall have time</LINE>
<LINE>To speak your bosom freely.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am much bound to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  A room in the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO, IAGO, and Gentlemen</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>These letters give, Iago, to the pilot;</LINE>
<LINE>And by him do my duties to the senate:</LINE>
<LINE>That done, I will be walking on the works;</LINE>
<LINE>Repair there to me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, my good lord, I'll do't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This fortification, gentlemen, shall we see't?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Gentleman</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We'll wait upon your lordship.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  The garden of the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter DESDEMONA, CASSIO, and EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be thou assured, good Cassio, I will do</LINE>
<LINE>All my abilities in thy behalf.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good madam, do: I warrant it grieves my husband,</LINE>
<LINE>As if the case were his.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, that's an honest fellow. Do not doubt, Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>But I will have my lord and you again</LINE>
<LINE>As friendly as you were.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bounteous madam,</LINE>
<LINE>Whatever shall become of Michael Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>He's never any thing but your true servant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know't; I thank you. You do love my lord:</LINE>
<LINE>You have known him long; and be you well assured</LINE>
<LINE>He shall in strangeness stand no further off</LINE>
<LINE>Than in a polite distance.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but, lady,</LINE>
<LINE>That policy may either last so long,</LINE>
<LINE>Or feed upon such nice and waterish diet,</LINE>
<LINE>Or breed itself so out of circumstance,</LINE>
<LINE>That, I being absent and my place supplied,</LINE>
<LINE>My general will forget my love and service.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not doubt that; before Emilia here</LINE>
<LINE>I give thee warrant of thy place: assure thee,</LINE>
<LINE>If I do vow a friendship, I'll perform it</LINE>
<LINE>To the last article: my lord shall never rest;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll watch him tame and talk him out of patience;</LINE>
<LINE>His bed shall seem a school, his board a shrift;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll intermingle every thing he does</LINE>
<LINE>With Cassio's suit: therefore be merry, Cassio;</LINE>
<LINE>For thy solicitor shall rather die</LINE>
<LINE>Than give thy cause away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, here comes my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, I'll take my leave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, stay, and hear me speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, not now: I am very ill at ease,</LINE>
<LINE>Unfit for mine own purposes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, do your discretion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit CASSIO</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO and IAGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! I like not that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What dost thou say?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nothing, my lord: or if--I know not what.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Was not that Cassio parted from my wife?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassio, my lord! No, sure, I cannot think it,</LINE>
<LINE>That he would steal away so guilty-like,</LINE>
<LINE>Seeing you coming.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do believe 'twas he.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, my lord!</LINE>
<LINE>I have been talking with a suitor here,</LINE>
<LINE>A man that languishes in your displeasure.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who is't you mean?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, your lieutenant, Cassio. Good my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>If I have any grace or power to move you,</LINE>
<LINE>His present reconciliation take;</LINE>
<LINE>For if he be not one that truly loves you,</LINE>
<LINE>That errs in ignorance and not in cunning,</LINE>
<LINE>I have no judgment in an honest face:</LINE>
<LINE>I prithee, call him back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Went he hence now?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, sooth; so humbled</LINE>
<LINE>That he hath left part of his grief with me,</LINE>
<LINE>To suffer with him. Good love, call him back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not now, sweet Desdemona; some other time.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But shall't be shortly?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The sooner, sweet, for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall't be to-night at supper?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, not to-night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To-morrow dinner, then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I shall not dine at home;</LINE>
<LINE>I meet the captains at the citadel.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, then, to-morrow night; or Tuesday morn;</LINE>
<LINE>On Tuesday noon, or night; on Wednesday morn:</LINE>
<LINE>I prithee, name the time, but let it not</LINE>
<LINE>Exceed three days: in faith, he's penitent;</LINE>
<LINE>And yet his trespass, in our common reason--</LINE>
<LINE>Save that, they say, the wars must make examples</LINE>
<LINE>Out of their best--is not almost a fault</LINE>
<LINE>To incur a private cheque. When shall he come?</LINE>
<LINE>Tell me, Othello: I wonder in my soul,</LINE>
<LINE>What you would ask me, that I should deny,</LINE>
<LINE>Or stand so mammering on. What! Michael Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>That came a-wooing with you, and so many a time,</LINE>
<LINE>When I have spoke of you dispraisingly,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath ta'en your part; to have so much to do</LINE>
<LINE>To bring him in! Trust me, I could do much,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, no more: let him come when he will;</LINE>
<LINE>I will deny thee nothing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, this is not a boon;</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis as I should entreat you wear your gloves,</LINE>
<LINE>Or feed on nourishing dishes, or keep you warm,</LINE>
<LINE>Or sue to you to do a peculiar profit</LINE>
<LINE>To your own person: nay, when I have a suit</LINE>
<LINE>Wherein I mean to touch your love indeed,</LINE>
<LINE>It shall be full of poise and difficult weight</LINE>
<LINE>And fearful to be granted.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will deny thee nothing:</LINE>
<LINE>Whereon, I do beseech thee, grant me this,</LINE>
<LINE>To leave me but a little to myself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall I deny you? no: farewell, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, my Desdemona: I'll come to thee straight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Emilia, come. Be as your fancies teach you;</LINE>
<LINE>Whate'er you be, I am obedient.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt DESDEMONA and EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Excellent wretch! Perdition catch my soul,</LINE>
<LINE>But I do love thee! and when I love thee not,</LINE>
<LINE>Chaos is come again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My noble lord--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What dost thou say, Iago?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did Michael Cassio, when you woo'd my lady,</LINE>
<LINE>Know of your love?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He did, from first to last: why dost thou ask?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But for a satisfaction of my thought;</LINE>
<LINE>No further harm.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why of thy thought, Iago?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I did not think he had been acquainted with her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, yes; and went between us very oft.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed! ay, indeed: discern'st thou aught in that?</LINE>
<LINE>Is he not honest?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Honest, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Honest! ay, honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, for aught I know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What dost thou think?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think, my lord!</LINE>
<LINE>By heaven, he echoes me,</LINE>
<LINE>As if there were some monster in his thought</LINE>
<LINE>Too hideous to be shown. Thou dost mean something:</LINE>
<LINE>I heard thee say even now, thou likedst not that,</LINE>
<LINE>When Cassio left my wife: what didst not like?</LINE>
<LINE>And when I told thee he was of my counsel</LINE>
<LINE>In my whole course of wooing, thou criedst 'Indeed!'</LINE>
<LINE>And didst contract and purse thy brow together,</LINE>
<LINE>As if thou then hadst shut up in thy brain</LINE>
<LINE>Some horrible conceit: if thou dost love me,</LINE>
<LINE>Show me thy thought.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, you know I love you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think thou dost;</LINE>
<LINE>And, for I know thou'rt full of love and honesty,</LINE>
<LINE>And weigh'st thy words before thou givest them breath,</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore these stops of thine fright me the more:</LINE>
<LINE>For such things in a false disloyal knave</LINE>
<LINE>Are tricks of custom, but in a man that's just</LINE>
<LINE>They are close delations, working from the heart</LINE>
<LINE>That passion cannot rule.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>For Michael Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>I dare be sworn I think that he is honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think so too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Men should be what they seem;</LINE>
<LINE>Or those that be not, would they might seem none!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Certain, men should be what they seem.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, then, I think Cassio's an honest man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, yet there's more in this:</LINE>
<LINE>I prithee, speak to me as to thy thinkings,</LINE>
<LINE>As thou dost ruminate, and give thy worst of thoughts</LINE>
<LINE>The worst of words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good my lord, pardon me:</LINE>
<LINE>Though I am bound to every act of duty,</LINE>
<LINE>I am not bound to that all slaves are free to.</LINE>
<LINE>Utter my thoughts? Why, say they are vile and false;</LINE>
<LINE>As where's that palace whereinto foul things</LINE>
<LINE>Sometimes intrude not? who has a breast so pure,</LINE>
<LINE>But some uncleanly apprehensions</LINE>
<LINE>Keep leets and law-days and in session sit</LINE>
<LINE>With meditations lawful?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou dost conspire against thy friend, Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>If thou but think'st him wrong'd and makest his ear</LINE>
<LINE>A stranger to thy thoughts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do beseech you--</LINE>
<LINE>Though I perchance am vicious in my guess,</LINE>
<LINE>As, I confess, it is my nature's plague</LINE>
<LINE>To spy into abuses, and oft my jealousy</LINE>
<LINE>Shapes faults that are not--that your wisdom yet,</LINE>
<LINE>From one that so imperfectly conceits,</LINE>
<LINE>Would take no notice, nor build yourself a trouble</LINE>
<LINE>Out of his scattering and unsure observance.</LINE>
<LINE>It were not for your quiet nor your good,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor for my manhood, honesty, or wisdom,</LINE>
<LINE>To let you know my thoughts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What dost thou mean?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good name in man and woman, dear my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>Is the immediate jewel of their souls:</LINE>
<LINE>Who steals my purse steals trash; 'tis something, nothing;</LINE>
<LINE>'Twas mine, 'tis his, and has been slave to thousands:</LINE>
<LINE>But he that filches from me my good name</LINE>
<LINE>Robs me of that which not enriches him</LINE>
<LINE>And makes me poor indeed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By heaven, I'll know thy thoughts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You cannot, if my heart were in your hand;</LINE>
<LINE>Nor shall not, whilst 'tis in my custody.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, beware, my lord, of jealousy;</LINE>
<LINE>It is the green-eyed monster which doth mock</LINE>
<LINE>The meat it feeds on; that cuckold lives in bliss</LINE>
<LINE>Who, certain of his fate, loves not his wronger;</LINE>
<LINE>But, O, what damned minutes tells he o'er</LINE>
<LINE>Who dotes, yet doubts, suspects, yet strongly loves!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O misery!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Poor and content is rich and rich enough,</LINE>
<LINE>But riches fineless is as poor as winter</LINE>
<LINE>To him that ever fears he shall be poor.</LINE>
<LINE>Good heaven, the souls of all my tribe defend</LINE>
<LINE>From jealousy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, why is this?</LINE>
<LINE>Think'st thou I'ld make a lie of jealousy,</LINE>
<LINE>To follow still the changes of the moon</LINE>
<LINE>With fresh suspicions? No; to be once in doubt</LINE>
<LINE>Is once to be resolved: exchange me for a goat,</LINE>
<LINE>When I shall turn the business of my soul</LINE>
<LINE>To such exsufflicate and blown surmises,</LINE>
<LINE>Matching thy inference. 'Tis not to make me jealous</LINE>
<LINE>To say my wife is fair, feeds well, loves company,</LINE>
<LINE>Is free of speech, sings, plays and dances well;</LINE>
<LINE>Where virtue is, these are more virtuous:</LINE>
<LINE>Nor from mine own weak merits will I draw</LINE>
<LINE>The smallest fear or doubt of her revolt;</LINE>
<LINE>For she had eyes, and chose me. No, Iago;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll see before I doubt; when I doubt, prove;</LINE>
<LINE>And on the proof, there is no more but this,--</LINE>
<LINE>Away at once with love or jealousy!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad of it; for now I shall have reason</LINE>
<LINE>To show the love and duty that I bear you</LINE>
<LINE>With franker spirit: therefore, as I am bound,</LINE>
<LINE>Receive it from me. I speak not yet of proof.</LINE>
<LINE>Look to your wife; observe her well with Cassio;</LINE>
<LINE>Wear your eye thus, not jealous nor secure:</LINE>
<LINE>I would not have your free and noble nature,</LINE>
<LINE>Out of self-bounty, be abused; look to't:</LINE>
<LINE>I know our country disposition well;</LINE>
<LINE>In Venice they do let heaven see the pranks</LINE>
<LINE>They dare not show their husbands; their best conscience</LINE>
<LINE>Is not to leave't undone, but keep't unknown.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost thou say so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She did deceive her father, marrying you;</LINE>
<LINE>And when she seem'd to shake and fear your looks,</LINE>
<LINE>She loved them most.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And so she did.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, go to then;</LINE>
<LINE>She that, so young, could give out such a seeming,</LINE>
<LINE>To seal her father's eyes up close as oak-</LINE>
<LINE>He thought 'twas witchcraft--but I am much to blame;</LINE>
<LINE>I humbly do beseech you of your pardon</LINE>
<LINE>For too much loving you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am bound to thee for ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I see this hath a little dash'd your spirits.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not a jot, not a jot.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I' faith, I fear it has.</LINE>
<LINE>I hope you will consider what is spoke</LINE>
<LINE>Comes from my love. But I do see you're moved:</LINE>
<LINE>I am to pray you not to strain my speech</LINE>
<LINE>To grosser issues nor to larger reach</LINE>
<LINE>Than to suspicion.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Should you do so, my lord,</LINE>
<LINE>My speech should fall into such vile success</LINE>
<LINE>As my thoughts aim not at. Cassio's my worthy friend--</LINE>
<LINE>My lord, I see you're moved.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, not much moved:</LINE>
<LINE>I do not think but Desdemona's honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Long live she so! and long live you to think so!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And yet, how nature erring from itself,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, there's the point: as--to be bold with you--</LINE>
<LINE>Not to affect many proposed matches</LINE>
<LINE>Of her own clime, complexion, and degree,</LINE>
<LINE>Whereto we see in all things nature tends--</LINE>
<LINE>Foh! one may smell in such a will most rank,</LINE>
<LINE>Foul disproportion thoughts unnatural.</LINE>
<LINE>But pardon me; I do not in position</LINE>
<LINE>Distinctly speak of her; though I may fear</LINE>
<LINE>Her will, recoiling to her better judgment,</LINE>
<LINE>May fall to match you with her country forms</LINE>
<LINE>And happily repent.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Farewell, farewell:</LINE>
<LINE>If more thou dost perceive, let me know more;</LINE>
<LINE>Set on thy wife to observe: leave me, Iago:</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Going</STAGEDIR>  My lord, I take my leave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why did I marry? This honest creature doubtless</LINE>
<LINE>Sees and knows more, much more, than he unfolds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Returning</STAGEDIR>  My lord, I would I might entreat</LINE>
<LINE>your honour</LINE>
<LINE>To scan this thing no further; leave it to time:</LINE>
<LINE>Though it be fit that Cassio have his place,</LINE>
<LINE>For sure, he fills it up with great ability,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet, if you please to hold him off awhile,</LINE>
<LINE>You shall by that perceive him and his means:</LINE>
<LINE>Note, if your lady strain his entertainment</LINE>
<LINE>With any strong or vehement importunity;</LINE>
<LINE>Much will be seen in that. In the mean time,</LINE>
<LINE>Let me be thought too busy in my fears--</LINE>
<LINE>As worthy cause I have to fear I am--</LINE>
<LINE>And hold her free, I do beseech your honour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fear not my government.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I once more take my leave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This fellow's of exceeding honesty,</LINE>
<LINE>And knows all qualities, with a learned spirit,</LINE>
<LINE>Of human dealings. If I do prove her haggard,</LINE>
<LINE>Though that her jesses were my dear heartstrings,</LINE>
<LINE>I'ld whistle her off and let her down the wind,</LINE>
<LINE>To pray at fortune. Haply, for I am black</LINE>
<LINE>And have not those soft parts of conversation</LINE>
<LINE>That chamberers have, or for I am declined</LINE>
<LINE>Into the vale of years,--yet that's not much--</LINE>
<LINE>She's gone. I am abused; and my relief</LINE>
<LINE>Must be to loathe her. O curse of marriage,</LINE>
<LINE>That we can call these delicate creatures ours,</LINE>
<LINE>And not their appetites! I had rather be a toad,</LINE>
<LINE>And live upon the vapour of a dungeon,</LINE>
<LINE>Than keep a corner in the thing I love</LINE>
<LINE>For others' uses. Yet, 'tis the plague of great ones;</LINE>
<LINE>Prerogatived are they less than the base;</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis destiny unshunnable, like death:</LINE>
<LINE>Even then this forked plague is fated to us</LINE>
<LINE>When we do quicken. Desdemona comes:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter DESDEMONA and EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>If she be false, O, then heaven mocks itself!</LINE>
<LINE>I'll not believe't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, my dear Othello!</LINE>
<LINE>Your dinner, and the generous islanders</LINE>
<LINE>By you invited, do attend your presence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am to blame.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why do you speak so faintly?</LINE>
<LINE>Are you not well?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have a pain upon my forehead here.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, that's with watching; 'twill away again:</LINE>
<LINE>Let me but bind it hard, within this hour</LINE>
<LINE>It will be well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your napkin is too little:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>He puts the handkerchief from him; and it drops</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Let it alone. Come, I'll go in with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am very sorry that you are not well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt OTHELLO and DESDEMONA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad I have found this napkin:</LINE>
<LINE>This was her first remembrance from the Moor:</LINE>
<LINE>My wayward husband hath a hundred times</LINE>
<LINE>Woo'd me to steal it; but she so loves the token,</LINE>
<LINE>For he conjured her she should ever keep it,</LINE>
<LINE>That she reserves it evermore about her</LINE>
<LINE>To kiss and talk to. I'll have the work ta'en out,</LINE>
<LINE>And give't Iago: what he will do with it</LINE>
<LINE>Heaven knows, not I;</LINE>
<LINE>I nothing but to please his fantasy.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter Iago</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now! what do you here alone?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not you chide; I have a thing for you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A thing for me? it is a common thing--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To have a foolish wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, is that all? What will you give me now</LINE>
<LINE>For the same handkerchief?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What handkerchief?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What handkerchief?</LINE>
<LINE>Why, that the Moor first gave to Desdemona;</LINE>
<LINE>That which so often you did bid me steal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hast stol'n it from her?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, 'faith; she let it drop by negligence.</LINE>
<LINE>And, to the advantage, I, being here, took't up.</LINE>
<LINE>Look, here it is.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A good wench; give it me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What will you do with 't, that you have been</LINE>
<LINE>so earnest</LINE>
<LINE>To have me filch it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Snatching it</STAGEDIR>  Why, what's that to you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it be not for some purpose of import,</LINE>
<LINE>Give't me again: poor lady, she'll run mad</LINE>
<LINE>When she shall lack it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be not acknown on 't; I have use for it.</LINE>
<LINE>Go, leave me.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>I will in Cassio's lodging lose this napkin,</LINE>
<LINE>And let him find it. Trifles light as air</LINE>
<LINE>Are to the jealous confirmations strong</LINE>
<LINE>As proofs of holy writ: this may do something.</LINE>
<LINE>The Moor already changes with my poison:</LINE>
<LINE>Dangerous conceits are, in their natures, poisons.</LINE>
<LINE>Which at the first are scarce found to distaste,</LINE>
<LINE>But with a little act upon the blood.</LINE>
<LINE>Burn like the mines of Sulphur. I did say so:</LINE>
<LINE>Look, where he comes!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter OTHELLO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Not poppy, nor mandragora,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor all the drowsy syrups of the world,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall ever medicine thee to that sweet sleep</LINE>
<LINE>Which thou owedst yesterday.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! ha! false to me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, how now, general! no more of that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Avaunt! be gone! thou hast set me on the rack:</LINE>
<LINE>I swear 'tis better to be much abused</LINE>
<LINE>Than but to know't a little.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What sense had I of her stol'n hours of lust?</LINE>
<LINE>I saw't not, thought it not, it harm'd not me:</LINE>
<LINE>I slept the next night well, was free and merry;</LINE>
<LINE>I found not Cassio's kisses on her lips:</LINE>
<LINE>He that is robb'd, not wanting what is stol'n,</LINE>
<LINE>Let him not know't, and he's not robb'd at all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am sorry to hear this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I had been happy, if the general camp,</LINE>
<LINE>Pioners and all, had tasted her sweet body,</LINE>
<LINE>So I had nothing known. O, now, for ever</LINE>
<LINE>Farewell the tranquil mind! farewell content!</LINE>
<LINE>Farewell the plumed troop, and the big wars,</LINE>
<LINE>That make ambition virtue! O, farewell!</LINE>
<LINE>Farewell the neighing steed, and the shrill trump,</LINE>
<LINE>The spirit-stirring drum, the ear-piercing fife,</LINE>
<LINE>The royal banner, and all quality,</LINE>
<LINE>Pride, pomp and circumstance of glorious war!</LINE>
<LINE>And, O you mortal engines, whose rude throats</LINE>
<LINE>The immortal Jove's dead clamours counterfeit,</LINE>
<LINE>Farewell! Othello's occupation's gone!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't possible, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Villain, be sure thou prove my love a whore,</LINE>
<LINE>Be sure of it; give me the ocular proof:</LINE>
<LINE>Or by the worth of man's eternal soul,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hadst been better have been born a dog</LINE>
<LINE>Than answer my waked wrath!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't come to this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Make me to see't; or, at the least, so prove it,</LINE>
<LINE>That the probation bear no hinge nor loop</LINE>
<LINE>To hang a doubt on; or woe upon thy life!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My noble lord,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If thou dost slander her and torture me,</LINE>
<LINE>Never pray more; abandon all remorse;</LINE>
<LINE>On horror's head horrors accumulate;</LINE>
<LINE>Do deeds to make heaven weep, all earth amazed;</LINE>
<LINE>For nothing canst thou to damnation add</LINE>
<LINE>Greater than that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O grace! O heaven forgive me!</LINE>
<LINE>Are you a man? have you a soul or sense?</LINE>
<LINE>God be wi' you; take mine office. O wretched fool.</LINE>
<LINE>That livest to make thine honesty a vice!</LINE>
<LINE>O monstrous world! Take note, take note, O world,</LINE>
<LINE>To be direct and honest is not safe.</LINE>
<LINE>I thank you for this profit; and from hence</LINE>
<LINE>I'll love no friend, sith love breeds such offence.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, stay: thou shouldst be honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I should be wise, for honesty's a fool</LINE>
<LINE>And loses that it works for.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By the world,</LINE>
<LINE>I think my wife be honest and think she is not;</LINE>
<LINE>I think that thou art just and think thou art not.</LINE>
<LINE>I'll have some proof. Her name, that was as fresh</LINE>
<LINE>As Dian's visage, is now begrimed and black</LINE>
<LINE>As mine own face. If there be cords, or knives,</LINE>
<LINE>Poison, or fire, or suffocating streams,</LINE>
<LINE>I'll not endure it. Would I were satisfied!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I see, sir, you are eaten up with passion:</LINE>
<LINE>I do repent me that I put it to you.</LINE>
<LINE>You would be satisfied?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Would! nay, I will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And may: but, how? how satisfied, my lord?</LINE>
<LINE>Would you, the supervisor, grossly gape on--</LINE>
<LINE>Behold her topp'd?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Death and damnation! O!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It were a tedious difficulty, I think,</LINE>
<LINE>To bring them to that prospect: damn them then,</LINE>
<LINE>If ever mortal eyes do see them bolster</LINE>
<LINE>More than their own! What then? how then?</LINE>
<LINE>What shall I say? Where's satisfaction?</LINE>
<LINE>It is impossible you should see this,</LINE>
<LINE>Were they as prime as goats, as hot as monkeys,</LINE>
<LINE>As salt as wolves in pride, and fools as gross</LINE>
<LINE>As ignorance made drunk. But yet, I say,</LINE>
<LINE>If imputation and strong circumstances,</LINE>
<LINE>Which lead directly to the door of truth,</LINE>
<LINE>Will give you satisfaction, you may have't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give me a living reason she's disloyal.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not like the office:</LINE>
<LINE>But, sith I am enter'd in this cause so far,</LINE>
<LINE>Prick'd to't by foolish honesty and love,</LINE>
<LINE>I will go on. I lay with Cassio lately;</LINE>
<LINE>And, being troubled with a raging tooth,</LINE>
<LINE>I could not sleep.</LINE>
<LINE>There are a kind of men so loose of soul,</LINE>
<LINE>That in their sleeps will mutter their affairs:</LINE>
<LINE>One of this kind is Cassio:</LINE>
<LINE>In sleep I heard him say 'Sweet Desdemona,</LINE>
<LINE>Let us be wary, let us hide our loves;'</LINE>
<LINE>And then, sir, would he gripe and wring my hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Cry 'O sweet creature!' and then kiss me hard,</LINE>
<LINE>As if he pluck'd up kisses by the roots</LINE>
<LINE>That grew upon my lips: then laid his leg</LINE>
<LINE>Over my thigh, and sigh'd, and kiss'd; and then</LINE>
<LINE>Cried 'Cursed fate that gave thee to the Moor!'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O monstrous! monstrous!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, this was but his dream.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But this denoted a foregone conclusion:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis a shrewd doubt, though it be but a dream.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And this may help to thicken other proofs</LINE>
<LINE>That do demonstrate thinly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I'll tear her all to pieces.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, but be wise: yet we see nothing done;</LINE>
<LINE>She may be honest yet. Tell me but this,</LINE>
<LINE>Have you not sometimes seen a handkerchief</LINE>
<LINE>Spotted with strawberries in your wife's hand?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I gave her such a one; 'twas my first gift.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not that; but such a handkerchief--</LINE>
<LINE>I am sure it was your wife's--did I to-day</LINE>
<LINE>See Cassio wipe his beard with.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it be that--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If it be that, or any that was hers,</LINE>
<LINE>It speaks against her with the other proofs.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, that the slave had forty thousand lives!</LINE>
<LINE>One is too poor, too weak for my revenge.</LINE>
<LINE>Now do I see 'tis true. Look here, Iago;</LINE>
<LINE>All my fond love thus do I blow to heaven.</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis gone.</LINE>
<LINE>Arise, black vengeance, from thy hollow cell!</LINE>
<LINE>Yield up, O love, thy crown and hearted throne</LINE>
<LINE>To tyrannous hate! Swell, bosom, with thy fraught,</LINE>
<LINE>For 'tis of aspics' tongues!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yet be content.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, blood, blood, blood!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Patience, I say; your mind perhaps may change.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never, Iago: Like to the Pontic sea,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose icy current and compulsive course</LINE>
<LINE>Ne'er feels retiring ebb, but keeps due on</LINE>
<LINE>To the Propontic and the Hellespont,</LINE>
<LINE>Even so my bloody thoughts, with violent pace,</LINE>
<LINE>Shall ne'er look back, ne'er ebb to humble love,</LINE>
<LINE>Till that a capable and wide revenge</LINE>
<LINE>Swallow them up. Now, by yond marble heaven,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Kneels</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>In the due reverence of a sacred vow</LINE>
<LINE>I here engage my words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not rise yet.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Kneels</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Witness, you ever-burning lights above,</LINE>
<LINE>You elements that clip us round about,</LINE>
<LINE>Witness that here Iago doth give up</LINE>
<LINE>The execution of his wit, hands, heart,</LINE>
<LINE>To wrong'd Othello's service! Let him command,</LINE>
<LINE>And to obey shall be in me remorse,</LINE>
<LINE>What bloody business ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>They rise</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I greet thy love,</LINE>
<LINE>Not with vain thanks, but with acceptance bounteous,</LINE>
<LINE>And will upon the instant put thee to't:</LINE>
<LINE>Within these three days let me hear thee say</LINE>
<LINE>That Cassio's not alive.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My friend is dead; 'tis done at your request:</LINE>
<LINE>But let her live.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Damn her, lewd minx! O, damn her!</LINE>
<LINE>Come, go with me apart; I will withdraw,</LINE>
<LINE>To furnish me with some swift means of death</LINE>
<LINE>For the fair devil. Now art thou my lieutenant.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am your own for ever.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE IV.  Before the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter DESDEMONA, EMILIA, and Clown</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you know, sirrah, where Lieutenant Cassio lies?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I dare not say he lies any where.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, man?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's a soldier, and for one to say a soldier lies,</LINE>
<LINE>is stabbing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to: where lodges he?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To tell you where he lodges, is to tell you where I lie.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Can any thing be made of this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not where he lodges, and for me to devise a</LINE>
<LINE>lodging and say he lies here or he lies there, were</LINE>
<LINE>to lie in mine own throat.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Can you inquire him out, and be edified by report?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will catechise the world for him; that is, make</LINE>
<LINE>questions, and by them answer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Seek him, bid him come hither: tell him I have</LINE>
<LINE>moved my lord on his behalf, and hope all will be well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>Clown</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To do this is within the compass of man's wit: and</LINE>
<LINE>therefore I will attempt the doing it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where should I lose that handkerchief, Emilia?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Believe me, I had rather have lost my purse</LINE>
<LINE>Full of crusadoes: and, but my noble Moor</LINE>
<LINE>Is true of mind and made of no such baseness</LINE>
<LINE>As jealous creatures are, it were enough</LINE>
<LINE>To put him to ill thinking.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is he not jealous?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who, he? I think the sun where he was born</LINE>
<LINE>Drew all such humours from him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look, where he comes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not leave him now till Cassio</LINE>
<LINE>Be call'd to him.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How is't with you, my lord</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, my good lady.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O, hardness to dissemble!--</LINE>
<LINE>How do you, Desdemona?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, my good lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Give me your hand: this hand is moist, my lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It yet hath felt no age nor known no sorrow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This argues fruitfulness and liberal heart:</LINE>
<LINE>Hot, hot, and moist: this hand of yours requires</LINE>
<LINE>A sequester from liberty, fasting and prayer,</LINE>
<LINE>Much castigation, exercise devout;</LINE>
<LINE>For here's a young and sweating devil here,</LINE>
<LINE>That commonly rebels. 'Tis a good hand,</LINE>
<LINE>A frank one.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You may, indeed, say so;</LINE>
<LINE>For 'twas that hand that gave away my heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A liberal hand: the hearts of old gave hands;</LINE>
<LINE>But our new heraldry is hands, not hearts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot speak of this. Come now, your promise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What promise, chuck?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have sent to bid Cassio come speak with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have a salt and sorry rheum offends me;</LINE>
<LINE>Lend me thy handkerchief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That which I gave you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have it not about me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, indeed, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That is a fault.</LINE>
<LINE>That handkerchief</LINE>
<LINE>Did an Egyptian to my mother give;</LINE>
<LINE>She was a charmer, and could almost read</LINE>
<LINE>The thoughts of people: she told her, while</LINE>
<LINE>she kept it,</LINE>
<LINE>'Twould make her amiable and subdue my father</LINE>
<LINE>Entirely to her love, but if she lost it</LINE>
<LINE>Or made gift of it, my father's eye</LINE>
<LINE>Should hold her loathed and his spirits should hunt</LINE>
<LINE>After new fancies: she, dying, gave it me;</LINE>
<LINE>And bid me, when my fate would have me wive,</LINE>
<LINE>To give it her. I did so: and take heed on't;</LINE>
<LINE>Make it a darling like your precious eye;</LINE>
<LINE>To lose't or give't away were such perdition</LINE>
<LINE>As nothing else could match.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't possible?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis true: there's magic in the web of it:</LINE>
<LINE>A sibyl, that had number'd in the world</LINE>
<LINE>The sun to course two hundred compasses,</LINE>
<LINE>In her prophetic fury sew'd the work;</LINE>
<LINE>The worms were hallow'd that did breed the silk;</LINE>
<LINE>And it was dyed in mummy which the skilful</LINE>
<LINE>Conserved of maidens' hearts.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed! is't true?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most veritable; therefore look to't well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then would to God that I had never seen't!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha! wherefore?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why do you speak so startingly and rash?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't lost? is't gone? speak, is it out</LINE>
<LINE>o' the way?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Heaven bless us!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Say you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is not lost; but what an if it were?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I say, it is not lost.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fetch't, let me see't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, so I can, sir, but I will not now.</LINE>
<LINE>This is a trick to put me from my suit:</LINE>
<LINE>Pray you, let Cassio be received again.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fetch me the handkerchief: my mind misgives.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come;</LINE>
<LINE>You'll never meet a more sufficient man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The handkerchief!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray, talk me of Cassio.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The handkerchief!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A man that all his time</LINE>
<LINE>Hath founded his good fortunes on your love,</LINE>
<LINE>Shared dangers with you,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The handkerchief!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In sooth, you are to blame.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is not this man jealous?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I ne'er saw this before.</LINE>
<LINE>Sure, there's some wonder in this handkerchief:</LINE>
<LINE>I am most unhappy in the loss of it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis not a year or two shows us a man:</LINE>
<LINE>They are all but stomachs, and we all but food;</LINE>
<LINE>To eat us hungerly, and when they are full,</LINE>
<LINE>They belch us. Look you, Cassio and my husband!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIO and IAGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is no other way; 'tis she must do't:</LINE>
<LINE>And, lo, the happiness! go, and importune her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, good Cassio! what's the news with you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, my former suit: I do beseech you</LINE>
<LINE>That by your virtuous means I may again</LINE>
<LINE>Exist, and be a member of his love</LINE>
<LINE>Whom I with all the office of my heart</LINE>
<LINE>Entirely honour: I would not be delay'd.</LINE>
<LINE>If my offence be of such mortal kind</LINE>
<LINE>That nor my service past, nor present sorrows,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor purposed merit in futurity,</LINE>
<LINE>Can ransom me into his love again,</LINE>
<LINE>But to know so must be my benefit;</LINE>
<LINE>So shall I clothe me in a forced content,</LINE>
<LINE>And shut myself up in some other course,</LINE>
<LINE>To fortune's alms.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, thrice-gentle Cassio!</LINE>
<LINE>My advocation is not now in tune;</LINE>
<LINE>My lord is not my lord; nor should I know him,</LINE>
<LINE>Were he in favour as in humour alter'd.</LINE>
<LINE>So help me every spirit sanctified,</LINE>
<LINE>As I have spoken for you all my best</LINE>
<LINE>And stood within the blank of his displeasure</LINE>
<LINE>For my free speech! you must awhile be patient:</LINE>
<LINE>What I can do I will; and more I will</LINE>
<LINE>Than for myself I dare: let that suffice you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is my lord angry?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He went hence but now,</LINE>
<LINE>And certainly in strange unquietness.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Can he be angry? I have seen the cannon,</LINE>
<LINE>When it hath blown his ranks into the air,</LINE>
<LINE>And, like the devil, from his very arm</LINE>
<LINE>Puff'd his own brother:--and can he be angry?</LINE>
<LINE>Something of moment then: I will go meet him:</LINE>
<LINE>There's matter in't indeed, if he be angry.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I prithee, do so.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit IAGO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Something, sure, of state,</LINE>
<LINE>Either from Venice, or some unhatch'd practise</LINE>
<LINE>Made demonstrable here in Cyprus to him,</LINE>
<LINE>Hath puddled his clear spirit: and in such cases</LINE>
<LINE>Men's natures wrangle with inferior things,</LINE>
<LINE>Though great ones are their object. 'Tis even so;</LINE>
<LINE>For let our finger ache, and it indues</LINE>
<LINE>Our other healthful members even to that sense</LINE>
<LINE>Of pain: nay, we must think men are not gods,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor of them look for such observances</LINE>
<LINE>As fit the bridal. Beshrew me much, Emilia,</LINE>
<LINE>I was, unhandsome warrior as I am,</LINE>
<LINE>Arraigning his unkindness with my soul;</LINE>
<LINE>But now I find I had suborn'd the witness,</LINE>
<LINE>And he's indicted falsely.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray heaven it be state-matters, as you think,</LINE>
<LINE>And no conception nor no jealous toy</LINE>
<LINE>Concerning you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas the day! I never gave him cause.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But jealous souls will not be answer'd so;</LINE>
<LINE>They are not ever jealous for the cause,</LINE>
<LINE>But jealous for they are jealous: 'tis a monster</LINE>
<LINE>Begot upon itself, born on itself.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Heaven keep that monster from Othello's mind!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lady, amen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will go seek him. Cassio, walk hereabout:</LINE>
<LINE>If I do find him fit, I'll move your suit</LINE>
<LINE>And seek to effect it to my uttermost.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I humbly thank your ladyship.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exeunt DESDEMONA and EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter BIANCA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Save you, friend Cassio!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What make you from home?</LINE>
<LINE>How is it with you, my most fair Bianca?</LINE>
<LINE>I' faith, sweet love, I was coming to your house.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And I was going to your lodging, Cassio.</LINE>
<LINE>What, keep a week away? seven days and nights?</LINE>
<LINE>Eight score eight hours? and lovers' absent hours,</LINE>
<LINE>More tedious than the dial eight score times?</LINE>
<LINE>O weary reckoning!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pardon me, Bianca:</LINE>
<LINE>I have this while with leaden thoughts been press'd:</LINE>
<LINE>But I shall, in a more continuate time,</LINE>
<LINE>Strike off this score of absence. Sweet Bianca,</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Giving her DESDEMONA's handkerchief</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Take me this work out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Cassio, whence came this?</LINE>
<LINE>This is some token from a newer friend:</LINE>
<LINE>To the felt absence now I feel a cause:</LINE>
<LINE>Is't come to this? Well, well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to, woman!</LINE>
<LINE>Throw your vile guesses in the devil's teeth,</LINE>
<LINE>From whence you have them. You are jealous now</LINE>
<LINE>That this is from some mistress, some remembrance:</LINE>
<LINE>No, in good troth, Bianca.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, whose is it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know not, sweet: I found it in my chamber.</LINE>
<LINE>I like the work well: ere it be demanded--</LINE>
<LINE>As like enough it will--I'ld have it copied:</LINE>
<LINE>Take it, and do't; and leave me for this time.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Leave you! wherefore?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do attend here on the general;</LINE>
<LINE>And think it no addition, nor my wish,</LINE>
<LINE>To have him see me woman'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, I pray you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not that I love you not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But that you do not love me.</LINE>
<LINE>I pray you, bring me on the way a little,</LINE>
<LINE>And say if I shall see you soon at night.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis but a little way that I can bring you;</LINE>
<LINE>For I attend here: but I'll see you soon.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis very good; I must be circumstanced.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT IV</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Cyprus. Before the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO and IAGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you think so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think so, Iago!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What,</LINE>
<LINE>To kiss in private?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An unauthorized kiss.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Or to be naked with her friend in bed</LINE>
<LINE>An hour or more, not meaning any harm?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Naked in bed, Iago, and not mean harm!</LINE>
<LINE>It is hypocrisy against the devil:</LINE>
<LINE>They that mean virtuously, and yet do so,</LINE>
<LINE>The devil their virtue tempts, and they tempt heaven.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So they do nothing, 'tis a venial slip:</LINE>
<LINE>But if I give my wife a handkerchief,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, then, 'tis hers, my lord; and, being hers,</LINE>
<LINE>She may, I think, bestow't on any man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She is protectress of her honour too:</LINE>
<LINE>May she give that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Her honour is an essence that's not seen;</LINE>
<LINE>They have it very oft that have it not:</LINE>
<LINE>But, for the handkerchief,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By heaven, I would most gladly have forgot it.</LINE>
<LINE>Thou said'st, it comes o'er my memory,</LINE>
<LINE>As doth the raven o'er the infected house,</LINE>
<LINE>Boding to all--he had my handkerchief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, what of that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's not so good now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What,</LINE>
<LINE>If I had said I had seen him do you wrong?</LINE>
<LINE>Or heard him say,--as knaves be such abroad,</LINE>
<LINE>Who having, by their own importunate suit,</LINE>
<LINE>Or voluntary dotage of some mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>Convinced or supplied them, cannot choose</LINE>
<LINE>But they must blab--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath he said any thing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He hath, my lord; but be you well assured,</LINE>
<LINE>No more than he'll unswear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What hath he said?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, that he did--I know not what he did.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What? what?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lie--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With her?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With her, on her; what you will.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lie with her! lie on her! We say lie on her, when</LINE>
<LINE>they belie her. Lie with her! that's fulsome.</LINE>
<LINE>--Handkerchief--confessions--handkerchief!--To</LINE>
<LINE>confess, and be hanged for his labour;--first, to be</LINE>
<LINE>hanged, and then to confess.--I tremble at it.</LINE>
<LINE>Nature would not invest herself in such shadowing</LINE>
<LINE>passion without some instruction. It is not words</LINE>
<LINE>that shake me thus. Pish! Noses, ears, and lips.</LINE>
<LINE>--Is't possible?--Confess--handkerchief!--O devil!--</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Falls in a trance</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Work on,</LINE>
<LINE>My medicine, work! Thus credulous fools are caught;</LINE>
<LINE>And many worthy and chaste dames even thus,</LINE>
<LINE>All guiltless, meet reproach. What, ho! my lord!</LINE>
<LINE>My lord, I say! Othello!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now, Cassio!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord is fall'n into an epilepsy:</LINE>
<LINE>This is his second fit; he had one yesterday.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Rub him about the temples.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, forbear;</LINE>
<LINE>The lethargy must have his quiet course:</LINE>
<LINE>If not, he foams at mouth and by and by</LINE>
<LINE>Breaks out to savage madness. Look he stirs:</LINE>
<LINE>Do you withdraw yourself a little while,</LINE>
<LINE>He will recover straight: when he is gone,</LINE>
<LINE>I would on great occasion speak with you.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit CASSIO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How is it, general? have you not hurt your head?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost thou mock me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I mock you! no, by heaven.</LINE>
<LINE>Would you would bear your fortune like a man!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A horned man's a monster and a beast.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There's many a beast then in a populous city,</LINE>
<LINE>And many a civil monster.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did he confess it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good sir, be a man;</LINE>
<LINE>Think every bearded fellow that's but yoked</LINE>
<LINE>May draw with you: there's millions now alive</LINE>
<LINE>That nightly lie in those unproper beds</LINE>
<LINE>Which they dare swear peculiar: your case is better.</LINE>
<LINE>O, 'tis the spite of hell, the fiend's arch-mock,</LINE>
<LINE>To lip a wanton in a secure couch,</LINE>
<LINE>And to suppose her chaste! No, let me know;</LINE>
<LINE>And knowing what I am, I know what she shall be.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, thou art wise; 'tis certain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Stand you awhile apart;</LINE>
<LINE>Confine yourself but in a patient list.</LINE>
<LINE>Whilst you were here o'erwhelmed with your grief--</LINE>
<LINE>A passion most unsuiting such a man--</LINE>
<LINE>Cassio came hither: I shifted him away,</LINE>
<LINE>And laid good 'scuse upon your ecstasy,</LINE>
<LINE>Bade him anon return and here speak with me;</LINE>
<LINE>The which he promised. Do but encave yourself,</LINE>
<LINE>And mark the fleers, the gibes, and notable scorns,</LINE>
<LINE>That dwell in every region of his face;</LINE>
<LINE>For I will make him tell the tale anew,</LINE>
<LINE>Where, how, how oft, how long ago, and when</LINE>
<LINE>He hath, and is again to cope your wife:</LINE>
<LINE>I say, but mark his gesture. Marry, patience;</LINE>
<LINE>Or I shall say you are all in all in spleen,</LINE>
<LINE>And nothing of a man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dost thou hear, Iago?</LINE>
<LINE>I will be found most cunning in my patience;</LINE>
<LINE>But--dost thou hear?--most bloody.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's not amiss;</LINE>
<LINE>But yet keep time in all. Will you withdraw?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>OTHELLO retires</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Now will I question Cassio of Bianca,</LINE>
<LINE>A housewife that by selling her desires</LINE>
<LINE>Buys herself bread and clothes: it is a creature</LINE>
<LINE>That dotes on Cassio; as 'tis the strumpet's plague</LINE>
<LINE>To beguile many and be beguiled by one:</LINE>
<LINE>He, when he hears of her, cannot refrain</LINE>
<LINE>From the excess of laughter. Here he comes:</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter CASSIO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>As he shall smile, Othello shall go mad;</LINE>
<LINE>And his unbookish jealousy must construe</LINE>
<LINE>Poor Cassio's smiles, gestures and light behavior,</LINE>
<LINE>Quite in the wrong. How do you now, lieutenant?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The worser that you give me the addition</LINE>
<LINE>Whose want even kills me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ply Desdemona well, and you are sure on't.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Speaking lower</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Now, if this suit lay in Bianco's power,</LINE>
<LINE>How quickly should you speed!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, poor caitiff!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look, how he laughs already!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I never knew woman love man so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, poor rogue! I think, i' faith, she loves me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now he denies it faintly, and laughs it out.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you hear, Cassio?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now he importunes him</LINE>
<LINE>To tell it o'er: go to; well said, well said.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She gives it out that you shall marry hey:</LINE>
<LINE>Do you intend it?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha, ha, ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do you triumph, Roman? do you triumph?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I marry her! what? a customer! Prithee, bear some</LINE>
<LINE>charity to my wit: do not think it so unwholesome.</LINE>
<LINE>Ha, ha, ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So, so, so, so: they laugh that win.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, the cry goes that you shall marry her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, say true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am a very villain else.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you scored me? Well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is the monkey's own giving out: she is</LINE>
<LINE>persuaded I will marry her, out of her own love and</LINE>
<LINE>flattery, not out of my promise.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Iago beckons me; now he begins the story.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She was here even now; she haunts me in every place.</LINE>
<LINE>I was the other day talking on the sea-bank with</LINE>
<LINE>certain Venetians; and thither comes the bauble,</LINE>
<LINE>and, by this hand, she falls me thus about my neck--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Crying 'O dear Cassio!' as it were: his gesture</LINE>
<LINE>imports it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So hangs, and lolls, and weeps upon me; so hales,</LINE>
<LINE>and pulls me: ha, ha, ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now he tells how she plucked him to my chamber. O,</LINE>
<LINE>I see that nose of yours, but not that dog I shall</LINE>
<LINE>throw it to.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, I must leave her company.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Before me! look, where she comes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis such another fitchew! marry a perfumed one.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter BIANCA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What do you mean by this haunting of me?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let the devil and his dam haunt you! What did you</LINE>
<LINE>mean by that same handkerchief you gave me even now?</LINE>
<LINE>I was a fine fool to take it. I must take out the</LINE>
<LINE>work?--A likely piece of work, that you should find</LINE>
<LINE>it in your chamber, and not know who left it there!</LINE>
<LINE>This is some minx's token, and I must take out the</LINE>
<LINE>work? There; give it your hobby-horse: wheresoever</LINE>
<LINE>you had it, I'll take out no work on't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How now, my sweet Bianca! how now! how now!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By heaven, that should be my handkerchief!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>An you'll come to supper to-night, you may; an you</LINE>
<LINE>will not, come when you are next prepared for.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>After her, after her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, I must; she'll rail in the street else.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you sup there?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, I intend so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, I may chance to see you; for I would very fain</LINE>
<LINE>speak with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Prithee, come; will you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Go to; say no more.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit CASSIO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Advancing</STAGEDIR>  How shall I murder him, Iago?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did you perceive how he laughed at his vice?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Iago!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And did you see the handkerchief?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Was that mine?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yours by this hand: and to see how he prizes the</LINE>
<LINE>foolish woman your wife! she gave it him, and he</LINE>
<LINE>hath given it his whore.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would have him nine years a-killing.</LINE>
<LINE>A fine woman! a fair woman! a sweet woman!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, you must forget that.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, let her rot, and perish, and be damned to-night;</LINE>
<LINE>for she shall not live: no, my heart is turned to</LINE>
<LINE>stone; I strike it, and it hurts my hand. O, the</LINE>
<LINE>world hath not a sweeter creature: she might lie by</LINE>
<LINE>an emperor's side and command him tasks.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, that's not your way.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hang her! I do but say what she is: so delicate</LINE>
<LINE>with her needle: an admirable musician: O! she</LINE>
<LINE>will sing the savageness out of a bear: of so high</LINE>
<LINE>and plenteous wit and invention:--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She's the worse for all this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, a thousand thousand times: and then, of so</LINE>
<LINE>gentle a condition!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, too gentle.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, that's certain: but yet the pity of it, Iago!</LINE>
<LINE>O Iago, the pity of it, Iago!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you are so fond over her iniquity, give her</LINE>
<LINE>patent to offend; for, if it touch not you, it comes</LINE>
<LINE>near nobody.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will chop her into messes: cuckold me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, 'tis foul in her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With mine officer!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's fouler.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get me some poison, Iago; this night: I'll not</LINE>
<LINE>expostulate with her, lest her body and beauty</LINE>
<LINE>unprovide my mind again: this night, Iago.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do it not with poison, strangle her in her bed, even</LINE>
<LINE>the bed she hath contaminated.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good, good: the justice of it pleases: very good.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And for Cassio, let me be his undertaker: you</LINE>
<LINE>shall hear more by midnight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Excellent good.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>A trumpet within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What trumpet is that same?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Something from Venice, sure. 'Tis Lodovico</LINE>
<LINE>Come from the duke: and, see, your wife is with him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter LODOVICO, DESDEMONA, and Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Save you, worthy general!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With all my heart, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The duke and senators of Venice greet you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Gives him a letter</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I kiss the instrument of their pleasures.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Opens the letter, and reads</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And what's the news, good cousin Lodovico?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am very glad to see you, signior</LINE>
<LINE>Welcome to Cyprus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I thank you. How does Lieutenant Cassio?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lives, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cousin, there's fall'n between him and my lord</LINE>
<LINE>An unkind breach: but you shall make all well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you sure of that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Reads</STAGEDIR>  'This fail you not to do, as you will--'</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He did not call; he's busy in the paper.</LINE>
<LINE>Is there division 'twixt my lord and Cassio?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A most unhappy one: I would do much</LINE>
<LINE>To atone them, for the love I bear to Cassio.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fire and brimstone!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you wise?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, is he angry?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>May be the letter moved him;</LINE>
<LINE>For, as I think, they do command him home,</LINE>
<LINE>Deputing Cassio in his government.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Trust me, I am glad on't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Indeed!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad to see you mad.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, sweet Othello,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Striking her</STAGEDIR>  Devil!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have not deserved this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, this would not be believed in Venice,</LINE>
<LINE>Though I should swear I saw't: 'tis very much:</LINE>
<LINE>Make her amends; she weeps.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O devil, devil!</LINE>
<LINE>If that the earth could teem with woman's tears,</LINE>
<LINE>Each drop she falls would prove a crocodile.</LINE>
<LINE>Out of my sight!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not stay to offend you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Going</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Truly, an obedient lady:</LINE>
<LINE>I do beseech your lordship, call her back.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Mistress!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What would you with her, sir?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who, I, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay; you did wish that I would make her turn:</LINE>
<LINE>Sir, she can turn, and turn, and yet go on,</LINE>
<LINE>And turn again; and she can weep, sir, weep;</LINE>
<LINE>And she's obedient, as you say, obedient,</LINE>
<LINE>Very obedient. Proceed you in your tears.</LINE>
<LINE>Concerning this, sir,--O  well-painted passion!--</LINE>
<LINE>I am commanded home. Get you away;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll send for you anon. Sir, I obey the mandate,</LINE>
<LINE>And will return to Venice. Hence, avaunt!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit DESDEMONA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Cassio shall have my place. And, sir, tonight,</LINE>
<LINE>I do entreat that we may sup together:</LINE>
<LINE>You are welcome, sir, to Cyprus.--Goats and monkeys!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is this the noble Moor whom our full senate</LINE>
<LINE>Call all in all sufficient? Is this the nature</LINE>
<LINE>Whom passion could not shake? whose solid virtue</LINE>
<LINE>The shot of accident, nor dart of chance,</LINE>
<LINE>Could neither graze nor pierce?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He is much changed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are his wits safe? is he not light of brain?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's that he is: I may not breathe my censure</LINE>
<LINE>What he might be: if what he might he is not,</LINE>
<LINE>I would to heaven he were!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, strike his wife!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, that was not so well; yet would I knew</LINE>
<LINE>That stroke would prove the worst!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is it his use?</LINE>
<LINE>Or did the letters work upon his blood,</LINE>
<LINE>And new-create this fault?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, alas!</LINE>
<LINE>It is not honesty in me to speak</LINE>
<LINE>What I have seen and known. You shall observe him,</LINE>
<LINE>And his own courses will denote him so</LINE>
<LINE>That I may save my speech: do but go after,</LINE>
<LINE>And mark how he continues.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am sorry that I am deceived in him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  A room in the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO and EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have seen nothing then?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor ever heard, nor ever did suspect.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, you have seen Cassio and she together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But then I saw no harm, and then I heard</LINE>
<LINE>Each syllable that breath made up between them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, did they never whisper?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor send you out o' the way?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To fetch her fan, her gloves, her mask, nor nothing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Never, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's strange.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I durst, my lord, to wager she is honest,</LINE>
<LINE>Lay down my soul at stake: if you think other,</LINE>
<LINE>Remove your thought; it doth abuse your bosom.</LINE>
<LINE>If any wretch have put this in your head,</LINE>
<LINE>Let heaven requite it with the serpent's curse!</LINE>
<LINE>For, if she be not honest, chaste, and true,</LINE>
<LINE>There's no man happy; the purest of their wives</LINE>
<LINE>Is foul as slander.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Bid her come hither: go.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exit EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>She says enough; yet she's a simple bawd</LINE>
<LINE>That cannot say as much. This is a subtle whore,</LINE>
<LINE>A closet lock and key of villanous secrets</LINE>
<LINE>And yet she'll kneel and pray; I have seen her do't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter DESDEMONA with EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord, what is your will?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Pray, chuck, come hither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is your pleasure?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Let me see your eyes;</LINE>
<LINE>Look in my face.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What horrible fancy's this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To EMILIA</STAGEDIR>  Some of your function, mistress;</LINE>
<LINE>Leave procreants alone and shut the door;</LINE>
<LINE>Cough, or cry 'hem,' if any body come:</LINE>
<LINE>Your mystery, your mystery: nay, dispatch.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Upon my knees, what doth your speech import?</LINE>
<LINE>I understand a fury in your words.</LINE>
<LINE>But not the words.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, what art thou?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your wife, my lord; your true</LINE>
<LINE>And loyal wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, swear it, damn thyself</LINE>
<LINE>Lest, being like one of heaven, the devils themselves</LINE>
<LINE>Should fear to seize thee: therefore be double damn'd:</LINE>
<LINE>Swear thou art honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Heaven doth truly know it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Heaven truly knows that thou art false as hell.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>To whom, my lord? with whom? how am I false?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O Desdemona! away! away! away!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas the heavy day! Why do you weep?</LINE>
<LINE>Am I the motive of these tears, my lord?</LINE>
<LINE>If haply you my father do suspect</LINE>
<LINE>An instrument of this your calling back,</LINE>
<LINE>Lay not your blame on me: If you have lost him,</LINE>
<LINE>Why, I have lost him too.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Had it pleased heaven</LINE>
<LINE>To try me with affliction; had they rain'd</LINE>
<LINE>All kinds of sores and shames on my bare head.</LINE>
<LINE>Steep'd me in poverty to the very lips,</LINE>
<LINE>Given to captivity me and my utmost hopes,</LINE>
<LINE>I should have found in some place of my soul</LINE>
<LINE>A drop of patience: but, alas, to make me</LINE>
<LINE>A fixed figure for the time of scorn</LINE>
<LINE>To point his slow unmoving finger at!</LINE>
<LINE>Yet could I bear that too; well, very well:</LINE>
<LINE>But there, where I have garner'd up my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>Where either I must live, or bear no life;</LINE>
<LINE>The fountain from the which my current runs,</LINE>
<LINE>Or else dries up; to be discarded thence!</LINE>
<LINE>Or keep it as a cistern for foul toads</LINE>
<LINE>To knot and gender in! Turn thy complexion there,</LINE>
<LINE>Patience, thou young and rose-lipp'd cherubin,--</LINE>
<LINE>Ay, there, look grim as hell!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I hope my noble lord esteems me honest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, ay; as summer flies are in the shambles,</LINE>
<LINE>That quicken even with blowing. O thou weed,</LINE>
<LINE>Who art so lovely fair and smell'st so sweet</LINE>
<LINE>That the sense aches at thee, would thou hadst</LINE>
<LINE>ne'er been born!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, what ignorant sin have I committed?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Was this fair paper, this most goodly book,</LINE>
<LINE>Made to write 'whore' upon? What committed!</LINE>
<LINE>Committed! O thou public commoner!</LINE>
<LINE>I should make very forges of my cheeks,</LINE>
<LINE>That would to cinders burn up modesty,</LINE>
<LINE>Did I but speak thy deeds. What committed!</LINE>
<LINE>Heaven stops the nose at it and the moon winks,</LINE>
<LINE>The bawdy wind that kisses all it meets</LINE>
<LINE>Is hush'd within the hollow mine of earth,</LINE>
<LINE>And will not hear it. What committed!</LINE>
<LINE>Impudent strumpet!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By heaven, you do me wrong.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are you not a strumpet?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, as I am a Christian:</LINE>
<LINE>If to preserve this vessel for my lord</LINE>
<LINE>From any other foul unlawful touch</LINE>
<LINE>Be not to be a strumpet, I am none.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, not a whore?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, as I shall be saved.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is't possible?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, heaven forgive us!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cry you mercy, then:</LINE>
<LINE>I took you for that cunning whore of Venice</LINE>
<LINE>That married with Othello.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Raising his voice</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>You, mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>That have the office opposite to Saint Peter,</LINE>
<LINE>And keep the gate of hell!</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Re-enter EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>You, you, ay, you!</LINE>
<LINE>We have done our course; there's money for your pains:</LINE>
<LINE>I pray you, turn the key and keep our counsel.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, what does this gentleman conceive?</LINE>
<LINE>How do you, madam? how do you, my good lady?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, half asleep.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good madam, what's the matter with my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With who?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, with my lord, madam.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who is thy lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He that is yours, sweet lady.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have none: do not talk to me, Emilia;</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot weep; nor answer have I none,</LINE>
<LINE>But what should go by water. Prithee, tonight</LINE>
<LINE>Lay on my bed my wedding sheets: remember;</LINE>
<LINE>And call thy husband hither.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here's a change indeed!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis meet I should be used so, very meet.</LINE>
<LINE>How have I been behaved, that he might stick</LINE>
<LINE>The small'st opinion on my least misuse?</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter EMILIA with IAGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is your pleasure, madam?</LINE>
<LINE>How is't with you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cannot tell. Those that do teach young babes</LINE>
<LINE>Do it with gentle means and easy tasks:</LINE>
<LINE>He might have chid me so; for, in good faith,</LINE>
<LINE>I am a child to chiding.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter, lady?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, Iago, my lord hath so bewhored her.</LINE>
<LINE>Thrown such despite and heavy terms upon her,</LINE>
<LINE>As true hearts cannot bear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Am I that name, Iago?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What name, fair lady?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Such as she says my lord did say I was.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He call'd her whore: a beggar in his drink</LINE>
<LINE>Could not have laid such terms upon his callat.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why did he so?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not know; I am sure I am none such.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do not weep, do not weep. Alas the day!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hath she forsook so many noble matches,</LINE>
<LINE>Her father and her country and her friends,</LINE>
<LINE>To be call'd whore? would it not make one weep?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is my wretched fortune.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beshrew him for't!</LINE>
<LINE>How comes this trick upon him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, heaven doth know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will be hang'd, if some eternal villain,</LINE>
<LINE>Some busy and insinuating rogue,</LINE>
<LINE>Some cogging, cozening slave, to get some office,</LINE>
<LINE>Have not devised this slander; I'll be hang'd else.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fie, there is no such man; it is impossible.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If any such there be, heaven pardon him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A halter pardon him! and hell gnaw his bones!</LINE>
<LINE>Why should he call her whore? who keeps her company?</LINE>
<LINE>What place? what time? what form? what likelihood?</LINE>
<LINE>The Moor's abused by some most villanous knave,</LINE>
<LINE>Some base notorious knave, some scurvy fellow.</LINE>
<LINE>O heaven, that such companions thou'ldst unfold,</LINE>
<LINE>And put in every honest hand a whip</LINE>
<LINE>To lash the rascals naked through the world</LINE>
<LINE>Even from the east to the west!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Speak within door.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, fie upon them! Some such squire he was</LINE>
<LINE>That turn'd your wit the seamy side without,</LINE>
<LINE>And made you to suspect me with the Moor.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You are a fool; go to.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O good Iago,</LINE>
<LINE>What shall I do to win my lord again?</LINE>
<LINE>Good friend, go to him; for, by this light of heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>I know not how I lost him. Here I kneel:</LINE>
<LINE>If e'er my will did trespass 'gainst his love,</LINE>
<LINE>Either in discourse of thought or actual deed,</LINE>
<LINE>Or that mine eyes, mine ears, or any sense,</LINE>
<LINE>Delighted them in any other form;</LINE>
<LINE>Or that I do not yet, and ever did.</LINE>
<LINE>And ever will--though he do shake me off</LINE>
<LINE>To beggarly divorcement--love him dearly,</LINE>
<LINE>Comfort forswear me! Unkindness may do much;</LINE>
<LINE>And his unkindness may defeat my life,</LINE>
<LINE>But never taint my love. I cannot say 'whore:'</LINE>
<LINE>It does abhor me now I speak the word;</LINE>
<LINE>To do the act that might the addition earn</LINE>
<LINE>Not the world's mass of vanity could make me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I pray you, be content; 'tis but his humour:</LINE>
<LINE>The business of the state does him offence,</LINE>
<LINE>And he does chide with you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If 'twere no other--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis but so, I warrant.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Trumpets within</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Hark, how these instruments summon to supper!</LINE>
<LINE>The messengers of Venice stay the meat;</LINE>
<LINE>Go in, and weep not; all things shall be well.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Exeunt DESDEMONA and EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>How now, Roderigo!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not find that thou dealest justly with me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What in the contrary?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Every day thou daffest me with some device, Iago;</LINE>
<LINE>and rather, as it seems to me now, keepest from me</LINE>
<LINE>all conveniency than suppliest me with the least</LINE>
<LINE>advantage of hope. I will indeed no longer endure</LINE>
<LINE>it, nor am I yet persuaded to put up in peace what</LINE>
<LINE>already I have foolishly suffered.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you hear me, Roderigo?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Faith, I have heard too much, for your words and</LINE>
<LINE>performances are no kin together.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You charge me most unjustly.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With nought but truth. I have wasted myself out of</LINE>
<LINE>my means. The jewels you have had from me to</LINE>
<LINE>deliver to Desdemona would half have corrupted a</LINE>
<LINE>votarist: you have told me she hath received them</LINE>
<LINE>and returned me expectations and comforts of sudden</LINE>
<LINE>respect and acquaintance, but I find none.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well; go to; very well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Very well! go to! I cannot go to, man; nor 'tis</LINE>
<LINE>not very well: nay, I think it is scurvy, and begin</LINE>
<LINE>to find myself fobbed in it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Very well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I tell you 'tis not very well. I will make myself</LINE>
<LINE>known to Desdemona: if she will return me my</LINE>
<LINE>jewels, I will give over my suit and repent my</LINE>
<LINE>unlawful solicitation; if not, assure yourself I</LINE>
<LINE>will seek satisfaction of you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You have said now.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and said nothing but what I protest intendment of doing.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, now I see there's mettle in thee, and even from</LINE>
<LINE>this instant to build on thee a better opinion than</LINE>
<LINE>ever before. Give me thy hand, Roderigo: thou hast</LINE>
<LINE>taken against me a most just exception; but yet, I</LINE>
<LINE>protest, I have dealt most directly in thy affair.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It hath not appeared.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I grant indeed it hath not appeared, and your</LINE>
<LINE>suspicion is not without wit and judgment. But,</LINE>
<LINE>Roderigo, if thou hast that in thee indeed, which I</LINE>
<LINE>have greater reason to believe now than ever, I mean</LINE>
<LINE>purpose, courage and valour, this night show it: if</LINE>
<LINE>thou the next night following enjoy not Desdemona,</LINE>
<LINE>take me from this world with treachery and devise</LINE>
<LINE>engines for my life.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, what is it? is it within reason and compass?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, there is especial commission come from Venice</LINE>
<LINE>to depute Cassio in Othello's place.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Is that true? why, then Othello and Desdemona</LINE>
<LINE>return again to Venice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, no; he goes into Mauritania and takes away with</LINE>
<LINE>him the fair Desdemona, unless his abode be</LINE>
<LINE>lingered here by some accident: wherein none can be</LINE>
<LINE>so determinate as the removing of Cassio.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How do you mean, removing of him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, by making him uncapable of Othello's place;</LINE>
<LINE>knocking out his brains.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And that you would have me to do?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, if you dare do yourself a profit and a right.</LINE>
<LINE>He sups to-night with a harlotry, and thither will I</LINE>
<LINE>go to him: he knows not yet of his horrorable</LINE>
<LINE>fortune. If you will watch his going thence, which</LINE>
<LINE>I will fashion to fall out between twelve and one,</LINE>
<LINE>you may take him at your pleasure: I will be near</LINE>
<LINE>to second your attempt, and he shall fall between</LINE>
<LINE>us. Come, stand not amazed at it, but go along with</LINE>
<LINE>me; I will show you such a necessity in his death</LINE>
<LINE>that you shall think yourself bound to put it on</LINE>
<LINE>him. It is now high suppertime, and the night grows</LINE>
<LINE>to waste: about it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will hear further reason for this.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And you shall be satisfied.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE III.  Another room In the castle.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO, LODOVICO, DESDEMONA, EMILIA and
Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do beseech you, sir, trouble yourself no further.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, pardon me: 'twill do me good to walk.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Madam, good night; I humbly thank your ladyship.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Your honour is most welcome.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you walk, sir?</LINE>
<LINE>O,--Desdemona,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Get you to bed on the instant; I will be returned</LINE>
<LINE>forthwith: dismiss your attendant there: look it be done.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt OTHELLO, LODOVICO, and Attendants</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How goes it now? he looks gentler than he did.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He says he will return incontinent:</LINE>
<LINE>He hath commanded me to go to bed,</LINE>
<LINE>And bade me to dismiss you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dismiss me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It was his bidding: therefore, good Emilia,.</LINE>
<LINE>Give me my nightly wearing, and adieu:</LINE>
<LINE>We must not now displease him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I would you had never seen him!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>So would not I my love doth so approve him,</LINE>
<LINE>That even his stubbornness, his cheques, his frowns--</LINE>
<LINE>Prithee, unpin me,--have grace and favour in them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have laid those sheets you bade me on the bed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All's one. Good faith, how foolish are our minds!</LINE>
<LINE>If I do die before thee prithee, shroud me</LINE>
<LINE>In one of those same sheets.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, come you talk.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My mother had a maid call'd Barbara:</LINE>
<LINE>She was in love, and he she loved proved mad</LINE>
<LINE>And did forsake her: she had a song of 'willow;'</LINE>
<LINE>An old thing 'twas, but it express'd her fortune,</LINE>
<LINE>And she died singing it: that song to-night</LINE>
<LINE>Will not go from my mind; I have much to do,</LINE>
<LINE>But to go hang my head all at one side,</LINE>
<LINE>And sing it like poor Barbara. Prithee, dispatch.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Shall I go fetch your night-gown?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, unpin me here.</LINE>
<LINE>This Lodovico is a proper man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A very handsome man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He speaks well.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know a lady in Venice would have walked barefoot</LINE>
<LINE>to Palestine for a touch of his nether lip.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Singing</STAGEDIR>  The poor soul sat sighing by a sycamore tree,</LINE>
<LINE>Sing all a green willow:</LINE>
<LINE>Her hand on her bosom, her head on her knee,</LINE>
<LINE>Sing willow, willow, willow:</LINE>
<LINE>The fresh streams ran by her, and murmur'd her moans;</LINE>
<LINE>Sing willow, willow, willow;</LINE>
<LINE>Her salt tears fell from her, and soften'd the stones;</LINE>
<LINE>Lay by these:--</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Singing</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Sing willow, willow, willow;</LINE>
<LINE>Prithee, hie thee; he'll come anon:--</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Singing</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Sing all a green willow must be my garland.</LINE>
<LINE>Let nobody blame him; his scorn I approve,-</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, that's not next.--Hark! who is't that knocks?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It's the wind.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Singing</STAGEDIR>  I call'd my love false love; but what</LINE>
<LINE>said he then?</LINE>
<LINE>Sing willow, willow, willow:</LINE>
<LINE>If I court moe women, you'll couch with moe men!</LINE>
<LINE>So, get thee gone; good night Ate eyes do itch;</LINE>
<LINE>Doth that bode weeping?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis neither here nor there.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have heard it said so. O, these men, these men!</LINE>
<LINE>Dost thou in conscience think,--tell me, Emilia,--</LINE>
<LINE>That there be women do abuse their husbands</LINE>
<LINE>In such gross kind?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There be some such, no question.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wouldst thou do such a deed for all the world?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, would not you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, by this heavenly light!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nor I neither by this heavenly light;</LINE>
<LINE>I might do't as well i' the dark.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wouldst thou do such a deed for all the world?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The world's a huge thing: it is a great price.</LINE>
<LINE>For a small vice.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In troth, I think thou wouldst not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>In troth, I think I should; and undo't when I had</LINE>
<LINE>done. Marry, I would not do such a thing for a</LINE>
<LINE>joint-ring, nor for measures of lawn, nor for</LINE>
<LINE>gowns, petticoats, nor caps, nor any petty</LINE>
<LINE>exhibition; but for the whole world,--why, who would</LINE>
<LINE>not make her husband a cuckold to make him a</LINE>
<LINE>monarch? I should venture purgatory for't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Beshrew me, if I would do such a wrong</LINE>
<LINE>For the whole world.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why the wrong is but a wrong i' the world: and</LINE>
<LINE>having the world for your labour, tis a wrong in your</LINE>
<LINE>own world, and you might quickly make it right.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do not think there is any such woman.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, a dozen; and as many to the vantage as would</LINE>
<LINE>store the world they played for.</LINE>
<LINE>But I do think it is their husbands' faults</LINE>
<LINE>If wives do fall: say that they slack their duties,</LINE>
<LINE>And pour our treasures into foreign laps,</LINE>
<LINE>Or else break out in peevish jealousies,</LINE>
<LINE>Throwing restraint upon us; or say they strike us,</LINE>
<LINE>Or scant our former having in despite;</LINE>
<LINE>Why, we have galls, and though we have some grace,</LINE>
<LINE>Yet have we some revenge. Let husbands know</LINE>
<LINE>Their wives have sense like them: they see and smell</LINE>
<LINE>And have their palates both for sweet and sour,</LINE>
<LINE>As husbands have. What is it that they do</LINE>
<LINE>When they change us for others? Is it sport?</LINE>
<LINE>I think it is: and doth affection breed it?</LINE>
<LINE>I think it doth: is't frailty that thus errs?</LINE>
<LINE>It is so too: and have not we affections,</LINE>
<LINE>Desires for sport, and frailty, as men have?</LINE>
<LINE>Then let them use us well: else let them know,</LINE>
<LINE>The ills we do, their ills instruct us so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good night, good night: heaven me such uses send,</LINE>
<LINE>Not to pick bad from bad, but by bad mend!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

</ACT>

<ACT><TITLE>ACT V</TITLE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE I.  Cyprus. A street.</TITLE>
<STAGEDIR>Enter IAGO and RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, stand behind this bulk; straight will he come:</LINE>
<LINE>Wear thy good rapier bare, and put it home:</LINE>
<LINE>Quick, quick; fear nothing; I'll be at thy elbow:</LINE>
<LINE>It makes us, or it mars us; think on that,</LINE>
<LINE>And fix most firm thy resolution.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be near at hand; I may miscarry in't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, at thy hand: be bold, and take thy stand.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Retires</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have no great devotion to the deed;</LINE>
<LINE>And yet he hath given me satisfying reasons:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis but a man gone. Forth, my sword: he dies.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have rubb'd this young quat almost to the sense,</LINE>
<LINE>And he grows angry. Now, whether he kill Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>Or Cassio him, or each do kill the other,</LINE>
<LINE>Every way makes my gain: live Roderigo,</LINE>
<LINE>He calls me to a restitution large</LINE>
<LINE>Of gold and jewels that I bobb'd from him,</LINE>
<LINE>As gifts to Desdemona;</LINE>
<LINE>It must not be: if Cassio do remain,</LINE>
<LINE>He hath a daily beauty in his life</LINE>
<LINE>That makes me ugly; and, besides, the Moor</LINE>
<LINE>May unfold me to him; there stand I in much peril:</LINE>
<LINE>No, he must die. But so: I hear him coming.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter CASSIO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I know his gait, 'tis he.--Villain, thou diest!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Makes a pass at CASSIO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That thrust had been mine enemy indeed,</LINE>
<LINE>But that my coat is better than thou know'st</LINE>
<LINE>I will make proof of thine.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Draws, and wounds RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, I am slain!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>IAGO from behind wounds CASSIO in the leg, and exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am maim'd for ever. Help, ho! murder! murder!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Falls</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The voice of Cassio: Iago keeps his word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, villain that I am!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is even so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, help, ho! light! a surgeon!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis he:--O brave Iago, honest and just,</LINE>
<LINE>That hast such noble sense of thy friend's wrong!</LINE>
<LINE>Thou teachest me. Minion, your dear lies dead,</LINE>
<LINE>And your unblest fate hies: strumpet, I come.</LINE>
<LINE>Forth of my heart those charms, thine eyes, are blotted;</LINE>
<LINE>Thy bed, lust-stain'd, shall with lust's blood be spotted.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<STAGEDIR>Exit</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter LODOVICO and GRATIANO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, ho! no watch? no passage? murder! murder!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis some mischance; the cry is very direful.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, help!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hark!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O wretched villain!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Two or three groan: it is a heavy night:</LINE>
<LINE>These may be counterfeits: let's think't unsafe</LINE>
<LINE>To come in to the cry without more help.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nobody come? then shall I bleed to death.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hark!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter IAGO, with a light</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here's one comes in his shirt, with light and weapons.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who's there? whose noise is this that ones on murder?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>We do not know.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Did not you hear a cry?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Here, here! for heaven's sake, help me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is Othello's ancient, as I take it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The same indeed; a very valiant fellow.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What are you here that cry so grievously?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Iago? O, I am spoil'd, undone by villains!</LINE>
<LINE>Give me some help.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O me, lieutenant! what villains have done this?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I think that one of them is hereabout,</LINE>
<LINE>And cannot make away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O treacherous villains!</LINE>
<LINE>What are you there? come in, and give some help.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>To LODOVICO and GRATIANO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, help me here!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's one of them.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O murderous slave! O villain!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Stabs RODERIGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>RODERIGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O damn'd Iago! O inhuman dog!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kill men i' the dark!--Where be these bloody thieves?--</LINE>
<LINE>How silent is this town!--Ho! murder! murder!--</LINE>
<LINE>What may you be? are you of good or evil?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As you shall prove us, praise us.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Signior Lodovico?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He, sir.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I cry you mercy. Here's Cassio hurt by villains.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassio!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How is't, brother!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My leg is cut in two.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Marry, heaven forbid!</LINE>
<LINE>Light, gentlemen; I'll bind it with my shirt.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter BIANCA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter, ho? who is't that cried?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who is't that cried!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O my dear Cassio! my sweet Cassio! O Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>Cassio, Cassio!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O notable strumpet! Cassio, may you suspect</LINE>
<LINE>Who they should be that have thus many led you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am to find you thus: I have been to seek you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Lend me a garter. So. O, for a chair,</LINE>
<LINE>To bear him easily hence!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, he faints! O Cassio, Cassio, Cassio!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Gentlemen all, I do suspect this trash</LINE>
<LINE>To be a party in this injury.</LINE>
<LINE>Patience awhile, good Cassio. Come, come;</LINE>
<LINE>Lend me a light. Know we this face or no?</LINE>
<LINE>Alas my friend and my dear countryman</LINE>
<LINE>Roderigo! no:--yes, sure: O heaven! Roderigo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, of Venice?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Even he, sir; did you know him?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Know him! ay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Signior Gratiano? I cry you gentle pardon;</LINE>
<LINE>These bloody accidents must excuse my manners,</LINE>
<LINE>That so neglected you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am glad to see you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How do you, Cassio? O, a chair, a chair!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Roderigo!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He, he 'tis he.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>A chair brought in</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>O, that's well said; the chair!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Some good man bear him carefully from hence;</LINE>
<LINE>I'll fetch the general's surgeon.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To BIANCA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>For you, mistress,</LINE>
<LINE>Save you your labour. He that lies slain</LINE>
<LINE>here, Cassio,</LINE>
<LINE>Was my dear friend: what malice was between you?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>None in the world; nor do I know the man.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To BIANCA</STAGEDIR>  What, look you pale? O, bear him out</LINE>
<LINE>o' the air.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>CASSIO and RODERIGO are borne off</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Stay you, good gentlemen. Look you pale, mistress?</LINE>
<LINE>Do you perceive the gastness of her eye?</LINE>
<LINE>Nay, if you stare, we shall hear more anon.</LINE>
<LINE>Behold her well; I pray you, look upon her:</LINE>
<LINE>Do you see, gentlemen? nay, guiltiness will speak,</LINE>
<LINE>Though tongues were out of use.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Las, what's the matter? what's the matter, husband?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassio hath here been set on in the dark</LINE>
<LINE>By Roderigo and fellows that are scaped:</LINE>
<LINE>He's almost slain, and Roderigo dead.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, good gentleman! alas, good Cassio!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This is the fruit of whoring. Prithee, Emilia,</LINE>
<LINE>Go know of Cassio where he supp'd to-night.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>To BIANCA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What, do you shake at that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He supp'd at my house; but I therefore shake not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, did he so? I charge you, go with me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fie, fie upon thee, strumpet!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>BIANCA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am no strumpet; but of life as honest</LINE>
<LINE>As you that thus abuse me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>As I! foh! fie upon thee!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kind gentlemen, let's go see poor Cassio dress'd.</LINE>
<LINE>Come, mistress, you must tell's another tale.</LINE>
<LINE>Emilia run you to the citadel,</LINE>
<LINE>And tell my lord and lady what hath happ'd.</LINE>
<LINE>Will you go on? I pray.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Aside</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>This is the night</LINE>
<LINE>That either makes me or fordoes me quite.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>

<SCENE><TITLE>SCENE II.  A bedchamber in the castle: DESDEMONA in bed asleep; a light burning.</TITLE>

<STAGEDIR>Enter OTHELLO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is the cause, it is the cause, my soul,--</LINE>
<LINE>Let me not name it to you, you chaste stars!--</LINE>
<LINE>It is the cause. Yet I'll not shed her blood;</LINE>
<LINE>Nor scar that whiter skin of hers than snow,</LINE>
<LINE>And smooth as monumental alabaster.</LINE>
<LINE>Yet she must die, else she'll betray more men.</LINE>
<LINE>Put out the light, and then put out the light:</LINE>
<LINE>If I quench thee, thou flaming minister,</LINE>
<LINE>I can again thy former light restore,</LINE>
<LINE>Should I repent me: but once put out thy light,</LINE>
<LINE>Thou cunning'st pattern of excelling nature,</LINE>
<LINE>I know not where is that Promethean heat</LINE>
<LINE>That can thy light relume. When I have pluck'd the rose,</LINE>
<LINE>I cannot give it vital growth again.</LINE>
<LINE>It must needs wither: I'll smell it on the tree.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Kissing her</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Ah balmy breath, that dost almost persuade</LINE>
<LINE>Justice to break her sword! One more, one more.</LINE>
<LINE>Be thus when thou art dead, and I will kill thee,</LINE>
<LINE>And love thee after. One more, and this the last:</LINE>
<LINE>So sweet was ne'er so fatal. I must weep,</LINE>
<LINE>But they are cruel tears: this sorrow's heavenly;</LINE>
<LINE>It strikes where it doth love. She wakes.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who's there? Othello?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay. Desdemona.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Will you come to bed, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Have you pray'd to-night, Desdemona?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you bethink yourself of any crime</LINE>
<LINE>Unreconciled as yet to heaven and grace,</LINE>
<LINE>Solicit for it straight.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, my lord, what do you mean by that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, do it, and be brief; I will walk by:</LINE>
<LINE>I would not kill thy unprepared spirit;</LINE>
<LINE>No; heaven forfend! I would not kill thy soul.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Talk you of killing?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, I do.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then heaven</LINE>
<LINE>Have mercy on me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Amen, with all my heart!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If you say so, I hope you will not kill me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Hum!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And yet I fear you; for you are fatal then</LINE>
<LINE>When your eyes roll so: why I should fear I know not,</LINE>
<LINE>Since guiltiness I know not; but yet I feel I fear.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Think on thy sins.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>They are loves I bear to you.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, and for that thou diest.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That death's unnatural that kills for loving.</LINE>
<LINE>Alas, why gnaw you so your nether lip?</LINE>
<LINE>Some bloody passion shakes your very frame:</LINE>
<LINE>These are portents; but yet I hope, I hope,</LINE>
<LINE>They do not point on me.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, and be still!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will so. What's the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That handkerchief which I so loved and gave thee</LINE>
<LINE>Thou gavest to Cassio.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, by my life and soul!</LINE>
<LINE>Send for the man, and ask him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sweet soul, take heed,</LINE>
<LINE>Take heed of perjury; thou art on thy deathbed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, but not yet to die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes, presently:</LINE>
<LINE>Therefore confess thee freely of thy sin;</LINE>
<LINE>For to deny each article with oath</LINE>
<LINE>Cannot remove nor choke the strong conception</LINE>
<LINE>That I do groan withal. Thou art to die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Then Lord have mercy on me!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I say, amen.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And have you mercy too! I never did</LINE>
<LINE>Offend you in my life; never loved Cassio</LINE>
<LINE>But with such general warranty of heaven</LINE>
<LINE>As I might love: I never gave him token.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By heaven, I saw my handkerchief in's hand.</LINE>
<LINE>O perjured woman! thou dost stone my heart,</LINE>
<LINE>And makest me call what I intend to do</LINE>
<LINE>A murder, which I thought a sacrifice:</LINE>
<LINE>I saw the handkerchief.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He found it then;</LINE>
<LINE>I never gave it him: send for him hither;</LINE>
<LINE>Let him confess a truth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He hath confess'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, my lord?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That he hath used thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>How? unlawfully?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He will not say so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, his mouth is stopp'd;</LINE>
<LINE>Honest Iago hath ta'en order for't.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O! my fear interprets: what, is he dead?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Had all his hairs been lives, my great revenge</LINE>
<LINE>Had stomach for them all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas! he is betray'd and I undone.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Out, strumpet! weep'st thou for him to my face?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, banish me, my lord, but kill me not!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Down, strumpet!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Kill me to-morrow: let me live to-night!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, if you strive--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But half an hour!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Being done, there is no pause.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But while I say one prayer!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is too late.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>He stifles her</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  My lord, my lord! what, ho! my lord, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What noise is this? Not dead? not yet quite dead?</LINE>
<LINE>I that am cruel am yet merciful;</LINE>
<LINE>I would not have thee linger in thy pain: So, so.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  What, ho! my lord, my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Who's there?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  O, good my lord, I would speak a word with you!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Yes: 'tis Emilia. By and by. She's dead.</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis like she comes to speak of Cassio's death.--</LINE>
<LINE>The noise was here. Ha! no more moving?</LINE>
<LINE>Still as the grave. Shall she come in? were't good?--</LINE>
<LINE>I think she stirs again:--no. What's best to do?</LINE>
<LINE>If she come in, she'll sure speak to my wife:</LINE>
<LINE>My wife! my wife! what wife? I have no wife.</LINE>
<LINE>O insupportable! O heavy hour!</LINE>
<LINE>Methinks it should be now a huge eclipse</LINE>
<LINE>Of sun and moon, and that the affrighted globe</LINE>
<LINE>Should yawn at alteration.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  I do beseech you</LINE>
<LINE>That I may speak with you, O, good my lord!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I had forgot thee: O, come in, Emilia;</LINE>
<LINE>Soft; by and by. Let me the curtains draw.</LINE>
<LINE>Where art thou?</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Unlocks the door</STAGEDIR>
<STAGEDIR>Enter EMILIA</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>What's the matter with thee now?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, my good lord, yonder's foul murders done!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, now?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But now, my lord.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>It is the very error of the moon;</LINE>
<LINE>She comes more nearer earth than she was wont,</LINE>
<LINE>And makes men mad.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassio, my lord, hath kill'd a young Venetian</LINE>
<LINE>Call'd Roderigo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Roderigo kill'd!</LINE>
<LINE>And Cassio kill'd!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>No, Cassio is not kill'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Not Cassio kill'd! then murder's out of tune,</LINE>
<LINE>And sweet revenge grows harsh.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, falsely, falsely murder'd!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, what cry is that?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That! what?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Out, and alas! that was my lady's voice.</LINE>
<LINE>Help! help, ho! help! O lady, speak again!</LINE>
<LINE>Sweet Desdemona! O sweet mistress, speak!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>A guiltless death I die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, who hath done this deed?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>DESDEMONA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nobody; I myself. Farewell</LINE>
<LINE>Commend me to my kind lord: O, farewell!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Dies</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, how should she be murder'd?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Alas, who knows?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You heard her say herself, it was not I.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She said so: I must needs report the truth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She's, like a liar, gone to burning hell:</LINE>
<LINE>'Twas I that kill'd her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, the more angel she,</LINE>
<LINE>And you the blacker devil!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She turn'd to folly, and she was a whore.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou dost belie her, and thou art a devil.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She was false as water.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou art rash as fire, to say</LINE>
<LINE>That she was false: O, she was heavenly true!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Cassio did top her; ask thy husband else.</LINE>
<LINE>O, I were damn'd beneath all depth in hell,</LINE>
<LINE>But that I did proceed upon just grounds</LINE>
<LINE>To this extremity. Thy husband knew it all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My husband!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thy husband.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That she was false to wedlock?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, with Cassio. Nay, had she been true,</LINE>
<LINE>If heaven would make me such another world</LINE>
<LINE>Of one entire and Perfect chrysolite,</LINE>
<LINE>I'ld not have sold her for it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My husband!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, 'twas he that told me first:</LINE>
<LINE>An honest man he is, and hates the slime</LINE>
<LINE>That sticks on filthy deeds.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>My husband!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What needs this iteration, woman? I say thy husband.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O mistress, villany hath made mocks with love,</LINE>
<LINE>My husband say that she was false!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He, woman;</LINE>
<LINE>I say thy husband: dost understand the word?</LINE>
<LINE>My friend, thy husband, honest, honest Iago.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>If he say so, may his pernicious soul</LINE>
<LINE>Rot half a grain a day! he lies to the heart:</LINE>
<LINE>She was too fond of her most filthy bargain.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ha!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Do thy worst:</LINE>
<LINE>This deed of thine is no more worthy heaven</LINE>
<LINE>Than thou wast worthy her.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Peace, you were best.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Thou hast not half that power to do me harm</LINE>
<LINE>As I have to be hurt. O gull! O dolt!</LINE>
<LINE>As ignorant as dirt! thou hast done a deed--</LINE>
<LINE>I care not for thy sword; I'll make thee known,</LINE>
<LINE>Though I lost twenty lives.--Help! help, ho! help!</LINE>
<LINE>The Moor hath kill'd my mistress! Murder! murder!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter MONTANO, GRATIANO, IAGO, and others</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter? How now, general!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O, are you come, Iago? you have done well,</LINE>
<LINE>That men must lay their murders on your neck.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Disprove this villain, if thou be'st a man:</LINE>
<LINE>He says thou told'st him that his wife was false:</LINE>
<LINE>I know thou didst not, thou'rt not such a villain:</LINE>
<LINE>Speak, for my heart is full.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I told him what I thought, and told no more</LINE>
<LINE>Than what he found himself was apt and true.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>But did you ever tell him she was false?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I did.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You told a lie, an odious, damned lie;</LINE>
<LINE>Upon my soul, a lie, a wicked lie.</LINE>
<LINE>She false with Cassio!--did you say with Cassio?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>With Cassio, mistress. Go to, charm your tongue.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not charm my tongue; I am bound to speak:</LINE>
<LINE>My mistress here lies murder'd in her bed,--</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O heavens forfend!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>And your reports have set the murder on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, stare not, masters: it is true, indeed.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis a strange truth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O monstrous act!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Villany, villany, villany!</LINE>
<LINE>I think upon't, I think: I smell't: O villany!--</LINE>
<LINE>I thought so then:--I'll kill myself for grief:--</LINE>
<LINE>O villany, villany!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, are you mad? I charge you, get you home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Good gentlemen, let me have leave to speak:</LINE>
<LINE>'Tis proper I obey him, but not now.</LINE>
<LINE>Perchance, Iago, I will ne'er go home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O! O! O!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>He falls on the bed</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Nay, lay thee down and roar;</LINE>
<LINE>For thou hast kill'd the sweetest innocent</LINE>
<LINE>That e'er did lift up eye.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Rising</STAGEDIR>  O, she was foul!</LINE>
<LINE>I scarce did know you, uncle: there lies your niece,</LINE>
<LINE>Whose breath, indeed, these hands have newly stopp'd:</LINE>
<LINE>I know this act shows horrible and grim.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Poor Desdemona! I am glad thy father's dead:</LINE>
<LINE>Thy match was mortal to him, and pure grief</LINE>
<LINE>Shore his old thread in twain: did he live now,</LINE>
<LINE>This sight would make him do a desperate turn,</LINE>
<LINE>Yea, curse his better angel from his side,</LINE>
<LINE>And fall to reprobation.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis pitiful; but yet Iago knows</LINE>
<LINE>That she with Cassio hath the act of shame</LINE>
<LINE>A thousand times committed; Cassio confess'd it:</LINE>
<LINE>And she did gratify his amorous works</LINE>
<LINE>With that recognizance and pledge of love</LINE>
<LINE>Which I first gave her; I saw it in his hand:</LINE>
<LINE>It was a handkerchief, an antique token</LINE>
<LINE>My father gave my mother.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O heaven! O heavenly powers!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Come, hold your peace.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Twill out, 'twill out: I peace!</LINE>
<LINE>No, I will speak as liberal as the north:</LINE>
<LINE>Let heaven and men and devils, let them all,</LINE>
<LINE>All, all, cry shame against me, yet I'll speak.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Be wise, and get you home.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I will not.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>IAGO offers to stab EMILIA</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Fie!</LINE>
<LINE>Your sword upon a woman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O thou dull Moor! that handkerchief thou speak'st of</LINE>
<LINE>I found by fortune and did give my husband;</LINE>
<LINE>For often, with a solemn earnestness,</LINE>
<LINE>More than indeed belong'd to such a trifle,</LINE>
<LINE>He begg'd of me to steal it.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Villanous whore!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>She give it Cassio! no, alas! I found it,</LINE>
<LINE>And I did give't my husband.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Filth, thou liest!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>By heaven, I do not, I do not, gentlemen.</LINE>
<LINE>O murderous coxcomb! what should such a fool</LINE>
<LINE>Do with so good a woman?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Are there no stones in heaven</LINE>
<LINE>But what serve for the thunder?--Precious villain!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>He runs at IAGO  IAGO, from behind, stabs EMILIA, and exit</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>The woman falls; sure, he hath kill'd his wife.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay, ay: O, lay me by my mistress' side.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>He's gone, but his wife's kill'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>MONTANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>'Tis a notorious villain. Take you this weapon,</LINE>
<LINE>Which I have here recover'd from the Moor:</LINE>
<LINE>Come, guard the door without; let him not pass,</LINE>
<LINE>But kill him rather. I'll after that same villain,</LINE>
<LINE>For 'tis a damned slave.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt MONTANO and GRATIANO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not valiant neither,</LINE>
<LINE>But ever puny whipster gets my sword:</LINE>
<LINE>But why should honour outlive honesty?</LINE>
<LINE>Let it go all.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>EMILIA</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What did thy song bode, lady?</LINE>
<LINE>Hark, canst thou hear me? I will play the swan.</LINE>
<LINE>And die in music.</LINE>
<STAGEDIR>Singing</STAGEDIR>
<LINE>Willow, willow, willow,--</LINE>
<LINE>Moor, she was chaste; she loved thee, cruel Moor;</LINE>
<LINE>So come my soul to bliss, as I speak true;</LINE>
<LINE>So speaking as I think, I die, I die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Dies</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I have another weapon in this chamber;</LINE>
<LINE>It is a sword of Spain, the ice-brook's temper:--</LINE>
<LINE>O, here it is. Uncle, I must come forth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>Within</STAGEDIR>  If thou attempt it, it will cost thee dear:</LINE>
<LINE>Thou hast no weapon, and perforce must suffer.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Look in upon me then and speak with me,</LINE>
<LINE>Or, naked as I am, I will assault thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Re-enter GRATIANO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What is the matter?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Behold, I have a weapon;</LINE>
<LINE>A better never did itself sustain</LINE>
<LINE>Upon a soldier's thigh: I have seen the day,</LINE>
<LINE>That, with this little arm and this good sword,</LINE>
<LINE>I have made my way through more impediments</LINE>
<LINE>Than twenty times your stop: but, O vain boast!</LINE>
<LINE>Who can control his fate? 'tis not so now.</LINE>
<LINE>Be not afraid, though you do see me weapon'd;</LINE>
<LINE>Here is my journey's end, here is my butt,</LINE>
<LINE>And very sea-mark of my utmost sail.</LINE>
<LINE>Do you go back dismay'd? 'tis a lost fear;</LINE>
<LINE>Man but a rush against Othello's breast,</LINE>
<LINE>And he retires. Where should Othello go?</LINE>
<LINE>Now, how dost thou look now? O ill-starr'd wench!</LINE>
<LINE>Pale as thy smock! when we shall meet at compt,</LINE>
<LINE>This look of thine will hurl my soul from heaven,</LINE>
<LINE>And fiends will snatch at it. Cold, cold, my girl!</LINE>
<LINE>Even like thy chastity. O cursed slave!</LINE>
<LINE>Whip me, ye devils,</LINE>
<LINE>From the possession of this heavenly sight!</LINE>
<LINE>Blow me about in winds! roast me in sulphur!</LINE>
<LINE>Wash me in steep-down gulfs of liquid fire!</LINE>
<LINE>O Desdemona! Desdemona! dead!</LINE>
<LINE>Oh! Oh! Oh!</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Enter LODOVICO. MONTANO, CASSIO carried in a chair,
and Officers with IAGO, prisoner</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is this rash and most unfortunate man?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>That's he that was Othello: here I am.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Where is that viper? bring the villain forth.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I look down towards his feet; but that's a fable.</LINE>
<LINE>If that thou best a devil, I cannot kill thee.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Wounds IAGO</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Wrench his sword from him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I bleed, sir; but not kill'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I am not sorry neither: I'ld have thee live;</LINE>
<LINE>For, in my sense, 'tis happiness to die.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O thou Othello, thou wert once so good,</LINE>
<LINE>Fall'n in the practise of a damned slave,</LINE>
<LINE>What shall be said to thee?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Why, any thing:</LINE>
<LINE>An honourable murderer, if you will;</LINE>
<LINE>For nought I did in hate, but all in honour.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This wretch hath part confess'd his villany:</LINE>
<LINE>Did you and he consent in Cassio's death?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Ay.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Dear general, I never gave you cause.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I do believe it, and I ask your pardon.</LINE>
<LINE>Will you, I pray, demand that demi-devil</LINE>
<LINE>Why he hath thus ensnared my soul and body?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>IAGO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Demand me nothing: what you know, you know:</LINE>
<LINE>From this time forth I never will speak word.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>What, not to pray?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Torments will ope your lips.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Well, thou dost best.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Sir, you shall understand what hath befall'n,</LINE>
<LINE>Which, as I think, you know not. Here is a letter</LINE>
<LINE>Found in the pocket of the slain Roderigo;</LINE>
<LINE>And here another: the one of them imports</LINE>
<LINE>The death of Cassio to be undertook</LINE>
<LINE>By Roderigo.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O villain!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Most heathenish and most gross!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Now here's another discontented paper,</LINE>
<LINE>Found in his pocket too; and this, it seems,</LINE>
<LINE>Roderigo meant to have sent this damned villain;</LINE>
<LINE>But that belike Iago in the interim</LINE>
<LINE>Came in and satisfied him.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O the pernicious caitiff!</LINE>
<LINE>How came you, Cassio, by that handkerchief</LINE>
<LINE>That was my wife's?</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I found it in my chamber:</LINE>
<LINE>And he himself confess'd but even now</LINE>
<LINE>That there he dropp'd it for a special purpose</LINE>
<LINE>Which wrought to his desire.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O fool! fool! fool!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>There is besides in Roderigo's letter,</LINE>
<LINE>How he upbraids Iago, that he made him</LINE>
<LINE>Brave me upon the watch; whereon it came</LINE>
<LINE>That I was cast: and even but now he spake,</LINE>
<LINE>After long seeming dead, Iago hurt him,</LINE>
<LINE>Iago set him on.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>You must forsake this room, and go with us:</LINE>
<LINE>Your power and your command is taken off,</LINE>
<LINE>And Cassio rules in Cyprus. For this slave,</LINE>
<LINE>If there be any cunning cruelty</LINE>
<LINE>That can torment him much and hold him long,</LINE>
<LINE>It shall be his. You shall close prisoner rest,</LINE>
<LINE>Till that the nature of your fault be known</LINE>
<LINE>To the Venetian state. Come, bring him away.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>Soft you; a word or two before you go.</LINE>
<LINE>I have done the state some service, and they know't.</LINE>
<LINE>No more of that. I pray you, in your letters,</LINE>
<LINE>When you shall these unlucky deeds relate,</LINE>
<LINE>Speak of me as I am; nothing extenuate,</LINE>
<LINE>Nor set down aught in malice: then must you speak</LINE>
<LINE>Of one that loved not wisely but too well;</LINE>
<LINE>Of one not easily jealous, but being wrought</LINE>
<LINE>Perplex'd in the extreme; of one whose hand,</LINE>
<LINE>Like the base Indian, threw a pearl away</LINE>
<LINE>Richer than all his tribe; of one whose subdued eyes,</LINE>
<LINE>Albeit unused to the melting mood,</LINE>
<LINE>Drop tears as fast as the Arabian trees</LINE>
<LINE>Their medicinal gum. Set you down this;</LINE>
<LINE>And say besides, that in Aleppo once,</LINE>
<LINE>Where a malignant and a turban'd Turk</LINE>
<LINE>Beat a Venetian and traduced the state,</LINE>
<LINE>I took by the throat the circumcised dog,</LINE>
<LINE>And smote him, thus.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Stabs himself</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>O bloody period!</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>GRATIANO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>All that's spoke is marr'd.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>OTHELLO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>I kiss'd thee ere I kill'd thee: no way but this;</LINE>
<LINE>Killing myself, to die upon a kiss.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Falls on the bed, and dies</STAGEDIR>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>CASSIO</SPEAKER>
<LINE>This did I fear, but thought he had no weapon;</LINE>
<LINE>For he was great of heart.</LINE>
</SPEECH>

<SPEECH>
<SPEAKER>LODOVICO</SPEAKER>
<LINE><STAGEDIR>To IAGO</STAGEDIR>  O Spartan dog,</LINE>
<LINE>More fell than anguish, hunger, or the sea!</LINE>
<LINE>Look on the tragic loading of this bed;</LINE>
<LINE>This is thy work: the object poisons sight;</LINE>
<LINE>Let it be hid. Gratiano, keep the house,</LINE>
<LINE>And seize upon the fortunes of the Moor,</LINE>
<LINE>For they succeed on you. To you, lord governor,</LINE>
<LINE>Remains the censure of this hellish villain;</LINE>
<LINE>The time, the place, the torture: O, enforce it!</LINE>
<LINE>Myself will straight aboard: and to the state</LINE>
<LINE>This heavy act with heavy heart relate.</LINE>
</SPEECH>


<STAGEDIR>Exeunt</STAGEDIR>
</SCENE>
</ACT>
</PLAY>
